Ezekiel 29

1 In the tenth year, in the tenth month, on the eleventh day of the month, the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, set your face against Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and you shall prophesy about him and about all of Egypt.

3 Speak, and you shall say: Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I am against you, Pharaoh, king of Egypt, you great dragon, who rests in the midst of your rivers. And you say: 'Mine is the river, and I have made myself.'

4 But I will place a bridle in your jaws. And I will adhere the fish of your rivers to your scales. And I will draw you out of the midst of your rivers, and all your fish will adhere to your scales.

5 And I will cast you into the desert, with all the fish of your river. You will fall upon the surface of the earth; you will not be taken up, nor gathered together. I have given you to the beasts of the earth and to the birds of the air, to be devoured.

6 And all the inhabitants of Egypt shall know that I am the Lord. For you have been a staff made of reed to the house of Israel.

7 When they took hold of you with the hand, you broke, and so you wounded all of their shoulders. And when they leaned on you, you shattered, and so you injured all of their lower backs.

8 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will lead the sword over you, and I will destroy both man and beast from among you.

9 And the land of Egypt will be a desert and a wilderness. And they shall know that I am the Lord. For you have said, 'The river is mine, and I have made it.'

10 Therefore, behold, I am against you and against your rivers. And I will make the land of Egypt into a wilderness, destroyed by the sword from the tower of Syene all the way to the borders of Ethiopia.

11 The foot of man will not pass through it, and the foot of cattle will not walk in it. And it will be uninhabited for forty years.

12 And I will set the land of Egypt in desolation, in the midst of desolate lands, and its cities in the midst of overturned cites. And they will be desolate for forty years. And I will scatter the Egyptians among the nations, and I will disperse them among the lands.

13 For thus says the Lord God: After the end of forty years, I will gather the Egyptians from the peoples among whom they had been scattered.

14 And I will lead back the captivity of Egypt, and I will collect them in the land of Pathros, in the land of their nativity. And in that place, they will be a lowly kingdom.

15 It will be the lowest among the other kingdoms, and it will no longer be exalted above the nations. And I will diminish them, lest they rule over the Gentiles.

16 And they will no longer be the confidence of the house of Israel, teaching iniquity, so that they may flee and follow them. And they shall know that I am the Lord God."

17 And it happened that, in the twenty-seventh year, in the first month, on the first of the month, the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

18 "Son of man, Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, has caused his army to serve with great servility against Tyre. Every head was shaven, and every shoulder was stripped of hair. And wages have not been paid to him, nor to his army, for Tyre, for the service by which he served for me against it.

19 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will station Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, in the land of Egypt. And he will take its multitude, and he will prey upon its profits, and he will plunder its spoils. And this shall be the wages for his army

20 and for the work by which he has served against it. I have given to him the land of Egypt, because he has labored for me, says the Lord God.

21 In that day, a horn will spring forth for the house of Israel, and I will give to you an open mouth in their midst. And they shall know that I am the Lord."

Ezekiel 30

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, prophesy and say: Thus says the Lord God: Wail: 'Woe, woe to the day!'

3 For the day is near, and the day of the Lord is approaching! It is a day of gloom; it will be the time of the Gentiles.

4 And the sword will come to Egypt. And there will be dread in Ethiopia, when the wounded will have fallen in Egypt, and its multitude will have been taken away, and its foundations will have been destroyed.

5 Ethiopia, and Libya, and Lydia, and all the rest of the common people, and Chub, and the sons of the land of the covenant, will fall with them by the sword.

6 Thus says the Lord God: And those who prop up Egypt will fall, and the arrogance of its reign will be brought down. They will fall in it by the sword, before the tower of Syene, says the Lord, the God of hosts.

7 And they will be scattered into the midst of desolate lands, and its cities will be in the midst of cities that have been deserted.

8 And they shall know that I am the Lord, when I will have brought a fire into Egypt, and when all its helpers will have been worn away.

9 In that day, messengers will go forth from my face in Greek warships, in order to crush the confidence of Ethiopia. And there will be dread among them in the day of Egypt; for without doubt, it will happen.

10 Thus says the Lord God: By the hand of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, I will cause the multitude of Egypt to cease.

11 He, and his people with him, the strongest of the Gentiles, will be brought forth in order to destroy the land. And they will draw their swords over Egypt. And they will fill the land with the slain.

12 And I will cause the channels of the rivers to dry up. And I will deliver the land into the hand of the most wicked. And by the hands of foreigners, I will utterly destroy the land and its plenitude. I, the Lord, have spoken.

13 Thus says the Lord God: And I will destroy the graven images, and I will cause the idols of Memphis to cease. And there will no longer be a commander of the land of Egypt. And I will send terror upon the land of Egypt.

14 And I will destroy the land of Pathros, and I will send a fire upon Tahpanhes, and I will execute judgments in Alexandria.

15 And I will pour out my indignation upon Pelusium, the strength of Egypt, and I will kill the multitude of Alexandria.

16 And I will send a fire upon Egypt. Pelusium will be in pain, like a woman giving birth. And Alexandria will be utterly destroyed. And in Memphis, there will be anguish every day.

17 The young men of Heliopolis and Pibeseth will fall by the sword, and the young women will be led into captivity.

18 And in Tahpanhes, the day will grow black, when, in that place, I will break the scepters of Egypt. And the arrogance of her authority will fail within her; a gloom will cover her. Then her daughters will be led into captivity.

19 And I will execute judgments in Egypt. And they shall know that I am the Lord."

20 And it happened that, in the eleventh year, in the first month, on the seventh of the month, the word of the Lord came, me, saying:

21 "Son of man, I have broken the arm of Pharaoh, the king of Egypt. And behold, it has not been wrapped, so that it might be restored to health; it has not been bound with cloths, or bandaged with linen, so that, having recovered strength, it would be able to hold the sword.

22 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Behold, I am against Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and I will shatter his strong arm, which has already been broken. And I will cast the sword away from his hand.

23 And I will disperse Egypt among the nations, and I will scatter them among the lands.

24 And I will strengthen the arms of the king of Babylon. And I will put my sword into his hand. And I will break the arms of Pharaoh. And they will groan acutely, when they are slain before his face.

25 And I will strengthen the arms of the king of Babylon. And the arms of Pharaoh will fall. And they shall know that I am the Lord, when I will have given my sword into the hand of the king of Babylon, and when he will have extended it over the land of Egypt.

26 And I will disperse Egypt among the nations, and I will scatter them among the lands. And they shall know that I am the Lord."

Ezekiel 31

1 And it happened that, in the eleventh year, in the third month, on the first of the month, the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, speak to Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and to his people: To whom can you be compared in your greatness?

3 Behold, Assur is like the cedar of Lebanon, with fair branches, and full of leaves, and of high stature, and his summit has been elevated above the thick branches.

4 The waters have nourished him. The abyss has exalted him. Its rivers have flowed around his roots, and it has sent forth its streams to all the trees of the regions.

5 Because of this, his height was exalted above all the trees of the regions, and his groves were multiplied, and his own branches were elevated, because of the many waters.

6 And when he had extended his shadow, all the birds of the air made their nests in his branches, and all the beasts of the forest conceived their young under his foliage, and an assembly of the many peoples lived under his shadow.

7 And he was most beautiful in his greatness and in the expansion of his groves. For his root was near many waters.

8 The cedars in the Paradise of God were not higher than he was. The spruce trees were not equal to his summit, and the plane trees were not equal to his fullness. No tree in the Paradise of God was similar to him or to his beauty.

9 For I made him beautiful, and dense with many branches. And all the trees of delight, which were in the Paradise of God, were jealous of him.

10 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Since he was sublime in height, and he made his summit green and dense, and his heart was exalted because of his height,

11 I have delivered him into the hands of the most powerful one among the Gentiles, so that he will deal with him. I have cast him out, in accord with his impiety.

12 And foreigners, and the most cruel among the nations, will cut him down. And they will cast him on the mountains. And his branches will fall in every steep valley, and his grove will be broken apart on every cliff of the earth. And all the peoples of the earth will withdraw from his shadow, and abandon him.

13 All the birds of the air lived upon his ruins, and all the beasts of the countryside were among his branches.

14 For this reason, none of the trees among the waters will exalt themselves because of their height, nor will they place their summits above the thick branches and foliage, nor will any of those that are irrigated stand out because of their height. For they have all been delivered unto death, to the lowest part of the earth, into the midst of the sons of men, those who descend into the pit.

15 Thus says the Lord God: In the day when he descended into hell, I led in grieving. I covered him with the abyss. And I held back its rivers, and I restrained the many waters. Lebanon was saddened over him, and all the trees of the field were struck together.

16 I shook the Gentiles with the sound of his ruin, when I led him down to hell, with those who were descending into the pit. And all the trees of delights, the finest and best in Lebanon, all that were irrigated with waters, were consoled in the deepest parts of the earth.

17 For they, too, will descend with him into hell, to those who have been slain by the sword. And the arm of each one will reside under his shadow, in the midst of the nations.

18 To whom can you be compared, O famous and sublime one, among the trees of pleasure? Behold, you have been brought down, with the trees of pleasure, to the lowest part of the earth. You will sleep in the midst of the uncircumcised, with those who have been slain by the sword. This is Pharaoh, and all his multitude, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 32

1 And it happened that, in the twelfth year, in the twelfth month, on the first of the month, the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, take up a lamentation over Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and you shall say to him: You are like the lion of the Gentiles, and like the dragon that is in the sea. And you brandished a horn among your rivers, and you disturbed the waters with your feet, and you trampled upon their rivers.

3 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: I will spread my net over you, with the multitude of many peoples, and I will draw you into my dragnet.

4 And I will throw you upon the land. I will cast you upon the surface of the field. And I will cause all the birds of the air to live upon you. And I will satiate the beasts of the entire earth with you.

5 And I will place your flesh upon the mountains. And I will fill up your hills with your decaying flesh.

6 And I will irrigate the earth with your rotting blood upon the mountains. And the valleys will be filled with you.

7 And I will cover heaven, when you will have been extinguished. And I will cause its stars to grow dark. I will shroud the sun with gloom, and the moon will not give her light.

8 I will cause all the lights of heaven to grieve over you. And I will bring darkness upon your land, says the Lord God, when your wounded will have fallen in the midst of the land, says the Lord God.

9 And I will provoke the heart of many peoples to anger, when I will have led in your destruction among the Gentiles, over the lands that you have not known.

10 And I will cause many peoples to be stupefied over you. And their kings will be afraid, with great horror, over you, when my sword will begin to fly above their faces. And suddenly, they will be struck with astonishment, each one concerning his own life, on the day of their ruination.

11 For thus says the Lord God: The sword of the king of Babylon will come to you.

12 By the swords of the strong, I will cast down your multitude. All these nations are invincible, and they will lay waste to the arrogance of Egypt, and so its multitude will be destroyed.

13 And I will perish all its cattle, which were above the many waters. And the foot of man will no longer disturb them, and the hoof of cattle will no longer trouble them.

14 Then I will cause their waters to be very pure, and their rivers to be like oil, says the Lord God,

15 when I will have set the land of Egypt in desolation. And the land will be deprived of her plenitude, when I will have struck all its inhabitants. And they shall know that I am the Lord.

16 This is the lamentation. And they shall lament it. The daughters of the Gentiles shall lament it. They shall lament it over Egypt and over its multitude, says the Lord God."

17 And it happened that, in the twelfth year, on the fifteenth of the month, the word of the Lord came to me saying:

18 "Son of man, sing mournfully over the multitude of Egypt. And cast her down, both her and the daughters of the robust nations, to the lowest part of the earth, with those who descend into the pit.

19 Whom do you exceed in beauty? Descend and sleep with the uncircumcised!

20 They will fall by the sword in the midst of the slain. The sword has been given. They have dragged her down, with all her people.

21 The most powerful among the strong will speak to him from the midst of hell, those who descended with his helpers and who went to sleep uncircumcised, slain by the sword.

22 Assur is in that place, with all his multitude. Their graves are all around him: all of the slain and those who fell by the sword.

23 Their graves have been placed in the lowest parts of the pit. And his multitude was stationed on all sides of his grave: all of the slain, and those who fell by the sword, who formerly spread terror in the land of the living.

24 Elam is in that place, with all his multitude, on all sides of his grave, all those who were slain or who fell by the sword, who descended uncircumcised to the lowest part of the earth, who caused their terror in the land of the living. And they have borne their disgrace, with those who descend into the pit.

25 They have appointed him a place to lie among all his people, in the midst of the slain. Their graves are all around him. All these are uncircumcised and were slain by the sword. For they spread their terror in the land of the living, and they have borne their disgrace, with those who descend into the pit. They have been stationed in the midst of the slain.

26 Meshech and Tubal are in that place, with all their multitude. Their graves are all around him: all these are uncircumcised, and they were slain and fell by the sword. For they spread their terror in the land of the living.

27 But they shall not sleep with the strong, and with those who also fell uncircumcised, who descended to hell with their weapons, and who placed their swords under their heads, while their iniquities were in their bones. For they were the terror of the strong in the land of the living.

28 Therefore, you also will be broken in the midst of the uncircumcised, and you will sleep with those who were slain by the sword.

29 Idumea is in that place, with her kings and all her commanders, who with their army have been given to those who were slain by the sword. And they have slept with the uncircumcised and with those who descend into the pit.

30 All the leaders of the north are in that place, with all the hunters, who were brought down with the slain, fearful and confounded in their strength, who have gone to sleep uncircumcised, with those who were slain by the sword. And they have borne their disgrace, with those who descend into the pit.

31 Pharaoh saw them, and he was consoled over all his multitude, which was slain by the sword, even Pharaoh and all his army, says the Lord God.

32 For I have spread my terror in the land of the living, and he has gone to sleep in the midst of the uncircumcised, with those who were slain by the sword, even Pharaoh and all his multitude, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 33

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, speak to the sons of your people, and you shall say to them: Concerning the land, when I will have led the sword over it: if the people of the land take a man, one of their least, and appoint him over themselves as a watchman,

3 and if he sees the sword approaching over the land, and he sounds the trumpet, and he announces to the people,

4 then, having heard the sound of the trumpet, whoever he is, if he also does not take care of himself, and the sword arrives and takes him: his blood will be upon his own head.

5 He heard the sound of the trumpet, and he did not take care of himself, so his blood will be upon him. But if he guards himself, he will save his own life.

6 And if the watchman sees the sword approaching, and he does not sound the trumpet, and so the people do not guard themselves, and the sword arrives and takes some of their lives, certainly these have been taken due to their own iniquity. But I will attribute their blood to the hand of the watchman.

7 And as for you, son of man, I have made you a watchman to the house of Israel. Therefore, having heard the word from my mouth, you shall announce it to them from me.

8 When I say to the impious, 'O impious man, you will die a death,' if you have not spoken so that the impious man will keep himself from his way, then that impious man will die in his iniquity. But I will attribute his blood to your hand.

9 But if you have announced to the impious man, so that he may be converted from his ways, and he has not converted from his way, then he will die in his iniquity. Yet you will have freed your own soul.

10 You, therefore, O son of man, say to the house of Israel: You have spoken in this way, saying: 'Our iniquities and our sins are upon us, and we waste away in them. So then, how would we be able to live?'

11 Say to them: As I live, says the Lord God, I do not desire the death of the impious, but that the impious should convert from his way and live. Be converted, be converted from your evil ways! For why should you die, O house of Israel?

12 And as for you then, son of man, say to the sons of your people: The justice of the just man will not deliver him, on whatever day he will have sinned. And the impiety of the impius man will not harm him, on whatever day he will have been converted from his impiety. And the just man will not be able to live by his justice, on whatever day he will have sinned.

13 Even now, if I say to the just man that he shall certainly live, and so, with confidence in his justice, he commits iniquity, all his justices will be delivered into oblivion, and by his iniquity, which he has done, by this he shall die.

14 And if I say to the impious man, 'You shall certainly die,' and yet he repents from his sin, and he does judgment and justice,

15 and if that impious man returns the collateral, and repays what he has taken by force, and if he walks in the commandments of life, and does not do anything unjust, then he shall certainly live, and he shall not die.

16 None of his sins, which he has committed, will be imputed to him. He has done judgment and justice, so he shall certainly live.

17 And the sons of your people have said, 'The way of the Lord is not a fair balance,' even while their own way is unjust.

18 For when the just man will have withdraw from his justice, and committed iniquities, he shall die by these.

19 And when the impious man will have withdrawn from his impiety, and have done judgment and justice, he shall live by these.

20 And yet you say, 'The way of the Lord is not right.' But I shall judge each one of you according to his own ways, O house of Israel."

21 And it happened that, in the twelfth year of our transmigration, in the tenth month, on the fifth of the month, one who had fled from Jerusalem arrived saying, "The city has been laid waste."

22 But the hand of the Lord had been upon me in the evening, before the one who had fled arrived. And he opened my mouth, until he came to me in the morning. And since my mouth had been opened, I was no longer silent.

23 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

24 "Son of man, as for those who live in these ruinous ways on the soil of Israel, when speaking, they say: 'Abraham was one man, and he possessed the land as an inheritance. But we are many; the land has been given to us as a possession.'

25 Therefore, you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord God: You who eat even the blood, and who lift up your eyes to your uncleannesses, and who shed blood: will you possess the land as an inheritance?

26 You stood by your swords, you committed abominations, and each one has defiled his neighbor's wife. And will you possess the land as an inheritance?

27 You shall say these things to them: So says the Lord God: As I live, those who live in ruinous ways will fall by the sword. And whoever is in the field will be delivered over to wild beasts to be devoured. But those who are in fortresses and in caves will die of the pestilence.

28 And I will make the land into a wilderness and a desert. And its arrogant strength will fail. And the mountains of Israel will be desolate; for there will be no one who crosses through them.

29 And they shall know that I am the Lord, when I will have make their land desolate and deserted, because of all their abominations, which they have worked.

30 And as for you, O son of man: the sons of your people speak about you beside the walls and in the doorways of houses. And they speak to one another, each man to his neighbor, saying: 'Come, and let us hear what may be the word going forth from the Lord.'

31 And they come to you, as if the people were entering, and my people sit before you. And they listen to your words, but they do not do them. For they turn them into a song for their mouth, but their heart pursues their own avarice.

32 And you are to them like a verse set to music, which is sung with a sweet and pleasing voice. And they hear your words, but they do not do them.

33 And when what has been predicted occurs, for behold it is approaching, then they shall know that a prophet was among them."

Ezekiel 34

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, prophesy about the shepherds of Israel. Prophesy, and you shall say to the shepherds: Thus says the Lord God: Woe to the shepherds of Israel who feed themselves! Should not the flocks be fed by the shepherds?

3 You consumed the milk, and you covered yourselves with the wool, and you killed what was fattened. But my flock you did not feed.

4 What was weak, you have not strengthened, and what was sick, you have not healed. What was broken, you have not bound, and what was cast aside, you have not led back again, and what was lost, you have not sought. Instead, you ruled over them with severity and with power.

5 And my sheep were scattered, because there was no shepherd. And they became devoured by all the wild beasts of the field, and they were dispersed.

6 My sheep have wandered to every mountain and to every exalted hill. And my flocks have been scattered across the face of the earth. And there was no one who sought them; there was no one, I say, who sought them.

7 Because of this, O shepherds, listen to the word of the Lord:

8 As I live, says the Lord God, since my flocks have become a prey, and my sheep have been devoured by all the wild beasts of the field, since there was no shepherd, for my shepherds did not seek my flock, but instead the shepherds fed themselves, and they did not feed my flocks:

9 because of this, O shepherds, listen to the word of the Lord:

10 Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I myself will be over the shepherds. I will require my flock at their hand, and I will cause them to cease, so that they no longer refrain from feeding the flock. Neither will the shepherds feed themselves any more. And I will deliver my flock from their mouth; and it will no longer be food for them.

11 For thus says the Lord God: Behold, I myself will seek my sheep, and I myself will visit them.

12 Just as a shepherd visits his flock, in the day when he will be in the midst of his sheep that were scattered, so will I visit my sheep. And I will deliver them from all the places to which they had been scattered in the day of gloom and darkness.

13 And I will lead them away from the peoples, and I will gather them from the lands, and I will bring them into their own land. And I will pasture them on the mountains of Israel, by the rivers, and in all the settlements of the land.

14 I will feed them in very fertile pastures, and their pastures will be on the lofty mountains of Israel. There they will rest on the green grass, and they will be fed in the fat pastures, on the mountains of Israel.

15 I will feed my sheep, and I will cause them to lie down, says the Lord God.

16 I will seek what had been lost. And I will lead back again what had been cast aside. And I will bind up what had been broken. And I will strengthen what had been infirm. And I will preserve what was fat and strong. And I will feed them on judgment.

17 But as for you, O my flocks, thus says the Lord God: Behold, I judge between cattle and cattle, among rams and among he-goats.

18 Was it not enough for you to feed upon good pastures? For you even trample with your feet upon the remainder of your pastures. And when you drank the purist water, you disturbed the remainder with your feet.

19 And my sheep were pastured from what you had trampled with your feet, and they drank from what your feet had disturbed.

20 Because of this, thus says the Lord God to you: Behold, I myself am judging between the fat cattle and the lean.

21 For you have pushed with your sides and shoulders, and you have threatened all the weak cattle with your horns, until they were scattered abroad.

22 I will save my flock, and it will be no longer be a prey, and I will judge between cattle and cattle.

23 And I will raise up over them ONE SHEPHERD, who will feed them, my servant David. He himself will feed them, and he will be their shepherd.

24 And I, the Lord, will be their God. And my servant David will be the leader in their midst. I, the Lord, have spoken.

25 And I will make a covenant of peace with them. And I will cause the very harmful beasts to cease from the land. And those who are living in the desert will sleep securely in the forests.

26 And I will make them a blessing all around my hill. And I will send the rain in due time; there will be showers of blessing.

27 And the tree of the field will yield its fruit, and the land will yield its crop. And they will be in their own land without fear. And they shall know that I am the Lord, when I will have crushed the chains of their yoke, and when I will have rescued them from the hand of those who rule over them.

28 And they will no longer be a prey to the Gentiles, nor will the wild beasts of the earth devour them. Instead, they will live in confidence without any terror.

29 And I will raise up for them a renown branch. And they will be no longer be diminished by famine in the land, nor will they carry any longer the reproach of the Gentiles.

30 And they shall know that I, the Lord their God, am with them, and that they are my people, the house of Israel, says the Lord God.

31 For you are my flocks; the flocks of my pasture are men. And I am the Lord your God, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 35

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, set your face against mount Seir, and you shall prophesy about it, and you shall say to it:

3 Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I am against you, mount Seir, and I will extend my hand over you, and I will make you desolate and deserted.

4 I will tear down your cities, and you will be deserted. And you shall know that I am the Lord.

5 For you have been a continual adversary, and you have enclosed the sons of Israel, by the hands of the sword, in the time of their affliction, in the time of extreme iniquity.

6 Because of this, as I live, says the Lord God, I will hand you over to blood, and blood will pursue you. Even though you have hated blood, blood will pursue you.

7 And I will make mount Seir desolate and deserted. And I will take away from it the one who departs and the one who returns.

8 And I will fill up its mountains with its slain. In your hills, and in your valleys, as well as in your torrents, the slain will fall by the sword.

9 I will hand you over to everlasting desolations, and your cities will not be inhabited. And you shall know that I am the Lord God.

10 For you have said, 'Two nations and two lands will be mine, and I will possess them as an inheritance,' though the Lord was in that place.

11 Because of this, as I live, says the Lord God, I will act in accord with your own wrath, and in accord with your own zeal, by which you have acted with hatred toward them. And I will be made known by them, when I will have judged you.

12 And you shall know that I, the Lord, have heard all your disgraces, which you have spoken about the mountains of Israel, saying: 'They are deserted. They have been given to us to devour.'

13 And you rose up against me with your mouth, and you disparaged against me with your words. I have heard.

14 Thus says the Lord God: When the whole earth will rejoice, I will reduce you to solitude.

15 Just as you have rejoiced over the inheritance of the house of Israel, when it was laid waste, so will I act toward you. You will be laid waste, O mount Seir, with all of Idumea. And they shall know that I am the Lord."

Ezekiel 36

1 "But as for you, son of man, prophesy over the mountains of Israel, and you shall say: O mountains of Israel, listen to the word of the Lord.

2 Thus says the Lord God: Because the enemy has said about you: 'It is well! The everlasting heights have been given to us as an inheritance!'

3 because of this, prophesy and say: Thus says the Lord God: Because you have been made desolate, and you have been trampled on every side, and you have been made into an inheritance for the remainder of the nations, and because you rose up, over the tip of the tongue and over the shame of the people,

4 because of this, O mountains of Israel, listen to the word of the Lord God. Thus says the Lord God to the mountains, and to the hills, to the torrents, and to the valleys, and to the deserts, and to the ruins, and to the forsaken cities, which have been depopulated and ridiculed by the remainder of the nations all around:

5 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: In the fire of my zeal, I have spoken about the remainder of the nations, and about all of Idumea, who have given my land to themselves, joyfully, as an inheritance, and with all the heart and mind, and who have cast it out, so that they may lay waste to it.

6 Therefore, prophesy over the soil of Israel, and you shall say to the mountains, and to the hills, to the ridges, and to the valleys: Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I have spoken in my zeal and in my fury, because you have endured the shame of the Gentiles.

7 Therefore, thus says the Lord God: I have lifted up my hand, so that the Gentiles, who are all around you, will themselves bear their shame.

8 But as for you, O mountains of Israel, spring forth your branches, and bear your fruit, to my people Israel. For they are close to their advent.

9 For behold, I am for you, and I will turn to you, and you will be plowed, and you will receive seed.

10 And I will multiply men among you and among all the house of Israel. And the cities shall be inhabited, and the ruinous places shall be restored.

11 And I will fill you again with men and with cattle. And they will be multiplied, and they will increase. And I will cause you to live as from the beginning, and I will give you even greater gifts than those you had from the start. And you shall know that I am the Lord.

12 And I will lead men over you, over my people Israel, and they will possess you as an inheritance. And you shall be to them as an inheritance. And you shall no longer be permitted to be without them.

13 Thus says the Lord God: Because they are saying about you, 'You are a woman who devours men, and you are strangling your own nation,'

14 because of this, you shall no longer consume men, and you shall no longer harm your own nation, says the Lord God.

15 Neither will I permit men to discover in you the shame of the Gentiles any more. And you shall never again bear the reproach of the peoples. And you shall not send your people away any more, says the Lord God."

16 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

17 "Son of man, the house of Israel lived on their own soil, and they defiled it with their ways and with their intentions. Their way, in my sight, became like the uncleanness of a menstruous woman.

18 And so I poured out my indignation upon them, because of the blood which they shed upon the land, and because they defiled it with their idols.

19 And I dispersed them among the Gentiles, and they have been scattered among the lands. I have judged them according to their ways and their plans.

20 And when they walked among the Gentiles, to whom they had entered, they defiled my holy name, though it was being said about them: 'This is the people of the Lord,' and 'They went forth from his land.'

21 But I have spared my holy name, which the house of Israel has defiled among the Gentiles, to whom they entered.

22 For this reason, you shall say to the house of Israel: Thus says the Lord God: I will act, not for your sake, O house of Israel, but for the sake of my holy name, which you have defiled among the Gentiles, to whom you entered.

23 And I will sanctify my great name, which was defiled among the Gentiles, which you have defiled in their midst. So may the Gentiles know that I am the Lord, says the Lord of hosts, when I will have been sanctified in you, before their eyes.

24 Certainly, I will take you away from the Gentiles, and I will gather you together from all the lands, and I will lead you into your own land.

25 And I will pour clean water over you, and you shall be cleansed from all your filth, and I will cleanse you from all your idols.

26 And I will give to you a new heart, and I will place in you a new spirit. And I will take away the heart of stone from your body, and I will give to you a heart of flesh.

27 And I will place my Spirit in your midst. And I will act so that you may walk in my precepts and keep my judgments, and so that you may fulfill them.

28 And you shall live in the land that I gave to your fathers. And you shall be my people, and I will be your God.

29 And I will save you from all your filth. And I will call for grain, and I will multiply it, and I will not impose a famine upon you.

30 And I will multiply the fruit of the tree and the produce of the field, so that you may no longer bear the disgrace of famine among the nations.

31 And you shall remember your very wicked ways and your intentions, which were not good. And you will be displeased by your own iniquities and your own crimes.

32 It is not for your sakes that I will act, says the Lord God; let this be known to you. Be confounded and ashamed over your own ways, O house of Israel.

33 Thus says the Lord God: In the day when I will have cleansed you from all your iniquities, and when I will have caused the cities to be inhabited, and when I will have restored the ruinous places,

34 and when the deserted land will have been cultivated, which previously was desolate to the eyes of all who passed by,

35 then they shall say: 'This uncultivated land has become a garden of delight, and the cities, which were deserted and destitute and overturned, have been settled and fortified.'

36 And the Gentiles, those who remain around you, shall know that I, the Lord, have built up what was destroyed, and have planted what was uncultivated. I, the Lord, have spoken and acted.

37 Thus says the Lord God: Even in this time, the house of Israel shall find me, so that I may act for them. I will multiply them like a flock of men,

38 like a holy flock, like the flock of Jerusalem in her solemnities. So shall the deserted cities be filled with flocks of men. And they shall know that I am the Lord."

Ezekiel 37

1 The hand of the Lord was set upon me, and he led me away in the Spirit of the Lord, and he released me in the midst of a plain which was full of bones.

2 And he led me around, through them, on every side. Now they were very many upon the face of the plain, and they were exceedingly dry.

3 And he said to me, "Son of man, do you think that these bones will live?" And I said, "O Lord God, you know."

4 And he said to me, "Prophesy about these bones. And you shall say to them: Dry bones, listen to the word of the Lord!

5 Thus says the Lord God to these bones: Behold, I will send spirit into you, and you shall live.

6 And I will set sinews upon you, and I will cause flesh to grow over you, and I will extend skin over you. And I will give you spirit, and you shall live. And you shall know that I am the Lord."

7 And I prophesied, just as he had instructed me. But a noise occurred, as I was prophesying, and behold: a commotion. And the bones joined together, each one at its joint.

8 And I saw, and behold: sinews and flesh rose up over them; and skin was extended over them. But they had no spirit within them.

9 And he said to me: "Prophesy to the spirit! Prophesy, O son of man, and you shall say to the spirit: Thus says the Lord God: Approach, O spirit, from the four winds, and blow across these ones who were slain, and revive them."

10 And I prophesied, just as he had instructed me. And spirit entered into them, and they lived. And they stood upon their feet, an exceedingly great army.

11 And he said to me: "Son of man: All these bones are the house of Israel. They say: 'Our bones are dried out, and our hope has perished, and we have been cut off.'

12 Because of this, prophesy, and you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will open your tombs, and I will lead you away from your sepulchers, O my people. And I will lead you into the land of Israel.

13 And you shall know that I am the Lord, when I will have opened your sepulchers, and when I will have led you away from your tombs, O my people.

14 And I will place my Spirit within you, and you shall live. And I will cause you to rest upon your own soil. And you shall know that I, the Lord, have spoken and acted, says the Lord God."

15 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

16 "And as for you, son of man, take up a piece of wood for yourself, and write upon it: 'For Judah, and for the sons of Israel, his companions.' And take up another piece of wood, and write upon it: 'For Joseph, the wood of Ephraim, and for the entire house of Israel, and for his companions.'

17 And join these, one to the other, for yourself, as one piece of wood. And they will be united in your hand.

18 Then, when the sons of your people will speak to you, saying: 'Will you not tell us what you intend by this?'

19 you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will take up the wood of Joseph, which is in the hand of Ephraim, and the tribes of Israel, which are joined to him, and I will put them together with the wood of Judah, and I will make them one piece of wood. And they will be one in his hand.

20 Then the pieces of wood, on which you have written, will be in your hand, before their eyes.

21 And you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will take up the sons of Israel, from the midst of the nations to which they have gone, and I will gather them together on every side, and I will lead them onto their own soil.

22 And I will make them one nation in the land, on the mountains of Israel, and one king will be ruler over all. And they will no longer be two nations, nor will they be divided any more into two kingdoms.

23 And they will no longer be defiled by their idols, and by their abominations, and by all their iniquities. And I will save them, out of all the settlements in which they have sinned, and I will cleanse them. And they will be my people, and I will be their God.

24 And my servant David shall be the king over them, and they shall have one shepherd. They shall walk in my judgments, and they shall keep my commandments, and they shall do them.

25 And they shall live upon the land that I gave to my servant Jacob, in which your fathers lived. And they shall live upon it, they and their sons, and the sons of their sons, even for all time. And David, my servant, shall be their leader, in perpetuity.

26 And I will strike a covenant of peace with them. This will be an everlasting covenant for them. And I will establish them, and multiply them. And I will set my sanctuary in their midst, unceasingly.

27 And my tabernacle shall be among them. And I will be their God, and they will be my people.

28 And the Gentiles shall know that I am the Lord, the Sanctifier of Israel, when my sanctuary will be in their midst, forever."

Ezekiel 38

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, set your face against Gog, the land of Magog, the prince of the head of Meshech and Tubal, and prophesy about him.

3 And you shall say to him: Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I am against you, O Gog, prince of the head of Meshech and Tubal.

4 And I will turn you around, and I will place a bit in your jaws. And I will lead you away, with all your army, the horses and the horsemen all clothed in armor, a great multitude, equipped with spears and light shields and swords,

5 the Persians, the Ethiopians, and the Libyans with them, all with heavy shields and helmets,

6 Gomer, and all his companies, the house of Togarmah, the northern parts, and all his strength, and the many peoples with you.

7 Prepare and equip yourself, with all your multitude which has been assembled to you. And you shall be like a commandment to them.

8 After many days, you will be visited. At the end of the years, you will arrive at the land which was turned back by the sword, and which has been gathered from many peoples to the mountains of Israel that have been continually abandoned. These ones have been led away from the peoples, and all of them will be living confidently within it.

9 But you will ascend and arrive like a tempest and like a cloud, so that you may cover the land, you and all your companies, and the many peoples with you.

10 Thus says the Lord God: In that day, words will climb into your heart, and you will invent a most wicked plan.

11 And you will say: 'I will ascend to the land without a wall. I will go to those who are resting and dwelling securely. All these live without a wall; they have no bars or gates.'

12 Thus, you will plunder spoils, and you will take possession of prey, so that you may lay your hand upon those who had been abandoned, and afterwards were restored, and upon a people who were gathered away from the Gentiles, a people who have begun to possess, and to be the inhabitants of, the navel of the earth.

13 Sheba, and Dedan, and the merchants of Tarshish, and all its lions will say to you: 'Could you have arrived in order to purchase from the spoils? Behold, you have gathered your multitude in order to plunder a prey, so that you may take silver and gold, and carry away equipment and substance, and plunder immeasurable wealth.'

14 Because of this, son of man, prophesy, and you shall say to Gog: Thus says the Lord God: How is it that you do not know of that day, when my people, Israel, will be living in confidence?

15 And you will advance from your place, from the parts of the north, you and the many peoples with you, all of them riding on horses, a great assembly and an immense army.

16 And you will rise up over my people, Israel, like a cloud, so that you may cover the earth. In the latter days, you will be. And I will lead you over my own land, so that the Gentiles may know me, when I will have been sanctified in you, O Gog, before their eyes.

17 Thus says the Lord God: Therefore, you are the one, about whom I spoke in the days of antiquity, by the hand of my servants the prophets of Israel, who prophesied in the days of those times that I would lead you over them.

18 And this shall be in that day, in the day of the advent of Gog over the land of Israel, says the Lord God: my indignation will rise up in my fury.

19 And I have spoken, in my zeal and in the fire of my wrath, that there shall be a great commotion over the land of Israel, in that day.

20 And before my face there shall be stirred up: the fish of the sea, and the flying things of the air, and the beasts of the field, and every crawling thing that moves across the soil, and all the men who are upon the face of the earth. And the mountains will be overturned, and the hedges will fall, and every wall will fall in ruin to the ground.

21 And I will call for the sword against him on all my mountains, says the Lord God. Each one's sword will be directed toward his brother.

22 And I will judge him by pestilence, and blood, and violent rainstorms, and immense hailstones. I will rain fire and brimstone upon him, and upon his army, and upon the many peoples who are with him.

23 And I will be magnified and sanctified. And I will be known in the eyes of the many nations. And they shall know that I am the Lord."

Ezekiel 39

1 "But as for you, son of man, prophesy against Gog, and you shall say: Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I am above you, O Gog, prince of the head of Meshech and Tubal.

2 And I will turn you around, and I will lead you away, and I will cause you to rise up from the parts of the north. And I will bring you over the mountains of Israel.

3 And I will strike your bow in your left hand, and I will cast away your arrows from your right hand.

4 You will fall upon the mountains of Israel, you and all your companies, and your peoples who are with you. I have given you over to the wild animals, to the birds, and to every flying thing, and to the beasts of the earth, in order to be devoured.

5 You will fall upon the face of the field. For I have spoken, says the Lord God.

6 And I will send a fire upon Magog, and upon those who are living confidently in the islands. And they shall know that I am the Lord.

7 And I will make known my holy name in the midst of my people, Israel, and my holy name will no longer be defiled. And the Gentiles shall know that I am the Lord, the Holy One of Israel.

8 Behold, it approaches, and it is done, says the Lord God. This is the day, about which I have spoken.

9 And the inhabitants from the cities of Israel will go forth, and they will kindle and burn the weapons, the shields and the spears, the bows and the arrows, and the staff and the lance. And they will kindle fires with them for seven years.

10 And they will not carry wood from the countryside, and they will not cut from the forests. For they will kindle the weapons with fire. And they will prey upon those who had preyed upon them, and they will plunder those who had plundered them, says the Lord God.

11 And this shall be in that day: I will give Gog a renown place as a sepulcher in Israel, the valley of the wayfarers to the east of the sea, which will cause astonishment in those who pass by. And in that place, they will bury Gog and all his multitude, and it will be called the valley of the multitude of Gog.

12 And the house of Israel will bury them, so that they may cleanse the land, for seven months

13 Then all the people of the earth will bury them, and this shall be for them a renown day, on which I have been glorified, says the Lord God.

14 And they shall appoint men to continually examine the earth, so that they may seek out and bury those who have remained on the surface of the earth, so that they may cleanse it. Then, after seven months, they will begin to seek.

15 And they will go around, traveling the earth. And when they will have seen the bone of a man, they will station a marker beside it, until the undertakers may bury it in the valley of the multitude of Gog.

16 And the name of the city will be: the Multitude. And they shall cleanse the earth.

17 As for you, then, son of man, thus says the Lord God: Say to every flying thing, and to all the birds, and to all the beasts of the field: Assemble! Hurry! Rush together from every side to my victim, which I have immolated for you, a great victim upon the mountains of Israel, so that you may consume flesh, and drink blood!

18 You shall eat the flesh of the powerful, and you shall drink the blood of the princes of the earth, of rams and lambs and he-goats and bulls, and of fattened birds and all that is fat.

19 And you shall consume the fat unto satiation, and you shall drink the blood unto inebriation, from the victim that I will immolate for you.

20 And you shall be satiated, upon my table, from horses and powerful horsemen, and from all the men of war, says the Lord God.

21 And I will set my glory among the Gentiles. And all the nations shall see my judgment, which I have accomplished, and my hand, which I have laid upon them.

22 And the house of Israel shall know that I am the Lord, their God, from that day and thereafter.

23 And the Gentiles shall know that the house of Israel was taken captive because of their own iniquity, because they abandoned me. And so I concealed my face from them, and I delivered them into the hands of their enemies, and they all fell by the sword.

24 I have acted toward them in accord with their uncleanness and wickedness, and so I concealed my face from them.

25 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Now I will lead back the captivity of Jacob, and I will take pity upon the entire house of Israel. And I will act with zeal on behalf of my holy name.

26 And they shall bear their shame and all their transgression, by which they betrayed me, though they were living in their own land confidently, dreading no one.

27 And I will lead them back from among the peoples, and I will gather them together from the lands of their enemies, and I will be sanctified in them, in the sight of the many nations.

28 And they shall know that I am the Lord, their God, because I carried them away to the nations, and I gathered them upon their own land, and I did not abandon any of them there.

29 And I will no longer conceal my face from them, for I have poured out my Spirit upon the entire house of Israel, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 40

1 In the twenty-fifth year of our transmigration, at the beginning of the year, on the tenth of the month, in the fourteenth year after the city was struck, on this very day, the hand of the Lord was placed upon me, and he brought me to that place.

2 In the visions of God, he brought me into the land of Israel, and he released me on an exceedingly high mountain, on which there was something like the edifice of a city, verging toward the south.

3 And he led me into that place. And behold, there was a man, whose appearance was like the appearance of brass, with a linen rope in his hand, and a measuring reed in his hand. And he was standing at the gate.

4 And the same man said to me: "Son of man, look with your eyes, and listen with your ears, and set your heart upon all that I will reveal to you. For you have been brought to this place, so that these things may be revealed to you. Announce all that you see to the house of Israel."

5 And behold, there was a wall outside of the house, encircling it all around, and in the man's hand was a measuring reed of six cubits and a palm. And he measured the width of the edifice with one reed; likewise, the height with one reed.

6 And he went to the gate which looked toward the east, and he ascended by its steps. And he measured the width of the threshold of the gate as one reed, that is, one threshold was one reed in width.

7 And a chamber was one reed in length and one reed in width. And between the chambers, there were five cubits.

8 And the threshold of the gate, next to the inner vestibule of the gate, was one reed.

9 And he measured the vestibule of the gate as eight cubits, and its front as two cubits. But the vestibule of the gate was inside.

10 Moreover, the chambers of the gate, toward the way of the east, were three from one side to the other. The three were of one measure, and the fronts were of one measure, on both sides.

11 And he measured the width of the threshold of the gate as ten cubits, and the length of the gate as thirteen cubits.

12 And before the chambers, the border was one cubit. And on both sides, the border was one cubit. But the chambers were six cubits, from one side to the other.

13 And he measured the gate, from the roof of one chamber to the roof of another, twenty-five cubits in width, from door to door.

14 And he found the fronts to be sixty cubits. And at the front, there was a court for the gate on every side all around.

15 And before the face of the gate, which extended even to the face of the vestibule of the gate of the interior, there were fifty cubits.

16 And there were slanting windows in the chambers and at their fronts, which were within the gate on every side all around. And similarly, there were also windows in the vestibules all around the interior, and there were images of palm trees before the fronts.

17 And he led me away to the outer court, and behold, there were storerooms and a layer of pavement stones throughout the court. Thirty storerooms encircled the pavement.

18 And the pavement in front of the gates, along the length of the gates, was lower.

19 And he measured the width, from the face of the lower gate to the front of the outer part of the inner court, to be one hundred cubits, to the east and to the north.

20 Likewise, he measured the gate of the outer court, which looked to the way of the north, to be as much in length as in width.

21 And its chambers were three from one side to the other. And its front and its vestibule, in accord with the measure of the former gate, were fifty cubits in its length and twenty-five cubits in width.

22 Now its windows, and the vestibule, and the engravings were in accord with the measure of the gate which looked to the east. And its ascent was by seven steps, and a vestibule was before it.

23 And the gate of the inner court was opposite the gate of the north, and that of the east. And he measured from gate to gate as one hundred cubits.

24 And he led me to the way of the south, and behold, there was a gate which looked toward the south. And he measured its front and its vestibule to be the same as the measures above.

25 And its windows and the vestibule all around were like the other windows: fifty cubits in length and twenty-five cubits in width.

26 And there were seven steps to ascend to it, and a vestibule before its doors. And there were engraved palm trees, one on each side, at its front.

27 And there was a gate at the inner court, on the way to the south. And he measured from one gate to another, on the way to the south, to be one hundred cubits.

28 And he led me into the inner court, to the south gate. And he measured the gate to be in accord with the measures above.

29 Its chamber, and its front, and its vestibule had the same measures. And its windows and its vestibule all around were fifty cubits in length, and twenty-five cubits in width.

30 And the vestibule all around was twenty-five cubits in length, and five cubits in width.

31 And its vestibule was toward the outer court, and its palm trees were at the front. And there were eight steps to ascend to it.

32 And he led me into the inner court, along the way of the east. And he measured the gate to be in accord with the measures above.

33 Its chamber, and its front, and its vestibule were as above. And its windows and its vestibules all around were fifty cubits in length, and twenty-five cubits in width.

34 And it had a vestibule, that is, at the outer court. And the engraved palm trees at its front were on one side and the other. And its ascent was by eight steps.

35 And he led me to the gate which looked toward the north. And he measured it to be in accord with the measures above.

36 Its chamber, and its front, and its vestibule, and its windows all around were fifty cubits in length, and twenty-five cubits in width.

37 And its vestibule looked toward the outer court. And an engraving of palm trees at its front was on one side and the other. And its ascent was by eight steps.

38 And at each one of the storerooms, there was a door at the front of the gates. There, they washed the holocaust.

39 And at the vestibule of the gate, there were two tables on one side, and two tables on the other side, so that the holocaust, and the offering for sin, and the offering for transgression could be immolated upon them.

40 And at the outer side, which ascends to the door of the gate that goes toward the north, there were two tables. And at the other side, before the vestibule of the gate, there were two tables.

41 Four tables were on one side, and four tables were on the other side; along the sides of the gate, there were eight tables, upon which they immolated.

42 Now the four tables for the holocausts were constructed of square stones: one and a half cubit in length, and one and a half cubits in width, and one cubit in height. Upon these, they placed the vessels, in which the holocaust and the victim were immolated.

43 And their edges were one palm in width, turned inward all around. And the flesh of the oblation was on the tables.

44 And outside the interior gate, there were storerooms for the cantors, in the inner court, which was beside the gate that looks toward the north. And their face was opposite the way to the south; one was beside the east gate, which looked toward the way of the north.

45 And he said to me: "This is the storeroom that looks toward the south; it shall be for the priests who keep watch for the protection of the temple.

46 Moreover, the storeroom that looks toward the north will be for the priests who keep watch over the ministry of the altar. These are the sons of Zadok, those among the sons of Levi who may draw near to the Lord, so that they may minister to him."

47 And he measured the court to be one hundred cubits in length, and one hundred cubits in width, with four equal sides. And the altar was before the face of the temple.

48 And he led me into the vestibule of the temple. And he measured the vestibule to be five cubits on one side, and five cubits on the other side. And the width of the gate was three cubits on one side, and three cubits on the other side.

49 Now the length of the vestibule was twenty cubits, and the width was eleven cubits, and there were eight steps to ascend to it. And there were pillars at the front, one on this side and another on that side.

Ezekiel 41

1 And he led me into the temple, and he measured the front to be six cubits in width on one side, and six cubits in width on the other side, which is the width of the tabernacle.

2 And the width of the gate was ten cubits. And the sides of the gate were five cubits on one side, and five cubits on the other side. And he measured its length to be forty cubits, and the width to be twenty cubits.

3 And proceeding inward, he measured the front of the gate to be two cubits. And the gate was six cubits, and the width of the gate was seven cubits.

4 And he measured its length to be twenty cubits, and its width to be twenty cubits, before the face of the temple. And he said to me, "This is the Holy of Holies."

5 And he measured the wall of the house to be six cubits, and the width of the sides to be four cubits, all around the house on every side.

6 Now the side chambers were side by side, and twice thirty-three. And they projected outward, so that they might enter along the wall of the house, on the sides all around, in order to contain, but not touch, the wall of the temple.

7 And there was a broad circular path, rising upward by winding, and it led to the cenacle of the temple by a circular course. As a result, the temple was wider in the higher parts. And so, from the lower parts, they rose up to the higher parts, in the center.

8 And in the house, I saw the height all around the foundations of the side chambers, which were the measure of a reed, the space of six cubits.

9 And the width of the exterior wall for the side chambers was five cubits. And the inner house was within the side chambers of the house.

10 And between the storerooms, there was the width of twenty cubits, all around the house on every side.

11 And the door of the side chambers was toward the place of prayer. One door was toward the way of the north, and one door was toward the way of the south. And the width of the place for prayer was five cubits all around.

12 And the edifice, which was separate, and which verged toward the way looking toward the sea, was seventy cubits in width. But the wall of the edifice was five cubits in width on all sides, and its length was ninety cubits.

13 And he measured the length of the house to be one hundred cubits, and the edifice, which was separate, with its walls, to be one hundred cubits in length.

14 Now the width before the face of the house, and of that which was separate facing the east, was one hundred cubits.

15 And he measured the length of the edifice opposite its face, which was separated at the back, and the porticos on both sides, to be one hundred cubits, with the inner temple and the vestibules of the court.

16 The thresholds, and the oblique windows, and the porticoes, encircling it on three sides, were opposite the threshold of each one, and were floored with wood throughout the entire area. But the floor reached even to the windows, and the windows were closed above the doors;

17 and it reached even to the inner house, and to the exterior, throughout the entire wall, all around the interior and exterior, for the entire extent.

18 And there were cherubim and palm trees wrought, and each palm tree was between one cherub and another, and every cherub had two faces.

19 The face of a man was closest to the palm tree on one side, and the face of a lion was closest to the palm tree on the other side. This was depicted throughout the entire house all around.

20 From the floor, even to the upper parts of the gate, there were cherubim and palm trees engraved in the wall of the temple.

21 The square threshold and the face of the sanctuary were one sight facing the other.

22 The altar of wood was three cubits in height, and its length was two cubits. And its corners, and its length, and its walls were of wood. And he said to me, "This is the table in the sight of the Lord."

23 And there were two doors in the temple and in the sanctuary.

24 And in the two doors, on both sides, were two little doors, which were folded within each other. For two doors were on both sides of the doors.

25 And cherubim were engraved in the same doors of the temple, with the figures of palm trees, as were depicted also on the walls. For this reason also, the boards were thicker in the front of the vestibule on the exterior.

26 Upon these were the oblique windows, with the representation of palm trees on one side as well as on the other, at the sides of the vestibule, in accord with the sides of the house, and the width of the walls.

Ezekiel 42

1 And he led me into the outer court by the way that leads to the north, and he led me into the storeroom that was opposite the separate edifice, and opposite the shrine that verges toward the north.

2 The length of the face of the north gate was one hundred cubits, and the width was fifty cubits.

3 Opposite the twenty cubits of the interior court, and opposite the layer of pavement stones in the outer court, in that place, there was a portico joined to a triple portico.

4 And before the storerooms, there was a walkway of ten cubits in width, looking toward the interior along a way of one cubit. And their doors were toward the north.

5 In that place, there were storerooms in the upper part of the lower level. For they supported the porticos, which projected from them out of the lower level, and out of the middle of the building.

6 For they were of three levels, and they did not have pillars, as they were like the pillars of the courts. Because of this, they projected from the lower levels and from the middle, fifty cubits from the ground.

7 And the exterior enclosing wall, adjacent to the storerooms that were along the way of the exterior court in front of the storerooms, was fifty cubits long.

8 For the length of the storerooms of the exterior court was fifty cubits, and the length before the face of the temple was one hundred cubits.

9 And under these storerooms, there was an entrance from the east, for those who were entering into it from the outer court.

10 In the width of the enclosing wall of the court that was opposite the way of the east, at the face of the separate edifice, there were also storerooms, before the edifice.

11 And the way before their face was in accord with the form of the storerooms which were along the way of the north. As was their length, so also was their width. And the entire entrance, and the likenesses, and their doors

12 were in accord with the doors of the storerooms that were on the way looking toward the Renown. There was a door at the head of the way, and the way was before a separate vestibule, along the way entering toward the east.

13 And he said to me: "The storerooms of the north, and the storerooms of the south, which are before the separate edifice, these are holy storerooms, in which the priests, who draw near to the Lord in the Holy of Holies, shall eat. There they shall station the Holy of Holies, and the offering for sin, and for trespasses. For it is a holy place.

14 And when the priests will have entered, they shall not depart from the holy places into the outer court. And in that place, they shall set their vestments, in which they minister, for they are holy. And they shall be clothed with other vestments, and in this manner they shall go forth to the people."

15 And when he had completed measuring the inner house, he led me out along the way of the gate that looked toward the way of the east. And he measured it on every side all around.

16 Then he measured facing the east wind with the measuring reed: five hundred reeds with the measuring reed throughout the course.

17 And he measured facing the wind of the north: five hundred reeds with the measuring reed throughout the course.

18 And toward the south wind, he measured five hundred reeds with the measuring reed throughout the course.

19 And toward the west wind, he measured five hundred reeds with the measuring reed.

20 By the four winds, he measured its wall, on every side throughout the course: five hundred cubits in length and five hundred cubits in width, dividing between the sanctuary and the place of the common people.

Ezekiel 43

1 And he led me to the gate which looked toward the way of the east.

2 And behold, the glory of the God of Israel entered along the way of the east. And his voice was like the voice of many waters. And the earth was resplendent before his majesty.

3 And I saw a vision in accord with the form that I had seen when he arrived so that he might destroy the city. And the form was in accord with the sight that I had seen beside the river Chebar. And I fell upon my face.

4 And the majesty of the Lord advanced into the temple, along the way of the gate which looked toward the east.

5 And the Spirit lifted me up and brought me into the inner court. And behold, the house was filled with the glory of the Lord.

6 And I heard someone speaking to me from the house, and the man who was standing beside me

7 said to me: "Son of man, the place of my throne, and the place of the steps of my feet, is where I live: in the midst of the sons of Israel forever. And the house of Israel, they and their kings, shall no longer defile my holy name by their fornications, and by the ruinous ways of their kings, and by exalted places.

8 They have fabricated their threshold beside my threshold, and their doorposts beside my doorposts. And there was a wall between me and them. And they defiled my holy name by the abominations which they committed. Because of this, I consumed them in my wrath.

9 Now therefore, let them drive away their fornications, and the ruinous ways of their kings, from before me. And I will live in their midst forever.

10 But as for you, son of man, reveal the temple to the house of Israel, and let them be confounded by their iniquities, and let them measure the fabrication,

11 and let them be ashamed at all the things that they have done. Reveal to them the form and the fabrication of the house, its exits and entrances, and its entire description, and all of its precepts, and its entire order, and all of its laws. And you shall write in their sight, so that they may observe its entire description and its precepts, and so that they may accomplish them."

12 This is the law of the house at the summit of the mountain, with all its parts all around. It is the Holy of Holies. Therefore, this is the law of the house.

13 Now these are the measures of the altar by the most true cubit, which has a cubit and a palm. Its bend was a cubit, and it was a cubit in width. And its boundary, even to its edge and all around, was the width of one palm. The trough of the altar was like this also.

14 And from the bend at the floor even to the furthest rim was two cubits, and the width was one cubit. And from the lesser rim even to the greater rim was four cubits, and the width was one cubit.

15 Now the hearth itself was four cubits. And from the hearth going upward, there were four horns.

16 And the hearth was twelve cubits in length by twelve cubits in width, foursquare, with equal sides.

17 And the rim was fourteen cubits in length, by fourteen cubits in width, at its four corners. And the crown all around it was one half cubit, and its bend was one cubit all around. And its steps turned toward the east.

18 And he said to me: "Son of man, thus says the Lord God: These are the rituals of the altar, in whatever day it will be made, so that holocausts may be offered upon it, and blood may be poured out.

19 And you shall present these to the priests and to the Levites, who are of the offspring of Zadok, those who draw near to me, says the Lord God, so that they may offer to me a calf from the herd on behalf of sin.

20 And you shall take from its blood, and you shall place it on its four horns, and on the four corners of the rim, and on the crown all around. And so shall you cleanse and expiate it.

21 And you shall take the calf, which will be offered for sin, and you shall burn it in a separate place in the house, outside of the sanctuary.

22 And on the second day, you shall offer an immaculate he-goat from among the she-goats on behalf of sin. And they shall expiate the altar, just as they expiated it with the calf.

23 And when you will have completed expiating it, you shall offer an immaculate calf from the herd and an immaculate ram from the flock.

24 And you shall offer them in the sight of the Lord. And the priests shall sprinkle salt over them, and they shall offer them as a holocaust to the Lord.

25 For seven days, you shall offer daily a he-goat on behalf of sin. Also, they shall offer a calf from the herd, and a ram from the flock, ones that are immaculate.

26 For seven days, they shall expiate the altar, and they shall cleanse it, and they shall fill its hand.

27 Then, when the days have been completed, on the eighth day and thereafter, the priests shall offer your holocausts upon the altar along with the peace offering. And I will be pleased with you, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 44

1 And he turned me back, toward the way of the gate of the outer sanctuary, which looked toward the east. And it was closed.

2 And the Lord said to me: "This gate will be closed; it will not be opened. And man shall not cross through it. For the Lord, the God of Israel, has entered through it, and it shall be closed

3 to the prince. The prince himself will sit at it, so that he may eat bread before the Lord; he will enter by the way of the vestibule of the gate, and he will depart by the same way."

4 And he led me in, along the way of the north gate, in the sight of the house. And I saw, and behold, the glory of the Lord filled the house of the Lord. And I fell upon my face.

5 And the Lord said to me: "Son of man, set within your heart, and see with your eyes, and hear with your ears all that I am speaking to you about all the ceremonies of the house of the Lord and about all its laws. And set your heart upon the ways of the temple, along all the exits of the sanctuary.

6 And you shall say to the house of Israel, which provokes me: Thus says the Lord God: Let all your wicked deeds be sufficient for you, O house of Israel.

7 For you bring in foreign sons, uncircumcised in heart and uncircumcised in flesh, so that they may be in my sanctuary and may defile my house. And you offer my bread, the fat, and the blood, yet you have broken my covenant by all your wicked deeds.

8 And you have not observed the precepts of my sanctuary, yet you have stationed observers of my vigil in my sanctuary for yourselves.

9 Thus says the Lord God: Any foreigner, any foreign son who is in the midst of the sons of Israel, who is uncircumcised in heart and uncircumcised in flesh, shall not enter into my sanctuary.

10 And as for the Levites, they have withdrawn far away from me, in the errors of the sons of Israel, and they have gone astray from me after their idols, and they have borne their iniquity.

11 They will be caretakers in my sanctuary, and doorkeepers at the gates of the house, and ministers to the house. They will slay the holocausts and the victims of the people. And they will stand before them, so that they may minister to them.

12 But because they ministered to them in the sight their idols, and they became a stumbling block of iniquity to the house of Israel, for this reason, I have lifted up my hand against them, says the Lord God, and they will bear their iniquity.

13 And they shall not draw near to me, so as to exercise the priesthood for me, and they shall not approach to any of my holy things, which are near the Holy of Holies. Instead, they will bear their shame and their wicked deeds, which they committed.

14 And I will make them doorkeepers of the house, for all its ministries and for all that will be done within it.

15 But the priests and the Levites who are the sons of Zadok, who observed the ceremonies of my sanctuary when the sons of Israel went astray from me, these shall draw near to me, so that they may minister for me. And they shall stand in my sight, so that they may offer to me the fat and the blood, says the Lord God.

16 They shall enter into my sanctuary, and they shall draw near to my table, so that they may minister for me, and so that they may observe my ceremonies.

17 And when they enter the gates of the inner court, they shall be clothed with linen garments. Neither shall anything woolen be placed over them, when they minister within the gates of the inner and the outer court.

18 They shall have linen bands on their heads, and linen undergarments over their loins, and they shall not be girded so as to sweat.

19 And when they go forth to the outer court to the people, they shall strip off their vestments, in which they ministered, and they shall place them in the storeroom of the sanctuary, and they shall clothe themselves with other garments. And they shall not sanctify the people in their vestments.

20 Now they shall not shave their heads, and they shall not grow long hair. Instead, they shall trim the hair of their heads.

21 And no priest shall drink wine, when he will be entering into the inner court.

22 And they shall not take as wife a widow or one who has been divorced. Instead, they shall take virgins from the offspring of the house of Israel. But they may also take a widow, if she is the widow of a priest.

23 And they shall teach my people the difference between holy and defiled, and they shall distinguish for them between clean and unclean.

24 And when there has been a controversy, they shall stand in my judgments, and they shall judge. They shall observe my laws and my precepts, in all my solemnities, and they shall sanctify my Sabbaths.

25 And they shall not enter to a dead person, lest they be defiled, except to father or mother, or son or daughter, or brother, or to a sister who does not have another man. By these, they may become unclean.

26 And after he will have been cleansed, they shall number for him seven days.

27 And on the day when he enters into the sanctuary, to the inner court, so that he may minister to me in the sanctuary, he shall make an offering because of his offense, says the Lord God.

28 And there shall be no inheritance for them. I am their inheritance. And you shall not give them any possession in Israel. For I am their possession.

29 They shall eat the victim both for sin and for offenses. And every vowed offering in Israel shall be theirs.

30 And the first-fruits of all the firstborn, and all the libations out of all that is offered, shall belong to the priests. And you shall give the first-fruits of your foods to the priest, so that he may return a blessing to your house.

31 The priests shall not consume anything which has died on its own, or which was seized by a beast, whether from the fowl or the cattle."

Ezekiel 45

1 "And when you will begin to divide the land by lot, separate as first-fruits for the Lord a sanctified portion of the land, in length twenty-five thousand and in width ten thousand. It will be holy within all its borders all around.

2 And there shall be, out of the entire region, a sanctified portion of five hundred by five hundred, foursquare all around, with fifty cubits for its suburbs on all sides.

3 And with this measure, you shall measure a length of twenty-five thousand, and a width of ten thousand, and within it shall be the temple and the Holy of Holies.

4 The sanctified portion of the land shall be for the priests, the ministers of the sanctuary, who approach for the ministry of the Lord. And it shall be a place for their houses, and for the holy place of the sanctuary.

5 Now twenty-five thousand in length, and ten thousand in width shall be for the Levites, who minister in the house. They shall possess twenty storerooms.

6 And you shall appoint a possession in the city of five thousand in width, and twenty-five thousand in length, in accord with the separation of the sanctuary, for the entire house of Israel.

7 Appoint the same for the prince, on one side and on the other, in the separation of the sanctuary, and in the possession of the city, opposite the face of the separation of the sanctuary, and opposite the face of the possession of the city, from the side of the sea even to the sea, and from the side of the east even to the east. And the length shall be just as in each part, from the western border even to the eastern border.

8 A portion of the land in Israel shall be for him. And the princes shall no longer plunder my people. Instead, they shall give the land to the house of Israel according to their tribes.

9 Thus says the Lord God: Let this be sufficient for you, O princes of Israel! Cease from iniquity and robberies, and execute judgment and justice. Separate your confines from my people, says the Lord God.

10 You shall have just scales, and a just unit of dry measure, and a just unit of liquid measure.

11 The units of dry and liquid measure shall be one uniform measure, so that a bath contains one tenth part of a cor, and an ephah contains one tenth part of a cor; each shall be of equal volume in accord with the measure of a cor.

12 Now the shekel consists of twenty obols. Furthermore, twenty shekels, and twenty-five shekels, and fifteen shekels makes one mina.

13 And these are the first-fruits that you shall take: a sixth part of an ephah from each cor of wheat, and a sixth part of an ephah from each cor of barley.

14 Likewise, a measure of oil, a bath of oil, is one tenth part of a cor. And ten baths make one cor. For ten baths complete one cor.

15 And take one ram from each flock of two hundred, out of those that Israel tends for sacrifice and holocausts and peace offerings, in order to make an expiation for them, says the Lord God.

16 All the people of the land will take hold of these first-fruits for the prince in Israel.

17 And concerning the prince, there shall be holocausts and sacrifice and libations, on solemnities and new moons and Sabbaths, and on all the solemnities of the house of Israel. He himself shall offer the sacrifice for sin, and the holocaust, and the peace offerings, in order to make expiation for the house of Israel.

18 Thus says the Lord God: In the first month, on the first of the month, you shall take an immaculate calf from the herd, and you shall expiate the sanctuary.

19 And the priest shall take from the blood that will be for the sin offering. And he shall place it on the doorposts of the house, and on the four corners of the rim of the altar, and on the posts of the gate of the inner court.

20 And so shall you do on the seventh day of the month, on behalf of each one who was ignorant or who was deceived by error. And you shall make expiation for the house.

21 In the first month, the fourteenth day of the month shall be for you the solemnity of the Passover. For seven days, unleavened bread shall be eaten.

22 And on that day, the prince shall offer, on behalf of himself and on behalf of all the people of the land, a calf for sin.

23 And during the solemnity of the seven days, he shall offer a holocaust to the Lord of seven immaculate calves and seven immaculate rams, daily for seven days, and a he-goat from among the she-goats, daily for sin.

24 And he shall offer the sacrifice of an ephah for each calf, and an ephah for each ram, and a hin of oil for every ephah.

25 In the seventh month, on the fifteenth day of the month, during the solemnities, he shall do just as was said above for the seven days, as much for the sin offering, as for the holocaust and sacrifice and oil."

Ezekiel 46

1 Thus says the Lord God: "The gate of the inner court which looks toward the east shall be closed for the six days on which work is done. Then, on the Sabbath day, it shall be opened. But also on the day of the new moon, it shall be opened.

2 And the prince shall enter from outside, by the way of the vestibule of the gate, and he shall stand at the threshold of the gate. And the priests shall offer his holocaust and his peace offerings. And he shall adore upon the threshold of the gate, and then depart. But the gate shall not be closed until evening.

3 And the people of the land shall adore at the entrance of the same gate, on the Sabbaths and on the new moons, in the sight of the Lord.

4 Now this holocaust, which the prince shall offer to the Lord on the Sabbath day, shall be six immaculate lambs, and one immaculate ram.

5 The sacrifice shall be one ephah for each ram. But for the lambs, the sacrifice shall be whatever his hand shall give. And there shall be one hin of oil for each ephah.

6 Then, on the day of the new moon, he shall offer one immaculate calf from the herd. Both the six lambs and the rams shall be immaculate.

7 And he shall offer the sacrifice of one ephah for each calf, and also one ephah for each ram. But for the lambs, it shall be just as his hand will find. And there shall be one hin of oil for each ephah.

8 And when the prince will enter, let him enter by the way of the vestibule of the gate, and let him go out by the same way.

9 And when the people of the land will enter in the sight of the Lord on the solemnities, whoever enters by the north gate so that he may adore, shall depart by the way of the south gate. And whoever enters by the way of the south gate shall depart by the way of the north gate. He shall not return by way of the gate through which he entered. Instead, he shall depart from the direction opposite to it.

10 But the prince in their midst shall enter when they enter, and he shall depart when they depart.

11 And during the feasts and the solemnities, there shall be the sacrifice of one ephah for each calf, and one ephah for each ram. But for the lambs, the sacrifice shall be just as his hand will find. And there shall be one hin of oil for each ephah.

12 But when the prince will offer a voluntary holocaust or a voluntary peace offering to the Lord, the gate which looks toward the east shall be opened to him. And he shall offer his holocaust and his peace offerings, just as is usually done on the Sabbath day. And he shall depart, and the gate shall be closed after he has gone out.

13 And daily he shall offer, as a holocaust to the Lord, an immaculate lamb of the same age. He shall offer it always in the morning.

14 And he shall offer as a sacrifice with it, morning after morning, one sixth part of an ephah, and one third part of a hin of oil, to be mixed with the fine flour, as a sacrifice to the Lord, by a continual and everlasting ordinance.

15 He shall offer the lamb and the sacrifice and the oil, morning after morning, as an everlasting holocaust.

16 Thus says the Lord God: If the prince grants a gift to any of his sons, the inheritance of it will go to his sons; they shall possess it as an inheritance.

17 But if he grants a legacy from his inheritance to one of his servants, it shall be his only until the year of remission, and then it shall be returned to the prince. For his inheritance shall go to his sons.

18 And the prince shall not take from the inheritance of the people by force, nor from their possession. Instead, from his own possession, he shall give an inheritance to his sons, so that my people will not be scattered, each one from his possession."

19 And he led me in by the entrance which was at the side of the gate, into the storerooms of the sanctuary for the priests, which looked toward the north. And there was a place there which verged toward the west.

20 And he said to me: "This is the place where the priests will cook the offering for sin and the offering for trespasses. Here, they shall cook the sacrifice, so that they need not carry it to the outer court, and so that the people may be sanctified."

21 And he led me away to the outer court, and he led me around by the four corners of the court. And behold, there was a little atrium at the corner of the court; a little atrium was at each corner of the court.

22 At the four corners of the court, little atriums were positioned, forty cubits in length, and thirty in width; each of the four were of the same measure.

23 And there was a wall all around, encircling the four little atriums. And kitchens had been constructed under the porticos on all sides.

24 And he said to me: "This is the house of the kitchens, in which the ministers of the house of the Lord will cook the victims of the people."

Ezekiel 47

1 And he turned me back to the gate of the house. And behold, waters went out, from under the threshold of the house, toward the east. For the face of the house looked toward the east. But the waters descended on the right side of the temple, toward the south of the altar.

2 And he led me out, along the way of the north gate, and he turned me back toward the way outside the exterior gate, the way which looked toward the east. And behold, the waters overflowed on the right side.

3 Then the man who held the rope in his hand departed toward the east, and he measured one thousand cubits. And he led me forward, through the water, up to the ankles.

4 And again he measured one thousand, and he led me forward, through the water, up to the knees.

5 And he measured one thousand, and he led me forward, through the water, up to the waist. And he measured one thousand, into a torrent, through which I was not able to pass. For the waters had risen to become a profound torrent, which was not able to be crossed.

6 And he said to me: "Son of man, certainly you have seen." And he led me out, and he turned me back to the bank of the torrent.

7 And when I had turned myself around, behold, on the bank of the torrent, there were very many trees on both sides.

8 And he said to me: "These waters, which go forth toward the hillocks of sand to the east, and which descend to the plains of the desert, will enter the sea, and will go out, and the waters will be healed.

9 And every living soul that moves, wherever the torrent arrives, will live. And there will be more than enough fish, after these waters have arrived there, and they will be healed. And all things will live, where the torrent arrives.

10 And fishermen will stand over these waters. There will be the drying of nets, from Engedi even to Eneglaim. There will be very many kinds of fish within it: a very great multitude, like the fish of the great sea.

11 But on its shore and in the marshes, they will not be healed. For these will be made into salt pits.

12 And above the torrent, on its banks on both sides, every kind of fruit tree will rise up. Their foliage will not fall away, and their fruit will not fail. Every single month they will bring forth first-fruits. For its waters will go forth from the sanctuary. And its fruits will be for food, and its leaves will be for medicine."

13 Thus says the Lord God: "This is the border, by which you shall possess the land, in accord with the twelve tribes of Israel. For Joseph shall have a double portion.

14 And you shall possess it, each one in equal manner as his brother. I lifted up my hand over it, so that I might give it to your fathers. And this land shall fall to you as a possession.

15 Now this is the border of the land toward the northern region, from the great sea, by the way of Hethlon, arriving at Zedad:

16 Hamath, Berothah, Sibraim, which is between the border of Damascus and the confines of Hamath, the house of Ticon, which is beside the border of Hauran,

17 and the border will be from the sea, even to the entrance of Enon, at the border of Damascus, and from the north to the north, at the border of Hamath, on the northern side.

18 Moreover, the eastern region will be from the midst of Hauran, and from the midst of Damascus, and from the midst of Gilead, and from the midst of the land of Israel, to the Jordan, marking the boundary to the eastern sea. For so shall you measure the eastern region.

19 Now the southern region, toward the meridian, will be from Tamar, even to the Waters of Contradiction at Kadesh, and from the Torrent, even to the great sea. And this is the southern region, toward the meridian.

20 And the region toward the sea will have its confines from the great sea continuing directly until one arrives at Hamath. This is the region of the sea.

21 And you shall divide this land among yourselves according to the tribes of Israel.

22 And you shall distribute it by lot as an inheritance, for yourselves and for the new arrival who will be added to you, who will conceive sons in your midst. And they shall be to you as the indigenous among the sons of Israel. They shall divide the possession with you, in the midst of the tribes of Israel.

23 And in whatever tribe the new arrival will be, there you shall give a possession to him, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 48

1 "And these are the names of the tribes, from the parts of the north, beside the way of Hethlon, continuing on to Hamath, at the entrance of Enon, to the border of Damascus toward the north, beside the way of Hamath. And from the region of the east to the sea, there will be one portion for Dan.

2 And beyond the border of Dan, from the eastern region, even to the region of the sea, there shall be one portion for Asher.

3 And beyond the border of Asher, from the eastern region, even to the region of the sea, there shall be one portion for Naphtali.

4 And beyond the border of Naphtali, from the eastern region, even to the region of the sea, there shall be one portion for Manasseh.

5 And beyond the border of Manasseh, from the eastern region, even to the region of the sea, there shall be one portion for Ephraim.

6 And beyond the border of Ephraim, from the eastern region, even to the region of the sea, there shall be one portion for Reuben.

7 And beyond the border of Reuben, from the eastern region, even to the region of the sea, there shall be one portion for Judah.

8 And beyond the border of Judah, from the eastern region, even to the region of the sea, there shall be the first-fruits, which you shall separate, twenty-five thousand in width, and in length, the same as each one of the portions from the eastern region, even to the region of the sea. And the sanctuary shall be in its midst.

9 The first-fruits, which you shall separate to the Lord, shall be, in length, twenty-five thousand, and in width, ten thousand.

10 And these shall be the first-fruits for the sanctuary of the priests: toward the north, in length, twenty-five thousand, and toward the sea, in width, ten thousand, but also, toward the east, in width, ten thousand, and toward the south, in length, twenty-five thousand. And the sanctuary of the Lord shall be in its midst.

11 The sanctuary shall be for the priests from the sons of Zadok, who observed my ceremonies and did not go astray, when the sons of Israel went astray, just as the Levites also went astray.

12 And so the foremost of the first-fruits of the land, the Holy of Holies, beside the border of the Levites, shall be for them.

13 But also the Levites, similarly, shall have, beside the borders of the priests, twenty-five thousand in length, and ten thousand in width. The entire length shall be twenty-five thousand, and the width shall be ten thousand.

14 And they shall not sell from it, nor exchange, and the first-fruits of the land shall not be transferred. For these have been sanctified to the Lord.

15 But the five thousand that is left over, out of the twenty-five thousand in width, will be a profane place of the city for dwelling and for the suburbs. And the city shall be in the center.

16 And these shall be its measurements: on the northern side, four thousand and five hundred; and on the southern side, four thousand and five hundred; and on the eastern side, four thousand and five hundred; and on the western side, four thousand and five hundred.

17 But the suburbs of the city shall be: to the north, two hundred and fifty; and to the south, two hundred and fifty; and to the east, two hundred and fifty; and to the sea, two hundred and fifty.

18 Now what will remain of the length, in accord with the first-fruits of the sanctuary, ten thousand in the east, and ten thousand in the west, shall be as the first-fruits of the sanctuary. And its produce will be for the bread of those who serve the city.

19 And those who serve the city will be taken from all the tribes of Israel.

20 All the first-fruits, of the twenty-five thousand by twenty-five thousand square, shall be separated as the first-fruits of the sanctuary and as the possession of the city.

21 And what will remain shall be for the prince out of every portion of the first-fruits of the sanctuary and of the possession of the city, from the region of the twenty-five thousand of the first-fruits, even to the eastern border. But also to the sea from the region of the twenty-five thousand, even to the border of the sea, similarly shall be the portion of the prince. And the first-fruits of the sanctuary, and the sanctuary of the temple, shall be in its center.

22 Now from the possession of the Levites, and from the possession of the city, which are in the midst of the prince's portions, whatever is between the border of Judah and the border of Benjamin, shall also belong to the prince.

23 And for the remainder of the tribes, from the eastern region, even to the western region, there shall be one portion for Benjamin.

24 And opposite the border of Benjamin, from the eastern region, even to the western region, there shall be one portion for Simeon.

25 And beyond the border of Simeon, from the eastern region, even to the western region, there shall be one portion for Issachar.

26 And beyond the border of Issachar, from the eastern region, even to the western region, there shall be one portion for Zebulun.

27 And beyond the border of Zebulun, from the eastern region, even to the region of the sea, there shall be one portion for Gad.

28 And beyond the border of Gad, toward the southern region, in the meridian, the last part shall be from Tamar, even to the Waters of Contradiction at Kadesh, as the inheritance opposite the great sea.

29 This is the land that you shall distribute by lot to the tribes of Israel, and these shall be their portions, says the Lord God.

30 And these shall be the exits of the city: from the northern region, you shall measure four thousand and five hundred.

31 And the gates of the city shall be according to the names of the tribes of Israel. There shall be three gates from the north: the gate of Reuben one, the gate of Judah one, the gate of Levi one.

32 And to the eastern region, there shall be four thousand and five hundred. And there shall be three gates: the gate of Joseph one, the gate of Benjamin one, the gate of Dan one.

33 And to the southern region, you shall measure four thousand and five hundred. And there shall be three gates: the gate of Simeon one, the gate of Issachar one, the gate of Zebulun one.

34 And to the western region, there shall be four thousand and five hundred, and their three gates: the gate of Gad one, the gate of Asher one, the gate of Naphtali one.

35 Along circumference, there shall be eighteen thousand. And the name of the city, from that day, shall be: 'The Lord is in that very place.' "

Daniel 1

1 In the third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came to Jerusalem and besieged it.

2 And the Lord delivered into his hand Jehoiakim the king of Judah and a portion of the vessels of the house of God. And he carried them away into the land of Shinar, to the house of his god, and he brought the vessels into the treasure chamber of his god.

3 And the king told Ashpenaz, the chief of the eunuchs, that he should bring in some of the sons of Israel, and some of the offspring of the king and of the sovereigns:

4 young men, in whom there was no blemish, noble in appearance, and accomplished in all wisdom, cautious in knowledge, and well-educated, and who could stand in the palace of the king, so that he might teach them the letters and the language of the Chaldeans.

5 And the king appointed for them provisions for each day, from his own food and from the wine which he himself drank, so that, after being nourished for three years, they would stand in the sight of the king.

6 Now, among those of the sons of Judah, there were Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah.

7 And the chief of the eunuchs assigned names to them: to Daniel, Belteshazzar; to Hananiah, Shadrach; to Mishael, Meshach; and to Azariah, Abednego.

8 But Daniel resolved in his heart that he would not be polluted with the king's meal, nor with the wine he drank, and he requested of the chief of the eunuchs that he might not be contaminated.

9 And so God gave Daniel grace and mercy in the sight of the leader of the eunuchs.

10 And the leader of the eunuchs said to Daniel, "I am afraid of my lord the king, who has appointed food and drink for you, who, if he should see that your faces are leaner than those of the other youths your age, you would condemn my head to the king."

11 And Daniel said to Malasar, whom the leader of the eunuchs had appointed over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah,

12 "I beg you to test us, your servants, for ten days, and let roots be given to us to eat and water to drink,

13 and then observe our faces, and the faces of the children who eat the king's food, and then deal with your servants according to what you see."

14 When he had heard these words, he tested them for ten days.

15 But, after ten days, their faces appeared better and fatter than all the children who had eaten from the king's food.

16 Thereafter, Malasar took away their portions and their wine for drinking, and he gave them roots.

17 Yet, to these children, God gave knowledge and instruction in every book, and wisdom, but to Daniel, also the understanding of all visions and dreams.

18 And when the time was completed, after which the king had said that they would be brought in, the chief of the eunuchs brought them in before the sight of Nebuchadnezzar.

19 And, when the king conversed with them, there had not been found any so great in all the world as Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah; and so they stood in the sight of the king.

20 And in every concept of wisdom and understanding, about which the king consulted with them, he found them to be ten times better than all the seers and astrologers put together, who were in his entire kingdom.

21 And so Daniel remained, even until the first year of king Cyrus.

Daniel 2

1 In the second year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuchadnezzar saw a dream, and his spirit was terrified, and his dream fled from him.

2 Yet the king commanded that the seers, and the astrologers, and the sorcerers, and the Chaldeans be gathered together to reveal to the king his dreams. When they arrived, they stood in front of the king.

3 And the king said to them, "I saw a dream, and, being confused in mind, I do not know what I saw."

4 And the Chaldeans answered the king in Syriac, "O king, live forever. Tell the dream to your servants, and we will reveal its interpretation."

5 And in answer, the king said to the Chaldeans, "The memory of it has slipped away from me. Unless you reveal the dream to me, and its meaning, you will be put to death, and your houses will be confiscated.

6 But if you explain the dream and its meaning, you will receive from me rewards, and gifts, and great honor. Therefore, reveal to me the dream and its interpretation."

7 They answered again and said, "Let the king tell the dream to his servants, and we will reveal its interpretation."

8 The king answered and said, "I am certain that you are stalling for time because you know that the memory of it has slipped away from me.

9 Therefore, if you do not reveal to me the dream, there is only one conclusion to be reached about you, that the interpretation is likewise false, and packed full of deception, so as to speak before me until the time passes away. And so, tell me the dream, so that I will also know that the interpretation that you tell me is likewise true."

10 Then the Chaldeans answered before the king, and they said, "There is no man on earth who can accomplish your word, O king. For neither has any king, however great and mighty, asked for an answer of this kind from every seer, and astrologer, and Chaldean.

11 For the answer that you seek, O king, is very difficult. Neither can anyone be found who can reveal it in the sight of the king, except the gods, whose conversation is not with men."

12 When he heard this, the king commanded, in fury and in great wrath, that all the wise men of Babylon should be destroyed.

13 And when the decree had gone forth, the wise men were put to death; and Daniel and his companions were sought, to be destroyed.

14 Then Daniel inquired, about the law and the sentence, of Arioch, the general of the king's army, who had gone forth to execute the wise men of Babylon.

15 And he asked him, who had received the orders of the king, for what reason such a cruel sentence had gone forth from the face of the king. And so, when Arioch had revealed the matter to Daniel,

16 Daniel went in and asked of the king that he would grant him time to reveal the solution to the king.

17 And he went into his house and explained the task to Hananiah, and Mishael, and Azariah, his companions,

18 so that they would seek mercy before the face of the God of heaven, about this mystery, and so that Daniel and his companions might not perish with the other wise men of Babylon.

19 Then the secret was revealed to Daniel by a vision in the night. And Daniel blessed the God of heaven,

20 and speaking aloud, he said, "May the name of the Lord be blessed by the present generation and for ever; for wisdom and fortitude are his.

21 And he alters the times and the ages. He takes away kingdoms and he establishes them. He gives wisdom to those who are wise and teaching skills to those who understand.

22 He reveals deep and hidden things, and he knows what has been established in darkness. And the light is with him.

23 To you, God of our fathers, I confess, and you, I praise. For you have given wisdom and fortitude to me, and now you have revealed to me what we asked of you, for you have uncovered for us the king's thoughts."

24 After this, Daniel went in to Arioch, whom the king had appointed to destroy the wise men of Babylon, and he spoke to him in this way, "Do not destroy the wise men of Babylon. Bring me in before the king, and I will explain the solution to the king."

25 Then Arioch quickly brought Daniel to the king, and he said to him, "I have found a man of the sons of the transmigration of Judah, who would announce the solution to the king."

26 The king answered and said to Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, "Do you really think that you can reveal to me the dream that I saw and its interpretation?"

27 And Daniel, facing the king, answered and said, "The secret that the king seeks, the wise men, the seers, and the soothsayers are unable to reveal to the king.

28 But there is a God in heaven who reveals mysteries, who has revealed to you, king Nebuchadnezzar, what will happen in the latter times. Your dream and the visions of your head upon your bed, are such as these.

29 You, O king, began to think, while in your blanket, about what will be hereafter. And he who reveals secrets showed you what will happen.

30 To me, likewise, this mystery is revealed, not according to the wisdom that is in me more than in other living things, but so that the interpretation might be made manifest to the king, and so that you may know the thoughts of your mind.

31 You, O king, saw, and behold, something like a great statue. This statue, which was great and high, stood exalted above you, and you considered how terrible it was.

32 The head of this statue was of the finest gold, but the breast and the arms were of silver, and further on, the belly and the thighs were of brass;

33 but the shins were of iron, a certain part of the feet were of iron and another part were of clay.

34 And so you looked until a stone was broken off without hands from a mountain, and it struck the statue on its feet, which were of iron and clay, and it shattered them.

35 Then the iron, the clay, the brass, the silver, and the gold were crushed together and diminished like the ashes of a summer courtyard, and they were quickly taken away by the wind, and no place was found for them; but the stone that struck the statue became a great mountain and filled the whole earth.

36 This is the dream; we will also tell its interpretation before you, O king.

37 You are a king among kings, and the God of heaven has given to you a kingdom, and fortitude, and power, and glory,

38 and all the places wherein the sons of men and the beasts of the field dwell. He has likewise given the flying creatures of the air into your hand, and he has placed all things under your realm. Therefore, you are the head of gold.

39 And after you, another kingdom will rise up, inferior to you, of silver, and another third kingdom of brass, which will rule over the whole world.

40 And the fourth kingdom will be like iron. Just as iron shatters and conquers all things, so will it shatter and crush all these.

41 Furthermore, because you saw the feet and the toes to be part of potter's clay and part of iron, the kingdom will be divided, but still, from the slip of iron it will take its origin, since you saw the iron mingled with the earthenware from clay.

42 And as the toes of the feet were partly of iron and partly of clay, part the kingdom will be strong and part will be crushed.

43 Yet, because you saw the iron mingled with pottery from the earth, they will indeed be combined together with the offspring of man, but they will not adhere to one another, just as iron cannot be mixed with earthenware.

44 But in the days of those kingdoms, the God of heaven will inspire a kingdom that will never be destroyed, and his kingdom will not be handed over to another people, and it will crush and will consume all these kingdoms, and this kingdom itself will stand in eternity.

45 In accordance with what you saw, because the stone was torn away from the mountain without hands, and it crushed the earthenware, and the iron, and the brass, and the silver, and the gold, the great God has shown the king what will happen after this. And the dream is true, and its interpretation is faithful."

46 Then king Nebuchadnezzar fell on his face and adored Daniel, and he commanded that they should offer in sacrifice to him victims and incense.

47 And so the king spoke with Daniel and said, "Truly, your God is the God of gods, and Lord of kings, and also a revealer of secrets, since you could uncover this mystery."

48 Then the king raised Daniel to a high rank and gave him many great gifts, and he appointed him as leader over all the provinces of Babylon and as chief of the magistrates over all the other wise men of Babylon.

49 However, Daniel required of the king that he appoint Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego over the works of the province of Babylon. But Daniel himself was at the king's door.

Daniel 3

1 King Nebuchadnezzar made a statue of gold, sixty cubits high and six cubits wide, and he set it up in the plain of Dura in the province of Babylon.

2 Then king Nebuchadnezzar sent to gather together the governors, magistrates and judges, generals and sovereigns and commanders, and all the leaders of the regions, to come together for the dedication of the statue, which king Nebuchadnezzar had raised.

3 Then the governors, magistrates and judges, generals and sovereigns and nobles, who were appointed to power, and all the leaders of the regions were brought together so as to convene for the dedication of the statue, which king Nebuchadnezzar had raised. And so they stood before the statue that king Nebuchadnezzar had set up.

4 And a herald proclaimed loudly, "To you it is said, to you peoples, tribes, and languages,

5 that in the hour when you will hear the sound of the trumpet and the pipe and the lute, the harp and the psaltery, and of the symphony and every kind of music, you must fall down and adore the gold statue, which king Nebuchadnezzar has set up.

6 But if anyone will not bow down and adore, in the same hour he will be cast into a furnace of burning fire."

7 After this, therefore, as soon as all the people heard the sound of the trumpet, the pipe and the lute, the harp and the psaltery, and of the symphony and every kind of music, all the peoples, tribes, and languages fell down and adored the gold statue, which king Nebuchadnezzar had set up.

8 And soon, about the same time, some influential Chaldeans came and accused the Jews,

9 and they said to king Nebuchadnezzar, "O king, live forever.

10 You, O king, have established a decree, so that every man who might hear the sound of the trumpet, the pipe and the lute, the harp and the psaltery, and of the symphony and every kind of music, will prostrate himself and adore the gold statue.

11 But if any man will not fall down and adore, he would be cast into a furnace of burning fire.

12 Yet there are influential Jews, whom you have appointed over the works of the region of Babylon, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. These men, O king, have scorned your decree. They do not worship your gods, and they do not adore the gold statue which you have raised up."

13 Then Nebuchadnezzar, in fury and in wrath, commanded that Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego should be brought, and so, without delay, they were brought before the king.

14 And king Nebuchadnezzar addressed them and said, "Is it true, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, that you do not worship my gods, nor adore the gold statue, which I have set up?

15 Therefore, if you are prepared now, whenever you hear the sound of the trumpet, pipe, lute, harp and psaltery, and of the symphony and every kind of music, prostrate yourselves and adore the statue which I have made. But if you will not adore, in the same hour you will be cast into the furnace of burning fire. And who is the God that will rescue you from my hand?"

16 Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego answered and said to king Nebuchadnezzar, "It is not right for us to obey you in this matter.

17 For behold our God, whom we worship, is able to rescue us from the oven of burning fire and to free us from your hands, O king.

18 But even if he will not, let it be known to you, O king, that we will not worship your gods, nor adore the gold statue, which you have raised up."

19 Then Nebuchadnezzar was filled with fury and the appearance of his face was changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, and he commanded that the furnace should be heated to seven times its usual fire.

20 And he ordered the strongest men of his army to bind the feet of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, and to cast them into the furnace of burning fire.

21 And immediately these men were bound, and along with their coats, and their hats, and their shoes, and their garments, were cast into the middle of the furnace of burning fire.

22 But the king's order was so urgent that the furnace was heated excessively. As a result, those men who had cast in Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, were killed by the flame of the fire.

23 But these three men, that is, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, having been bound, fell down in the middle of the oven of burning fire.

24 And they were walking in the midst of the flame, praising God and blessing the Lord.

25 Then Azariah, while standing, prayed in this manner, and opening his mouth in the midst of the fire, he said:

26 "Blessed are you, O Lord, the God of our fathers, and your name is praiseworthy and glorious for all ages.

27 For you are just in all the things that you have accomplished for us, and all your works are true, and your ways are right, and all your judgments are true.

28 For you have made equally true judgments in all the things that you have brought upon us and upon Jerusalem, the holy city of our fathers. For in truth and in judgment, you have brought down all these things because of our sins.

29 For we have sinned, and we have committed iniquity in withdrawing from you, and we have offended in all things.

30 And we have not listened to your precepts, nor have we observed or done as you have ordered us, so that it might go well with us.

31 Therefore, everything that you have brought upon us, and all that you have done for us, you have done in true judgment.

32 And you have delivered us into the hands of our enemies: traitors, unjust and most wicked, and to a king, unjust and most wicked, even more so than all others on earth.

33 And now we are not able to open our mouths. We have become a shame and a disgrace to your servants and to those who worship you.

34 Do not hand us over forever, we ask you, because of your name, and do not abolish your covenant.

35 And do not withdraw your mercy from us, because of Abraham, your beloved, and Isaac, your servant, and Israel, your holy one.

36 You have spoken with them, promising that you would multiply their offspring like the stars of heaven and like the sand on the seashore.

37 For we, O Lord, are diminished more than all other peoples, and we are brought low throughout all the earth, this day, because of our sins.

38 Neither is there, at this time, a leader, or a ruler, or a prophet, nor any holocaust, or sacrifice, or oblation, or incense, or place of first fruits, in your eyes,

39 so that we may be able to find your mercy. Nevertheless, with a contrite soul and humble spirit, let us be accepted.

40 Just as in the holocausts of rams and bullocks, and as in thousands of fat lambs, so let our sacrifice be in your sight this day, in order to please you. For there is no shame for those who trust in you.

41 And now we follow you wholeheartedly, and we fear you, and we seek your face.

42 Do not put us to shame, but deal with us in agreement with your clemency and according to the multitude of your mercies.

43 And rescue us by your wonders and give glory to your name, O Lord.

44 And let all those be confounded who lead your servants towards evil. May they be confounded by all your power and may their strength be crushed.

45 And may they know that you are the Lord, the only God, and glorious above the world."

46 And they did not cease, those attendants of the king who had cast them in, to heat the furnace with oil, and flax, and pitch, and brush.

47 And the flame streamed forth above the furnace for forty-nine cubits.

48 And the fire erupted and burnt those of the Chaldeans within its reach near the furnace.

49 But the angel of the Lord descended with Azariah and his companions into the furnace; and he cast the flame of the fire out of the furnace.

50 And he made the middle of the furnace like the blowing of a damp wind, and the fire did not touch them, nor afflict them, nor bother them at all.

51 Then these three, as if with one voice, praised and glorified and blessed God, in the furnace, saying:

52 "Blessed are you, Lord, God of our fathers: praiseworthy, and glorious, and exalted above all forever. And blessed is the holy name of your glory: praiseworthy, and exalted above all, for all ages.

53 Blessed are you in the holy temple of your glory: praiseworthy above all and exalted above all forever.

54 Blessed are you on the throne of your kingdom: praiseworthy above all and exalted above all forever.

55 Blessed are you who beholds the abyss and sits upon the cherubims: praiseworthy and exalted above all forever.

56 Blessed are you in the firmament of heaven: praiseworthy and glorious forever.

57 All works of the Lord, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

58 Angels of the Lord, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

59 Heaven, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

60 All waters that are above the heavens, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

61 All powers of the Lord, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

62 Sun and moon, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

63 Stars of heaven, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

64 Every rain and dew, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

65 Every breath of God, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

66 Fire and steam, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

67 Cold and heat, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

68 Dews and frost, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

69 Sleet and winter, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

70 Ice and snow, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

71 Nights and days, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

72 Light and darkness, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

73 Lightning and clouds, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

74 May the land bless the Lord: and praise and exalt him above all forever.

75 Mountains and hills, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

76 All things that grow in the land, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

77 Fountains, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

78 Seas and rivers, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

79 Whales and all things that move in the waters, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

80 All things that fly in the heavens, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

81 All beasts and cattle, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

82 Sons of men, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

83 May Israel bless the Lord: and praise and exalt him above all forever.

84 Priests of the Lord, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

85 Servants of the Lord, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

86 Spirits and souls of the just, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

87 Those who are holy and humble in heart, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.

88 Hananiah, Azariah, Mishael, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever. For he has delivered us from the underworld, and saved us from the hand of death, and freed us from the midst of the burning flame, and rescued us from the midst of the fire.

89 Give thanks to the Lord because he is good: because his mercy is forever.

90 All those who are pious, bless the Lord, the God of gods: praise him and acknowledge him because his mercy is for all generations."

91 Then king Nebuchadnezzar was astonished, and he quickly got up and said to his nobles: "Did we not cast three men shackled into the midst of the fire?" Answering the king, they said, "True, O king."

92 He answered and said, "Behold, I see four men unbound and walking in the midst of the fire, and no harm is in them, and the appearance of the fourth is like a son of God."

93 Then Nebuchadnezzar approached the entrance of the furnace of burning fire, and he said, "Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, servants of the supreme God, come out and approach." And immediately Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego went out from the midst of the fire.

94 And when the governors, and the magistrates, and the judges, and the powerful of the king had gathered together, they considered these men because the fire had no power against their bodies, and not a hair of their head had been scorched, and their pants had not been affected, and the smell of the fire had not passed onto them.

95 Then Nebuchadnezzar, bursting out, said, "Blessed is their God, the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, who sent his angel and rescued his servants who believed in him. And they altered the verdict of the king, and they delivered up their bodies, so that they would not serve or adore any god except their God.

96 Therefore, this decree is established by me: that every people, tribe, and language, whenever they have spoken blasphemy against the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, will perish and their homes will be destroyed. For there is no other God who is able to save in this way."

97 Then the king promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego in the province of Babylon.

98 NEBUCHADNEZZAR, the king, to all peoples, nations, and languages, who dwell in the whole world, may peace be increased with you.

99 The supreme God has accomplished signs and wonders with me. Therefore, it has pleased me to proclaim

100 his signs, which are great, and his wonders, which are mighty. For his kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and his power continues from generation to generation.

Daniel 4

1 I, Nebuchadnezzar, was content in my house and prospering in my palace.

2 I saw a dream that terrified me, and my thoughts on my bed and the visions in my head disturbed me.

3 And so a decree was established by me, that all of the wise men of Babylon should be brought in before me, and that they should reveal to me the answer to the dream.

4 Then the seers, the astrologers, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers entered, and I explained about the dream in their presence, but they did not reveal its answer to me.

5 And then their colleague came in before me, Daniel, (whose name is Belteshazzar according to the name of my god,) who has the spirit of the holy gods within his very self, and I told the dream directly to him.

6 Belteshazzar, leader of the seers, since I know that you have in you the spirit of the holy gods, and that no mystery is unreachable to you, explain to me the visions of my dreams, which I saw, and the solution to them.

7 This was the vision of my head on my bed. I looked, and behold, a tree in the middle of the earth, and its height was exceedingly great.

8 The tree was great and strong, and its height reached up to heaven. It could be seen all the way to the ends of the entire earth.

9 Its leaves were very beautiful, and its fruit was very abundant, and in it was food for the whole world. Under it, animals and beasts were dwelling, and in its branches, the birds of the sky were sheltered, and from it, all flesh was fed.

10 I saw in the vision of my head upon my blanket, and behold, a watcher and a holy one descended from heaven.

11 He cried out loudly, and he said this: "Cut down the tree and prune its branches; shake off its leaves and scatter its fruits; let flee the beasts, which are under it, and the birds from its branches.

12 Nevertheless, leave the stump of its roots in the earth, and let it be bound with a band of iron and brass among the plants, which are close by, and let it be touched by the dew of heaven, and let its place be with the wild animals among the plants of the earth.

13 Let his heart be changed from being human, and let the heart of a wild animal be given to him, and let seven periods of time pass over him.

14 This is the decree from the judgment of the watchers, and the decision and proclamation of the holy ones, until the living shall know that the Supreme One is ruler in the kingdom of men, and that he will give it to whomever he wills, and he will appoint the lowest man over it."

15 I, king Nebuchadnezzar, saw this dream. And so you, Belteshazzar, must quickly explain to me the interpretation because all the wise men of my kingdom are not able to declare the meaning of it to me. But you are able because the spirit of the holy gods is in you.

16 Then Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, began silently to think within himself for about one hour, and his thoughts troubled him. But the king responded, saying, "Belteshazzar, do not let the dream and its interpretation disturb you." Belteshazzar answered and said, "My lord, the dream is for those who hate you, and its interpretation may be for your enemies.

17 The tree that you saw was lofty and strong; its height reached toward heaven, and it could be seen throughout the whole world.

18 And its branches were very beautiful, and its fruit very abundant, and in it was food for all. Under it, dwelt the beasts of the field, and in its branches, the birds of the air stayed.

19 It is you, O king, who has been greatly esteemed, and you have grown strong. And you have increased your power, and it reaches towards heaven, and your rule is to the ends of the whole earth.

20 Yet the king also saw a watcher and a holy one descend from heaven and say: 'Cut down the tree and scatter it; however, leave the stump of its roots in the earth, and let it be bound with iron and brass, among the surrounding plants, and let it be sprinkled with the dew of heaven, and let his feeding be with the wild beasts, until seven periods of time pass over him.'

21 This is the interpretation of the judgment of the Most High, which has reached my lord, the king.

22 They will expel you from among men, and your dwelling will be with the beasts and the wild animals, and you will eat hay like an ox, and you will be drenched with the dew of heaven. Likewise, seven periods of time will pass over you, until you know that the Supreme One rules over the kingdom of men, and he gives it to whomever he wills.

23 But, since he commanded that the stump of its roots, that is, of the tree, should be left behind, your kingdom will be left for you, after you have realized that power is from divinity.

24 Because of this, O king, let my counsel be acceptable to you. And redeem your sins with alms, and your iniquities with mercy towards the poor. Perhaps he will forgive your offenses."

25 All these things came upon king Nebuchadnezzar.

26 After the end of twelve months, he was taking a walk in the palace of Babylon.

27 And the king spoke out loud, saying, "Isn't this the great Babylon, which I have built, as the home of the kingdom, by the strength of my power and in the glory of my excellence?"

28 And while the words were still in the king's mouth, a voice rushed down from heaven, "To you, O king Nebuchadnezzar, it is said: 'Your kingdom will be taken away from you,

29 and they will expel you from among men, and your dwelling will be with the beasts and the wild animals. You will eat hay like an ox, and seven times will pass over you, until you know that the Supreme One rules in the kingdom of men, and he gives it to whomever he wills.' "

30 The same hour, the sentence was fulfilled upon Nebuchadnezzar, and he was driven away from among men, and he ate hay like an ox, and his body was drenched with the dew of heaven, until his hair increased like the feathers of eagles, and his nails like those of birds.

31 Therefore, at the end of these days, I, Nebuchadnezzar, lifted up my eyes to heaven, and my mind was restored to me. And I blessed the Most High, and I praised and glorified him who lives forever. For his power is an everlasting power, and his kingdom is from generation to generation.

32 And all the inhabitants of the earth are reputed as nothing before him. For he acts according to his own will, with the inhabitants of the earth just as with the holy inhabitants of heaven. And there is no one who can resist his hand, or say to him, "Why have you done this?"

33 At the same time, my mind returned to me, and I arrived at the honor and glory of my kingdom. And my appearance was given back to me. And my nobles and my magistrates needed me. And I was restored to my kingdom, and even greater majesty was added to me.

34 Therefore I, Nebuchadnezzar, now praise, and magnify, and glorify the King of heaven, because all his works and the judgments of his way are true, and those who go forth in arrogance, he is able to bring low.

Daniel 5

1 Belshazzar, the king, made a great feast for a thousand of his nobles, and each one of them drank according to his age.

2 And so, when they were drunk, he instructed that the vessels of gold and silver should be brought, which Nebuchadnezzar, his father, had carried away from the temple, which was in Jerusalem, so that the king, and his nobles, and his wives, and the concubines, might drink from them.

3 Then the gold and silver vessels were presented, which he had carried away from the temple and which had been in Jerusalem, and the king, and his nobles, wives, and concubines, drank from them.

4 They drank wine, and they praised their gods of gold, and silver, brass, iron, and wood and stone.

5 In the same hour, there appeared fingers, as of the hand of a man, writing on the surface of the wall, opposite the candlestick, in the king's palace. And the king observed the part of the hand that wrote.

6 Then the king's countenance was changed, and his thoughts disturbed him, and he lost his self-control, and his knees knocked against one other.

7 And the king cried out loudly for them to bring in the astrologers, Chaldeans, and soothsayers. And the king proclaimed to the wise men of Babylon, saying, "Whoever will read this writing and make known to me its interpretation will be clothed with purple, and will have a golden chain on his neck, and will be third in my kingdom."

8 Then, in came all the wise men of the king, but they could neither read the writing, nor reveal the interpretation to the king.

9 Therefore, king Belshazzar was quite confused, and his face was altered, and even his nobles were disturbed.

10 But the queen, because of what had happened to the king and his nobles, entered the banquet house. And she spoke out, saying, "O king, live forever. Do not let your thoughts confuse you, neither should your face be altered.

11 There is a man in your kingdom, who has the spirit of the holy gods within himself, and in the days of your father, knowledge and wisdom were found in him. For king Nebuchadnezzar, your father, appointed him leader of the astrologers, enchanters, Chaldeans, and soothsayers, even your father, I say to you, O king.

12 For a greater spirit, and foresight, and understanding, and interpretation of dreams, and the revealing of secrets, and the solution to difficulties were found in him, that is, in Daniel, to whom the king gave the name Belteshazzar. Now, therefore, let Daniel be summoned, and he will explain the interpretation."

13 Then Daniel was brought in before the king. And the king spoke to him, saying, "Are you Daniel, of the sons of the captivity of Judah, whom my father the king led out of Judea?

14 I have heard of you, that you have the spirit of the gods, and that greater knowledge, as well as understanding and wisdom, have been found in you.

15 And now the wise astrologers have entered into my presence, so as to read this writing and to reveal to me its interpretation. And they were not able to tell me the meaning of this writing.

16 Furthermore, I have heard about you that you can interpret obscure things and solve difficulties. So then, if you succeed in reading the writing, and in revealing its interpretation, you will be clothed with purple, and you will have a chain of gold around your neck, and you will be the third leader in my kingdom."

17 To this Daniel responded by saying directly to the king, "Your rewards should be for yourself, and the gifts of your house you may give to another, but I will read to you the writing, O king, and I will reveal to you its interpretation.

18 O king, the Most High God gave to Nebuchadnezzar, your father, a kingdom and greatness, glory and honor.

19 And because of the greatness that he gave to him, all peoples, tribes, and languages trembled and were afraid of him. Whomever he wished, he put to death; and whomever he wished, he destroyed; and whomever he wished, he exalted; and whomever he wished, he lowered.

20 But when his heart was lifted up and his spirit was hardened in arrogance, he was deposed from the throne of his kingdom and his glory was taken away.

21 And he was expelled from the sons of men, and so his heart was placed with the beasts, and his dwelling was with the wild donkeys, and he ate hay like an ox, and his body was drenched with the dew of heaven, until he realized that the Most High holds power over the kingdom of men, and that whoever he wishes, he will set over it.

22 Likewise, you, his son Belshazzar, have not humbled your heart, though you knew all these things.

23 But you have lifted yourself up against the Lord of heaven. And the vessels of his house have been presented before you. And you, and your nobles, and your wives, and your concubines, have drunk wine from them. Likewise, you have praised the gods of silver, and gold, and brass, iron, and wood and stone, who neither see, nor hear, nor feel, yet you have not glorified the God who holds your breath and all your ways in his hand.

24 Therefore, he has sent the part of the hand which has written this, which has been inscribed.

25 But this is the writing that has been decreed: MANE, THECEL, PHARES.

26 And this is the interpretation of the words. MANE: God has numbered your kingdom and has finished it.

27 THECEL: you have been weighed on the scales and found lacking.

28 PHARES: your kingdom has been divided and has been given to the Medes and the Persians.

29 Then, by the king's command, Daniel was dressed with purple, and a chain of gold was placed around his neck, and it was proclaimed of him that he held power as the third in the kingdom.

30 That same night, king Belshazzar the Chaldean was killed.

31 And Darius the Mede succeeded to the kingdom, at the age of sixty-two years.

Daniel 6

1 It pleased Darius, and so he appointed over the kingdom one hundred twenty governors, to be placed throughout his whole kingdom.

2 And over these, three leaders, of whom Daniel was one, so that the governors would be accountable to them and the king would have no trouble.

3 And so Daniel excelled above all the leaders and governors, because a greater spirit of God was in him.

4 Furthermore, the king considered setting him over the entire kingdom; whereupon the leaders and the governors sought to find a complaint against Daniel and in favor of the king. And they could find no case, or even suspicion, because he was faithful, and no fault or suspicion was found in him.

5 Therefore, these men said, "We will not find any complaint against this Daniel, unless it is against the law of his God."

6 Then the leaders and governors took the king aside privately and spoke to him in this way: "King Darius, live forever.

7 All the leaders of your kingdom, the magistrates and governors, the senators and judges, have taken counsel that an imperial decree and edict should be published, so that all who ask any petition of any god or man for thirty days, except of you, O king, will be cast into the den of lions.

8 Now, therefore, O king, confirm this judgment and write the decree, so that what is established by the Medes and Persians may not be altered, nor will any man be allowed to transgress it."

9 And so king Darius set forth the decree and established it.

10 Now when Daniel learned of this, namely, that the law had been established, he entered his house, and, opening the windows in his upper room towards Jerusalem, he knelt down three times a day, and he adored and gave thanks before his God, as he had been accustomed to do previously.

11 Therefore, these men, inquiring diligently, discovered that Daniel was praying and making supplication to his God.

12 And they approached and spoke to the king about the edict. "O king, did you not decree that every man who makes a request to any of the gods or men for thirty days, except to yourself, O king, would be cast into the den of lions?" To which the king replied, saying, "The sentence is true, and according to the decree of the Medes and Persians, it is not lawful to violate it."

13 Then they answered and said before the king, "Daniel, of the sons of the captivity of Judah, is not concerned about your law, nor about the decree that you have established, but three times a day he prays his supplication."

14 Now when the king had heard these words, he was greatly grieved, and, on behalf of Daniel, he set his heart to free him, and he labored even until sunset to rescue him.

15 But these men, knowing the king, said to him, "You know, O king, that the law of the Medes and Persians is that every decree which the king has established may not be altered."

16 Then the king commanded, and they brought Daniel and cast him into the den of lions. And the king said to Daniel, "Your God, whom you always serve, he himself will free you."

17 And a stone was brought, and it was placed over the mouth of the den, which the king sealed with his own ring, and with the ring of his nobles, so that no one would act against Daniel.

18 And the king departed into his house, and he went to bed without eating, and food was not set before him, moreover, even sleep fled from him.

19 Then the king, getting himself up at first light, went quickly to the den of lions.

20 And coming near to the den, he cried out with a tearful voice to Daniel and spoke to him. "Daniel, servant of the living God, your God, whom you serve always, do you believe he has prevailed to free you from the lions?"

21 And Daniel, answering the king, said, "O king, live forever.

22 My God has sent his angel, and he has closed the mouths of the lions, and they have not harmed me, because before him justice has been found in me, and, even before you, O king, I have committed no offense."

23 Then was the king exceedingly glad for him, and he commanded that Daniel should be taken out of the den. And Daniel was taken out of the den, and no wound was found in him, because he believed in his God.

24 Moreover, by order of the king, those men were brought who had accused Daniel, and they were cast into the lions' den, they, and their sons, and their wives, and they did not reach the bottom of the den before the lions seized them and crushed all their bones.

25 Then king Darius wrote to all peoples, tribes, and languages dwelling in all the land. "May peace be increased with you.

26 It is hereby established by my decree that, in all my empire and my kingdom, they shall begin to tremble and fear the God of Daniel. For he is the living and eternal God forever, and his kingdom will not be destroyed, and his power will last forever.

27 He is the liberator and the savior, performing signs and wonders in heaven and on earth, who has freed Daniel from the lions' den."

28 Thereafter, Daniel continued through the reign of Darius until the reign of Cyrus, the Persian.

Daniel 7

1 In the first year of Belshazzar, king of Babylon, Daniel saw a dream and a vision in his head on his bed. And, writing down the dream, he understood it in a concise manner, and so, summarizing it tersely, he said:

2 I saw in my vision at night, and behold, the four winds of the heavens fought upon the great sea.

3 And four great beasts, different from one another, ascended from the sea.

4 The first was like a lioness and had the wings of an eagle. I watched as its wings were plucked off, and it was raised from the earth and stood on its feet like a man, and the heart of a man was given to it.

5 And behold, another beast, like a bear, stood to one side, and there were three rows in its mouth and in its teeth, and they spoke to it in this way: "Arise, devour much flesh."

6 After this, I watched, and behold, another like a leopard, and it had wings like a bird, four upon it, and four heads were on the beast, and power was given to it.

7 After this, I watched in the vision of the night, and behold, a fourth beast, terrible yet wondrous, and exceedingly strong; it had great iron teeth, eating yet crushing, and trampling down the remainder with his feet, but it was unlike the other beasts, which I had seen before it, and it had ten horns.

8 I considered the horns, and behold, another little horn rose out of the midst of them. And three of the first horns were rooted out by its presence. And behold, eyes like the eyes of a man were in this horn, and a mouth speaking unnatural things.

9 I watched until thrones were set up, and the ancient of days sat down. His garment was radiant like snow, and the hair of his head like clean wool; his throne was flames of fire, its wheels had been set on fire.

10 A river of fire rushed forth from his presence. Thousands upon thousands ministered to him, and ten thousand times hundreds of thousands attended before him. The trial began, and the books were opened.

11 I watched because of the voice of the great words which that horn was speaking, and I saw that the beast had been destroyed, and its body was ruined and had been handed over to be burnt with fire.

12 Likewise, the power of the other beasts was taken away, and a limited time of life was appointed to them, until one time and another.

13 I watched, therefore, in the vision of the night, and behold, with the clouds of heaven, one like a son of man arrived, and he approached all the way to the ancient of days, and they presented him before him.

14 And he gave him power, and honor, and the kingdom, and all peoples, tribes, and languages will serve him. His power is an eternal power, which will not be taken away, and his kingdom, one which will not be corrupted.

15 My spirit was terrified. I, Daniel, was fearful at these things, and the visions of my head disturbed me.

16 I approached one of the attendants and asked the truth from him about all these things. He told me the interpretation of the words, and he instructed me:

17 "These four great beasts are four kingdoms, which will rise from the earth.

18 Yet it is the saints of the Most High God who will receive the kingdom, and they will hold the kingdom from this generation, and forever and ever."

19 After this, I wanted to learn diligently about the fourth beast, which was very different from all, and exceedingly terrible; his teeth and claws were of iron; he devoured and crushed, and the remainder he trampled with his feet;

20 and about the ten horns, which he had on his head, and about the other, which had sprung up, before which three horns fell, and about that horn which had eyes and a mouth speaking great things, and which was more powerful than the rest.

21 I watched, and behold, that horn made war against the holy ones and prevailed over them,

22 until the Ancient of days came and gave judgment to the holy ones of the Supreme One, and the time arrived, and the holy ones obtained the kingdom.

23 And thus he said, "The fourth beast will be the fourth kingdom on earth, which will be greater than all the kingdoms, and will devour the whole earth, and will trample and crush it.

24 Moreover, the ten horns of the same kingdom will be ten kings, and another will rise up after them, and he will be mightier than the ones before him, and he will bring down three kings.

25 And he will speak words against the Supreme One, and will exhaust the holy ones of the Most High, and he will think about what it would take to change the times and the laws, and they will be given into his hand until a time, and times, and half a time.

26 And a trial will begin, so that his power may be taken away, and be crushed, and be undone all the way to the end.

27 Yet the kingdom, and the power, and the greatness of that kingdom, which is under all of heaven, shall be given to the people of the holy ones of the Most High, whose kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and all kings will serve and obey him."

28 And here is the end of the message. I, Daniel, was greatly disturbed by my thoughts, and my mood was changed in me, but I preserved the message in my heart.

Daniel 8

1 In the third year of the reign of Belshazzar the king, a vision appeared to me. After that which I had seen in the beginning, I, Daniel,

2 saw in my vision, that I was in the capital city of Susa, which is in the region of Elam, yet I saw in the vision that I was over the gate of Ulai.

3 And I lifted up my eyes and saw, and behold, a single ram stood before the marsh, having two high horns, and one was higher than the other and growing higher still.

4 After this, I saw the ram brandishing his horns against the West, and against the North, and against the Meridian, and all the beasts could not withstand him, nor be freed from his hand, and he did according to his own will, and he became great.

5 And I understood, and behold, a he-goat among she-goats came from the West above the face of the entire earth, and he did not touch the ground. Furthermore, the he-goat had a preeminent horn between his eyes.

6 And he went all the way to the ram that had the horns, which I had seen standing before the gate, and he ran towards him in the force of his strength.

7 And when he approached near to the ram, he was enraged against him, and he struck the ram, and broke his two horns, and the ram could not withstand him, and when he had cast him down on the ground, he trampled him, and no one was able to free the ram from his hand.

8 But the he-goat among she-goats became exceedingly great, and when he had prospered, the great horn was shattered, and four horns were rising up beneath it by means of the four winds of heaven.

9 But from one of them came forth one little horn, and it became great against the Meridian, and against the East, and against the strength.

10 And it was magnified even towards the strength of heaven, and it threw down those of the strength and of the stars, and it trampled them.

11 And it was magnified, even to the leader of the strength, and it took away from him the continual sacrifice, and cast down the place of his sanctuary.

12 And the advantage was given to him against the continual sacrifice, because of the sins, and truth will be struck down to the ground, and he will act, and he will prosper.

13 And I heard one of the holy ones speaking, and one saint said to another, (I know not to whom he was speaking,) "What is the extent of the vision, and the continual sacrifice, and the sin of the desolation, which has happened, and of the sanctuary and the strength, which will be trampled?"

14 And he said to him, "From evening until morning, two thousand three hundred days, and so the sanctuary will be cleansed."

15 But it came to pass, when I, Daniel, saw the vision and sought understanding that, behold, there stood in my sight something like the appearance of a man.

16 And I heard the voice of a man within Ulai, and he called out and said, "Gabriel, make this one understand the vision."

17 And he came and stood next to where I was standing, and when he approached, I fell on my face, trembling, and he said to me, "Understand, son of man, for in the time of the end the vision will be fulfilled."

18 And when he spoke to me, I fell forward onto the ground, and so he touched me and stood me upright.

19 And he said to me, "I will reveal to you what the future things are in the earlier tribulation, for the time has its end.

20 The ram, which you saw to have horns, is the king of the Medes and Persians.

21 Furthermore, the he-goat among she-goats is the king of the Greeks, and the great horn, which was between his eyes, is the same one, the first king.

22 And since, having been shattered, there grew four in its place, four kings will rise up from his people, but not in his strength.

23 And after their reign, when iniquities will be increased, there will arise a king of shameless face and understanding negotiations.

24 And his advantage will be strengthened, but not by his kind of force, and other than what he will be able to trust, everything will be eradicated, and he will prosper, and he will act. And he will execute the successful and the people of the saints,

25 according to his will, and treachery will be guided by his hand. And his heart will be inflated, and by the abundance of everything he will kill many, and he will rise up against the Lord of lords, and he will be knocked down without a hand.

26 And the vision of the evening and the morning, which was told, is true. Therefore, you must seal the vision, because, after many days, it will occur."

27 And I, Daniel, languished and was sick for some days, and when I had lifted myself up, I performed the king's works, and I was astonished at the vision, and there was none who could interpret it.

Daniel 9

1 In the first year of Darius, the son of Ahasuerus, of the offspring of the Medes, who ruled over the kingdom of the Chaldeans,

2 in year one of his reign, I, Daniel, understood in the books the number of the years, concerning the word of the Lord which came to Jeremiah, the prophet, that the desolation of Jerusalem would be completed in seventy years.

3 And I set my face to the Lord, my God, to ask and make supplication with fasting, and sackcloth, and ashes.

4 And I prayed to the Lord, my God, and I confessed, and I said, "I beg you, O Lord God, great and terrible, preserving the covenant and mercy for those who love you and keep your commandments.

5 We have sinned, we have committed iniquity, we acted impiously and have withdrawn, and we have turned aside from your commandments as well as your judgments.

6 We have not obeyed your servants, the prophets, who have spoken in your name to our kings, our leaders, our fathers, and all the people of the land.

7 To you, O Lord, is justice, but to us is confusion of face, just as it is on this day for the men of Judah, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and all Israel, for those who are near and those who are far off, in all the lands to which you have driven them, because of their iniquities by which they have sinned against you.

8 O Lord, to us belongs confusion of face: to our kings, our leaders, and our fathers, who have sinned.

9 But to you, the Lord our God, is mercy and atonement, for we have withdrawn from you,

10 and we have not listened to the voice of the Lord, our God, so as to walk in his law, which he established for us by his servants, the prophets.

11 And all Israel has transgressed your law and has turned away, not listening to your voice, and so the condemnation and the curse, which is written in the book of Moses, servant of God, has rained down upon us, because we have sinned against him.

12 And he has fulfilled his words, which he has spoken over us and over our leaders who judged us, that he would lead over us a great evil, such as has never before existed under all of heaven, according to what has been done in Jerusalem.

13 Just as it has been written in the law of Moses, all this evil has come upon us, and we did not entreat your face, O Lord our God, so that we might turn back from our iniquities and consider your truth.

14 And the Lord kept watch over the evil and has led it over us; the Lord, our God, is just in all his works, which he has accomplished, for we have not listened to his voice.

15 And now, O Lord, our God, who has led your people out of the land of Egypt with a strong hand and has made yourself a name in accordance with this day: we have sinned, we have done wrong.

16 O Lord, for all your righteousness, turn away, I beg you, your anger and your fury from your city, Jerusalem, and from your holy mountain. For, because of our sins and the iniquities of our fathers, Jerusalem and your people are a reproach to all who surround us.

17 Now, therefore, heed, O God, the prayer of your servant and his requests, and reveal your face over your sanctuary, which is desolate, for your own sake.

18 Incline your ear, O my God, and hear, open your eyes and see our desolation and the city over which your name is invoked. For it is not through our justifications that we offer requests before your face, but through the fullness of your compassion.

19 Heed, O Lord. Be pleased, O Lord. Turn and act. Do not delay, for your own sake, O my God, because your name is invoked over your city and over your people."

20 And while I was still speaking and praying and confessing my sins, and the sins of my people, Israel, and offering my prayers in the sight of my God, on behalf of the holy mountain of my God,

21 as I was still speaking in prayer, behold, the man Gabriel, whom I had seen in the vision at the beginning, flying swiftly, touched me at the time of the evening sacrifice.

22 And he instructed me, and he spoke to me and said, "Now, Daniel, I have come forth to teach you and to help you understand.

23 At the beginning of your prayers, the message came forth, yet I have come to explain it to you because you are a man who is seeking. Therefore, you must pay close attention to the message and understand the vision.

24 Seventy weeks of years are concentrated on your people and on your holy city, so that transgression shall be finished, and sin shall reach an end, and iniquity shall be wiped away, and so that everlasting justice shall be brought in, and vision and prophecy shall be fulfilled, and the Saint of saints shall be anointed.

25 Therefore, know and take heed: from the going forth of the word to build up Jerusalem again, until the Christ leader, there will be seven weeks of years, and sixty-two weeks of years; and the wide path will be built again, and the walls, in a time of anguish.

26 And after sixty-two weeks of years, the Christ leader will be slain. And the people who have denied him will not be his. And the people, when their leader arrives, will destroy the city and the sanctuary. And its end will be devastation, and, after the end of the war, the desolation will be set up.

27 But he will confirm a covenant with many for one week of years; and for half of the week of years, victim and sacrifice will nearly cease; but there will be in the temple the abomination of desolation. And the desolation will continue even to the consummation and the end."

Daniel 10

1 In the third year of Cyrus, king of the Persians, a message was revealed to Daniel, called Belteshazzar, and a true word, and great strength. And he understood the message, for understanding is needed in a vision.

2 In those days, I, Daniel, mourned for three weeks of days.

3 I ate no desirable bread, and neither meat, nor wine, entered my mouth, neither was I anointed with ointment, until the three weeks of days were completed.

4 But on the twenty-fourth day of the first month, I was next to the great river, which is the Tigris.

5 And I lifted up my eyes, and I saw, and behold, one man clothed in linen, and his waist was wrapped with the finest gold,

6 and his body was like the golden stone, and his face had the appearance of lightning, and his eyes that of a burning lamp, and his arms and all that is downward all the way to the feet had the appearance of glowing brass, and his speaking voice was like the voice of a multitude.

7 But I, Daniel, alone saw the vision, for the men who were with me did not see it, but an exceedingly great terror rushed over them, and they fled into hiding.

8 And I, having been left alone, saw this great vision, and there remained no strength in me, moreover, my appearance was altered, and I languished, not having any strength.

9 And I heard the voice of his words, and when I heard, I lay down in confusion on my face, and my face was close to the ground.

10 And behold, a hand touched me, and raised me onto my knees and the knuckles of my hands.

11 And he said to me, "Daniel, man of longing, understand the words that I speak to you, and stand yourself upright, for I am now sent to you." And when he had said these words to me, I stood trembling.

12 And he said to me, "Do not be afraid, Daniel, because from the first day that you set your heart to understand, by afflicting yourself in the sight of your God, your words have been heeded, and I have arrived because of your words.

13 But the leader of the kingdom of the Persians resisted me for twenty-one days, and behold, Michael, one of the primary leaders, came to help me, and I remained there next to the king of the Persians.

14 But I have come to teach you what will happen to your people in the latter days, because the vision is for a long time from now."

15 And while he was speaking words to me in this way, I cast my face down to the ground and was silent.

16 And behold, something in the likeness of a son of man touched my lips. Then, opening my mouth, I spoke and said to him who stood before me, "My lord, at the sight of you, my limbs became weak and no strength has remained in me.

17 And so, how can the servant of my lord speak with my lord? For no strength remains in me; and even my breathing is hindered."

18 Therefore, he who looked like a man, touched me again and strengthened me.

19 And he said, "Fear not, O man of longing. May peace be with you. Take courage and be strong." And when he spoke to me, I recovered, and I said, "Speak, my lord, for you have strengthened me."

20 And he said, "Do you not know why I have come to you? And next I will return, to fight against the leader of the Persians. When I was leaving, there appeared the leader of the Greeks arriving.

21 But, in truth, I announce to you what is expressed in the scripture of truth. And no one is my helper in all these things, except Michael your leader."

Daniel 11

1 "And so, from the first year of Darius the Mede, I stood firm, so that he might be reinforced and strengthened.

2 And now I will announce to you the truth. Behold, up to a certain point, three kings will stand in Persia, and the fourth will be exceedingly enriched in power above them all. And when he has grown strong by his resources, he will stir up all against the kingdom of Greece.

3 But there will rise up a strong king, and he will rule with great power, and he will do what he pleases.

4 And when he has been firmly established, his kingdom will be shattered and will be divided towards the four winds of the heaven, but not to his posterity, nor according to his power with which he ruled. For his kingdom will be torn to pieces, even for the outsiders who have been expelled from these.

5 And the king of the South will be reinforced, yet one of his leaders will prevail over him, and he will rule with riches, for great is his domain.

6 And after the end of years, they will form a federation, and the daughter of the king of the South will come to the king of the North to make friendship, but she will not obtain the strength of arms, neither will her offspring stand firm, and she will be handed over, along with those who brought her, her young men, and those who comforted her in these times.

7 And a transplant from the germination of her roots will stand up, and he will come with an army, and will enter into the province of the king of the North, and he will abuse them, and will hold it fast.

8 And, in addition, he will carry away captive into Egypt their gods, and their graven images, and likewise their precious vessels of gold and silver. He will prevail against the king of the North.

9 And the king of the South will enter into the kingdom, and will return to his own land.

10 But his sons will be challenged, and they will assemble a multitude of very many forces. And he will arrive rushing and overflowing. And he will be turned back, and he will be enraged, and he will join the battle in his redness.

11 And the king of the South, having being challenged, will go forth and will fight against the king of the North, and he will prepare an exceedingly great multitude, and a multitude will be given into his hand.

12 And he will seize a multitude, and his heart will be exalted, and he will cast down many thousands, but he will not prevail.

13 For the king of the North will change strategy and will prepare a multitude much greater than before, and at the end of times and years, he will rush forward with a great army and exceedingly great resources.

14 And in those times, many will rise up against the king of the South. And likewise the sons of the deceivers among your people will extol themselves, so as to fulfill the vision, and they will collapse.

15 And the king of the North will arrive and will transport siege works, and he will seize the most fortified cities. And the arms of the South will not withstand him, and his elect will rise up to resist, but the strength will not.

16 And when he arrives, he will do just as he pleases, and there will be none who stand against his face. And he will stand in the illustrious land, and it will be consumed by his hand.

17 And he will set his face to strive to hold his entire kingdom, and he will make fair conditions with him. And he will give him a daughter among women, so as to overthrow it. But she will not stand, neither will she be for him.

18 And he will turn his face towards the islands, and he will seize many. And he will cause the leader of his reproach to cease, and his reproach will be turned around for him.

19 And he will turn his face to the empire of his own land, and he will strike, and will overthrow, but he will not succeed.

20 And there will stand up in his place one who is most worthless and unworthy of kingly honor. And in a short time, he will be worn out, but not in fury, nor in battle.

21 And there will stand up in his place the despicable one, and he will not be assigned the honor of a king. And he will arrive in secret, and he will obtain the kingdom by deceitfulness.

22 And the arms of the fighting will be assaulted before his face and will be shattered, and, in addition, the leader of the federation.

23 And, after making friends, he will trick him, and he will go up and will overcome with a small people.

24 And he will enter into rich and resourceful cities, and he will do what his fathers never did, nor his fathers' fathers. He will scatter their spoils, and their prey, and their riches, and will form a plan against the most steadfast, and this until a time.

25 And his strength and his heart will be enraged against the king of the South with a great army. And the king of the South will be provoked into going to war by having many allies and exceedingly good circumstances, and yet these will not stand, for they will form plans against him.

26 And those who eat bread with him will crush him, and his army will be suppressed, and very many will die, having been executed.

27 And the heart of two kings will be similar, to do harm, and they will speak lies at one table, but they will not succeed, because as yet the end is for another time.

28 And he will return to his land with many resources. And his heart will be against the holy testament, and he will act, and he will return to his own land.

29 At the appointed time, he will return, and he will approach the South, but the latter time will not be like the former.

30 And the Greek warships and the Romans will come upon him, and he will be pierced, and will retreat, and will have scorn against the testament of the sanctuary, and he will act. And he will return and will consult their adversaries, who have forsaken the covenant of the sanctuary.

31 And arms will take his side, and they will pollute the sanctuary of the strength, and they will take away the continual sacrifice and will replace it with the abomination of desolation.

32 And the impious within the testament will imitate deceitfully, but the people, knowing their God, will persevere and will act.

33 And the teachers among the people will teach many, but they will be ruined by the sword, and by fire, and by captivity, and by assaults for many days.

34 And when they have fallen, they will be supported with a little help, but many will apply to them deceitfully.

35 And some of the learned will be ruined, that they may be kindled and chosen and purified, up to the predetermined time, because there will be still another time.

36 And the king will act according to his will, and he will be lifted up and will be extolled against every god. And he will speak great things against the God of gods, and he will control, until the passion is completed. Once accomplished, the limit is reached with certainty.

37 And he will give no thought to the God of his fathers, and he will be in the desire of women, and he will not attend to any gods, because he will rise up against all things.

38 But he will do homage to the god Maozim in his place, and, a god whom his fathers did not know, he will worship with gold, and silver, and precious stones, and costly things.

39 And he will act to reinforce Maozim with an alien god, of whom he has become aware, and he will increase their glory, and will give them power over many, and he will distribute land for free.

40 And, at the predetermined time, the king of the South will fight against him, and the king of the North will come against him like a tempest, with chariots, and with horsemen, and with a great fleet, and he will enter into the lands, and will crush and pass through.

41 And he will enter into the glorious land, and many will fall. But only these will be saved from his hand: Edom, and Moab, and the first part of the sons of Ammon.

42 And he will cast his hand upon the lands, and the land of Egypt will not escape.

43 And he will rule over the treasure chests of gold, and silver, and all the precious things of Egypt, and likewise he will pass through Libya and Ethiopia.

44 And rumors from the East and from the North will trouble him. And he will arrive with a great multitude to destroy and to execute many.

45 And he will fasten his tabernacle, Apadno, between the seas, upon an illustrious and holy mountain, and he will come even to its summit, and no one will help him."

Daniel 12

1 "But at that time Michael will rise up, the great leader, who stands up for the sons of your people. And a time will come, such as has not been from the time that nations began, even until that time. And, at that time, your people will be saved, all who will be found written in the book.

2 And many of those who sleep in the dust of the earth will awaken: some to everlasting life, and others to a reproach that they will always see.

3 But those who have taught will shine like the brightness of the firmament, and those who instruct many towards justice, like the stars for unending eternity.

4 But you, Daniel, close the message and seal the book, until the established time. Many will pass through, and knowledge will be increased."

5 And I, Daniel, looked, and behold, similarly two others stood up, one over here, on the bank of the river, and the other over there, on the other bank of the river.

6 And I said to the man, who was clothed in linen, who stood over the waters of the river, "How long will it be until the end of these wonders?"

7 And I heard the man, who was clothed in linen, who stood over the waters of the river, when he had lifted his right hand and his left hand up to heaven, and had sworn by He who lives forever, that it would be for a time, and times, and half a time. And when the dispersion of the hand of the holy people is completed, all these things will be completed.

8 And I heard and did not understand. And I said, "My lord, what will be after these things?"

9 And he said, "Go, Daniel, for the words are closed and sealed until the predetermined time.

10 Many will be chosen and purified, and, as if by fire, they will be tested, and the impious will act impiously, and none of the impious will understand, yet the teachers will understand.

11 And from the time when the continual sacrifice will be taken away and the abomination of desolation will be set up, there will be one thousand two hundred ninety days.

12 Blessed is he who waits and reaches until one thousand three hundred thirty-five days.

13 But you, go, until the predetermined time, and you will rest and will stand in your allotted place at the end of days.

Hosea 1

1 The word of the Lord that came to Hosea, the son of Beeri, in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam, the son of Joash, king of Israel.

2 The beginning of the Lord's conversation with Hosea. And the Lord said to Hosea: "Go, take to yourself a wife of fornications, and make for yourself sons of fornications, because, by fornicating, the land will fornicate away from the Lord."

3 And he went out and took Gomer the daughter of Diblaim; and she conceived and bore him a son.

4 And the Lord said to him: "Call his name Jezreel because, after a little while, I will visit the blood of Jezreel upon the house of Jehu, and I will put the kingdom of the house of Israel to rest.

5 And in that day, I will crush the stronghold of Israel in the valley of Jezreel."

6 And after a while, she conceived and bore a daughter. And he said to him: "Call her name, Without Mercy, for I will no longer have mercy on the house of Israel, but I will utterly forget them.

7 Yet I will have mercy on the house of Judah, and I will save them by the Lord their God. And I will not save them by bow and sword and battle and horses and horsemen."

8 And she weaned her, who was called Without Mercy. And she conceived and bore a son.

9 And he said: "Call his name, Not My People, for you are not my people, and I will not be yours.

10 And the number of the sons of Israel will be like the sand of the sea, which is without measure and cannot be numbered. And in the place where it will be said to them, 'You are not my people,' this will happen: it will be said to them, 'You are the sons of the living God.'

11 And the sons of Judah, and the sons of Israel, will be gathered together. And they will place over themselves one head, and they will rise up from the earth, for great is the day of Jezreel."

Hosea 2

1 "Say to your brothers, 'You are my people,' and to your sister, 'You have obtained mercy.'

2 Judge your mother, judge: for she is not my wife, and I am not her husband. Let her remove her fornications from before her face and her adulteries from between her breasts.

3 Otherwise, I may expose her nakedness and set her as on the day of her birth, and I may establish her as a wilderness and set her as an impassable land, and I may execute her with thirst.

4 And I will not have mercy on her sons, for they are the sons of fornications.

5 For their mother has been fornicating; she who conceived them has been brought to ruin. For she said, 'I will go after my lovers, who give me my bread and my water, my wool and my flax, my oil and my drink.'

6 Because of this, behold, I will fence in your way with thorns, and I will surround it with a wall, and she will not find her paths.

7 And she will pursue her lovers, but she will not obtain them, and she will seek them, but she will not find them, and she will say, 'I will go and return to my first husband, because it was to some extent better for me then, than it is now.'

8 And she did not know that I gave her grain and wine and oil, and that I increased her silver and gold, which they made into Baal.

9 For this reason, I will turn back, and I will take away my grain in its time and my wine in its time, and I will set free my wool and my flax, which had covered her disgrace.

10 And now, I will reveal her foolishness by the eyes of her lovers, and no man will rescue her from my hand.

11 And I will cause all her joy to cease: her solemnities, her new moons, her sabbaths, and all her feast dates.

12 And I will corrupt her vines and her fig trees, about which she said, 'These rewards, they are mine, my lovers have given them to me.' And I will place her in a narrow forest, and the beasts of the field will devour her.

13 And I will inflict on her the days of the Baals, for whom she burned incense, and ornamented herself with earrings and necklace, and went after her lovers, and forgot about me," says the Lord.

14 "Because of this, behold, I will attract her, and I will lead her into the wilderness, and I will speak to her heart.

15 And I will give to her, from the same place, her vinedressers, and the valley of Achor as a passage of hope. And she will sing there as in the days of her youth, and as in the days of her ascension from the land of Egypt.

16 And it will be in that day," says the Lord, "that she will call me, 'My Husband,' and she will no longer call me, 'My Baal.'

17 And I will remove the names of the Baals from her mouth, and she will no longer remember their name.

18 And in that day, I will strike a deal with them, with the beasts of the field, and with the birds of the sky, and with the creatures of the earth. And I will crush the bow and the sword, and I will wipe away war from the earth. And I will let them sleep securely.

19 And I will betroth you to me forever, and I will betroth you to me in justice and judgment, and in mercy and compassion.

20 And I will wed you to me in faith, and you will know that I am the Lord.

21 And this will happen in that day: I will listen closely," says the Lord. "I will hear the heavens, and they will hear the earth.

22 And the land will pay attention to the grain, and the wine, and the oil; and these will hear Jezreel.

23 And I will plant her for me in the land, and I will have mercy on her, though she had been called Without Mercy.

24 And I will say to Not My People, 'You are my people,' and they will say, 'You are my God.' "

Hosea 4

1 Listen to the word of the Lord, sons of Israel, for the Lord is judge of the inhabitants of the land. Yet there is no truth, and there is no mercy, and there is no knowledge of God, in the land.

2 Slander, and lying, and killing, and theft, and adultery have overflowed, and bloodshed has brought more bloodshed.

3 Because of this, the land will mourn, and all who dwell in it will languish, with the beasts of the field and the birds of the air. And the fishes of the sea also will be gathered together.

4 So, truly, let each and every one not judge, and let no man be accused, for your people are just like those who speak against the priesthood.

5 And you will be ruined on this day, and now the prophet will be ruined with you. In the night, I have made your mother to be silent.

6 My people have become silent because they had no knowledge. Since you have rejected knowledge, I will drive you away; you do not perform the duties of the priesthood for me, and you have forgotten the law of your God, and so I will forget your sons.

7 According to the multitude of them, so have they sinned against me. I will change their glory into disgrace.

8 They will devour the sins of my people, and they will lift up their souls towards their iniquity.

9 And, just as it is with the people, so will it be with the priest; and I will visit their ways upon them, and I will repay them for their intentions.

10 And they will eat and not be satisfied. They have been committing fornication, and they did not cease. Since they have abandoned the Lord, they will not be safeguarded.

11 Fornication, and wine, and drunkenness, have taken away their heart.

12 My people have inquired of their stave, and their staff has announced to them. For the spirit of fornication has deceived them, and they have been fornicating before their God.

13 They have offered sacrifice on the tops of the mountains and burnt incense on the hills, under the oak, and the poplar, and the terebinth tree, because its shadow was good; therefore, your daughters will commit fornication and your spouses will be adulteresses.

14 I will not send afflictions on your daughters, when they will commit fornication, nor on your spouses, when they will commit adultery, because you yourselves have associated with harlots and have offered sacrifice with the effeminate, and because the people who do not understand will be defeated.

15 If you commit fornication, Israel, at least let Judah not commit offenses; and do not be willing to enter into Gilgal, nor to ascend to Bethaven, and neither should you swear, "As the Lord lives."

16 For Israel has gone astray like a wanton heifer; so now the Lord will pasture them like a young lamb in a wide expanse.

17 Ephraim participates in idolatry, so send him away.

18 Their feasting has been set aside; they have committed fornication after fornication. They love to bring disgrace to their protectors.

19 The wind has fastened them to its wings, and they will be confounded because of their sacrifices.

Hosea 5

1 Hear this, priests, and pay attention, house of Israel, and listen closely, house of the king. For there is a judgment against you, because you have become a trap for those you watched over, and a net stretched out over Tabor.

2 And you have led astray victims into the depths, though I am the teacher of them all.

3 I know Ephraim, and Israel has not been hidden from me, yet now Ephraim has committed fornication, and Israel has been contaminated.

4 They will not set their thoughts to return to their God, for the spirit of fornication is in the midst of them, and they have not known the Lord.

5 And the arrogance of Israel will answer to his face. And Israel and Ephraim will fall in their iniquity, and even Judah will fall with them.

6 With their flocks and their herds, they will go to seek the Lord, and they will not find him. He has taken himself away from them.

7 They have sinned against the Lord. For they have conceived sons that are strangers. Now one month will devour them with all their own.

8 Sound the bugle in Gibeah, the trumpet in Ramah. Shout in Bethaven, behind your back, O Benjamin.

9 Ephraim will be in desolation on the day of correction, for within the tribes of Israel, I have revealed faith.

10 The leaders of Judah have become like those who assume the end. I will pour my wrath over them like water.

11 Ephraim has been enduring malicious slander and broken judgment, because he began to go after filth.

12 And I will be like a moth to Ephraim, and like decay to the house of Judah.

13 And Ephraim saw his own weakness, and Judah his chains. And Ephraim went to Assur, and he sent to the Avenging king. But he will not be able to heal you, nor is he able to release you from your chains.

14 For I will be like a lioness to Ephraim, and like a lion's offspring to the house of Judah. I myself will seize and go forth. I will take away, and there is no one who can rescue.

15 I will go and return to my place, until you shall grow faint and seek my face.

Hosea 6

1 In their tribulation, they will arise early to me. Come, let us return to the Lord.

2 For he has seized us, and he will heal us. He will strike, and he will cure us.

3 He will revive us after two days; on the third day he will raise us up, and we will live in his sight. We will understand, and we will continue on, so that we may know the Lord. His landing place has been prepared like the first light of morning, and he will come to us like the early and the late rains of the land.

4 What am I to do with you, Ephraim? What am I to do with you, Judah? Your mercy is like the morning mist, and like the dew passing away in the morning.

5 Because of this, I have cut them with the prophets, I have slain them with the words of my mouth; and your opinions will depart like the light.

6 For I desired mercy and not sacrifice, and knowledge of God more than holocausts.

7 But they, like Adam, have transgressed the covenant; in this, they have been dishonest with me.

8 Gilead is a city that manufactures idols; it has been tripped up by family relations.

9 And, like those who rob with skillful words, they, by conspiring with the priests, bring a death sentence to travelers on a pilgrimage from Shechem; for they have been performing evil deeds.

10 I have seen horrible things in the house of Israel; the fornications of Ephraim are there. Israel has been contaminated.

11 But you, Judah, set a harvest for yourself, while I reverse the captivity of my people.

Hosea 7

1 When I was willing to heal Israel, the iniquity of Ephraim was discovered, and the malice of Samaria, for they had been manufacturing lies. And the thief steals from inside, the robber from outside.

2 And, so that they may not say in their hearts that I am the one who has called to mind all of their wickedness: now their own inventions have encircled them. These things have happened in my presence.

3 The king has rejoiced at their wickedness, and the leaders have rejoiced in their lies.

4 They are all adulterers; like an oven heating up before baking, the city rested a little before the leaven was mixed in, until the whole was leavened.

5 On the day of our king, the leaders began to be mad with wine; he extended his hand with those who fabricate illusions.

6 For they have used their heart like an oven, while he laid snares for them; he slept through the night baking them, and by morning he himself was heated like a burning fire.

7 They have all become hot like an oven, and they have devoured their judges. All their kings have fallen. There is no one who calls to me among them.

8 Ephraim himself has been mingled with the nations. Ephraim has become like bread, baked under ashes, that has not been turned over.

9 Strangers have devoured his strength, and he did not know it. And grey hairs also have spread across him, and he is ignorant of it.

10 And the pride of Israel will be brought low before his face, for they have not returned to the Lord their God, nor have they sought him in all of this.

11 And Ephraim has become like a pigeon that has been led astray, not having a heart; for they called upon Egypt, they went to the Assyrians.

12 And when they will set out, I will spread my net over them. I will pull them down like the birds of the sky; I will cut them down in accordance with the reports of their meetings.

13 Woe to them, for they have withdrawn from me. They will waste away because they have been dishonest with me. And I redeemed them, and they have spoken lies against me.

14 And they have not cried out to me in their heart, but they howled on their beds. They have obsessed about wheat and wine; they have withdrawn from me.

15 And I have educated them, and I have reinforced their arms; and they have imagined evil against me.

16 They returned so that they might be without a yoke. They have become like a deceitful bow. Their leaders will fall by the sword because of the madness of their words. This is their derision in the land of Egypt.

Hosea 8

1 Let there be a trumpet in your throat, like an eagle over the house of the Lord, on behalf of those who have transgressed my covenant and violated my law.

2 They will call on me: "O my God, we, Israel, know you."

3 Israel has thrown away goodness; the enemy will overtake him.

4 They have reigned, but not by me. Leaders have emerged, and I did not recognize them. Their silver and their gold, they have made into idols for themselves, so that they might cross over.

5 Your calf, Samaria, has been rejected. My fury has been enraged against them. How long will they be incapable of being cleansed?

6 For it is itself also from Israel: a workman made it, and it is not God. For the calf of Samaria will be used for the webs of spiders.

7 For they will sow wind and reap a whirlwind. It does not have a firm stalk; the bud will yield no grain. But if it does yield, strangers will eat it.

8 Israel has been devoured. Now, among the nations, it has become like an unclean vessel.

9 For they have gone up to Assur, a wild ass alone by himself. Ephraim has given presents to his lovers.

10 But even when they will have brought the nations together for the sake of money, now I will assemble them. And they will rest for a little while from the burden of the king and the leaders.

11 For Ephraim multiplied altars to sin, and sanctuaries have become an offense for him.

12 I will write to him my intricate laws, which have been treated like strangers.

13 They will offer victims, they will immolate flesh and will eat, and the Lord will not accept them. For now he will remember their iniquity, and he will repay their sins: they will be turned back to Egypt.

14 And Israel has forgotten his Maker and has built shrines. And Judah has increased its fortified cities. And I will send fire upon his cities, and it will devour its structures.

Hosea 9

1 Do not choose to rejoice, Israel; do not celebrate as the crowds do. For you have been committing fornication against your God; you have loved a prize upon every threshing floor of wheat.

2 The threshing floor and the oil press will not feed them, and the wine will deceive them.

3 They will not dwell in the land of the Lord. Ephraim has been returned to Egypt, and he has eaten polluted things among the Assyrians.

4 They will not offer a libation of wine to the Lord, and they will not please him. Their sacrifices will be like the bread of mourners. All those who eat it will be defiled. For their bread is of their soul; it will not enter into the house of the Lord.

5 What will you do on the solemn day, on the day of the feast of the Lord?

6 For, behold, they have been sent away by devastation. Egypt will gather them together; Memphis will bury them. Nettles will inherit their desired silver; the burr will be in their tabernacles.

7 The days of visitation have arrived; the days of retribution are here. Know this, Israel: that the prophet was foolish, the spiritual man was mad, because of the multitude of your iniquities and the great extent of your foolishness.

8 The watcher of Ephraim was with my God. The prophet has become a snare of ruin over all his ways; insanity is in the house of his God.

9 They have sinned profoundly, just as in the days of Gibeah. He will remember their iniquity, and he will repay their sin.

10 I discovered Israel like grapes in the desert. Like the first fruits of the fig tree, I saw their fathers on the end of its branches. But they went in to Baal-peor, and they have been estranged by intermingling, and they have became abominable, just like the things that they chose to love.

11 Ephraim has chased away their glory like a bird: from birth, and from the womb, and from conception.

12 And even if they should nurture their sons, I will make them without children among men. Yes, and woe to them, when I have withdrawn from them.

13 Ephraim, as I see it, was a Tyre, founded by beauty. And Ephraim will lead his sons to execution.

14 Give them, O Lord. What will you give them? Give them a womb without children, and dry breasts.

15 All their wickedness is in Gilgal, for I held them there, in their hatred. Because of the malice of their inventions, I will expel them from my house. I will no longer say that I love them; all their leaders have retreated.

16 Ephraim has been struck; their root has been dried out: by no means will they yield fruit. And even if they should conceive, I will execute the most beloved of their womb.

17 My God will cast them aside because they have not listened to him; and they will be wanderers among the nations.

Hosea 10

1 Israel is a leafy vine, its fruit has been suitable to him. According to the multitude of his fruit, he has multiplied altars; according to the fertility of his land, he has abounded with graven images.

2 His heart has been divided, so now they will cross the divide. He will break apart their images; he will plunder their sanctuaries.

3 For now they will say, "We have no king. For we do not fear the Lord. And what would a king do for us?"

4 You speak words about a useless vision, and you will strike a deal. And judgment will spring up like bitterness in the furrows of the field.

5 The inhabitants of Samaria have worshipped the calf of Bethaven. For the keepers of its temple, who had exulted over it in its glory, and its people, have mourned over it because it migrated from there.

6 If, indeed, it also has been offered to Assur, as a gift for the Avenging king, confusion will seize Ephraim, and Israel will be confounded by his own will.

7 Samaria has required her king to pass by, like foam on the face of the water.

8 And the heights of the idol, the sin of Israel, will be utterly destroyed. The burr and the thistle will rise up over their altars. And they will say to the mountains, 'Cover us,' and to the hills, 'Fall on us.'

9 From the days of Gibeah, Israel has sinned; in this, they remained firm. The battle in Gibeah against the sons of iniquity will not take hold of them.

10 According to my desire, I will correct them. And the peoples will be gathered together over them, while they are chastised for their two iniquities.

11 Ephraim is a heifer that has been taught to love treading out the grain, but I passed over the beauty of her neck. I will rise over Ephraim. Judah will plough; Jacob will break up the soil for himself.

12 Sow for yourselves in justice, and harvest in the mouth of mercy; renew your fallow land. But the time when you will seek the Lord is the time when he will arrive who will teach you justice.

13 You have ploughed impiety; you have harvested iniquity; you have eaten the fruit of lies. For you had confidence in your ways, in the multitude of your good fortunes.

14 A tumult will arise among your people. And all your fortifications will be laid waste, just as Salman was destroyed by the house of him that judged Baal on the day of the battle, the mother having been crushed against her sons.

15 So has Bethel done to you, before the face of your malicious wickedness.

Hosea 11

1 Just as the morning passes, so has the king of Israel passed by. For Israel was a child and I loved him; and out of Egypt I called my son.

2 They called them, and so they departed before their face. They offered victims to the Baals, and they sacrificed to graven images.

3 And I was like a foster father to Ephraim. I carried them in my arms. And they did not know that I healed them.

4 I will draw them with the cords of Adam, with the bands of love. And I will be to them like one who raises the yoke over their jaws. And I will reach down to him so that he may eat.

5 He will not return to the land of Egypt, but Assur himself will be the king over him, because they were not willing to be converted.

6 The sword has begun in his cities, and it will consume his elect and devour their heads.

7 And my people will long for my return. But a yoke will be imposed on them together, which will not be taken away.

8 How will I provide for you, Ephraim; how will I protect you, Israel? How will I provide for you as for Adam; will I set you like Zeboiim? My heart has changed within me; together with my regret, it has been stirred up.

9 I will not act on the fury of my wrath. I will not turn back to utterly destroy Ephraim. For I am God, and not man, the Divine in your midst, and I will not advance upon the city.

10 They will walk after the Lord; he will roar like a lion. For he himself will roar, and the sons of the sea will dread.

11 And they will fly like a bird out of Egypt, and like a dove from the land of the Assyrians. And I will arrange them in their own houses, says the Lord.

12 Ephraim has besieged me with denials, and the house of Israel with deceit. But Judah went down as a witness before God and the holy ones of faith.

Hosea 12

1 Ephraim feeds on wind and follows burning heat; all day long he multiplies lies and desolation. And he has entered into a pact with the Assyrians, and he has carried oil into Egypt.

2 Therefore, the judgment of the Lord is with Judah and a visitation is upon Jacob. He will repay him according to his ways and according to his inventions.

3 In the womb, he supplanted his brother; for in his good fortune, he had been guided by an angel.

4 And he prevailed over an angel, for he had been strengthened. He wept and petitioned him. He found him in Bethel, and there he has spoken to us.

5 And the Lord God of hosts, the Lord is his memorial.

6 And so, you should convert to your God. Keep mercy and judgment, and have hope in your God always.

7 Canaan, in his hand is a deceitful balance, he has chosen false accusations.

8 And Ephraim has said, "Nevertheless, I have become rich; I have found an idol for myself. All of my labors will not reveal to me the iniquity that I have committed."

9 And I, the Lord your God from the land of Egypt, nevertheless will cause you to dwell in tabernacles, just as during the days of the feast.

10 And I have spoken through the prophets, and I have multiplied visions, and I have used parables through the hands of the prophets.

11 If Gilead is an idol, then they have been sacrificing cattle in Gilgal to no purpose. For even their altars are like clutter on the soil of the field.

12 Jacob fled into the region of Syria, and Israel served like a wife, and was served by a wife.

13 Yet by a prophet the Lord led Israel out of Egypt, and he was served by a prophet.

14 Ephraim has provoked me to wrath with his bitterness, and his blood will overcome him, and his Lord will requite him for his shamefulness.

Hosea 13

1 While Ephraim was speaking, a horror entered Israel, and he offended by Baal, and he died.

2 And now they add that they will be sinning more. And they have made themselves an image cast from their silver, just like the image of idols; but the whole thing has been made by craftsmen. These say to them, "Sacrifice men, you who adore calves."

3 For this reason, they will be like the morning clouds, and like the morning dew that passes away, just like the dust that is driven by a whirlwind away from the threshing floor, and like the smoke from a chimney.

4 But I am the Lord your God from the land of Egypt, and you will not know God apart from me, and there is no Savior except me.

5 I knew you in the desert, in the land of solitude.

6 According to their pastures, they have been filled up and have been satisfied. And they have lifted up their heart, and they have forgotten me.

7 And I will be to them like a lioness, like a leopard in the way of the Assyrians.

8 I will run to meet them like a bear that has been robbed of her young, and I will split open the middle of their liver. And I will devour them there like a lion; the beast of the field will tear them apart.

9 Perdition is yours, Israel. Your help is only in me.

10 Where is your king? Now, especially, let him save you in all your cities, and from your judges, about whom you said, "Give me kings and princes."

11 I will give you a king in my wrath, and I will take him away in my indignation.

12 The iniquity of Ephraim has been bound; his sin has been engulfed.

13 The pains of giving birth will reach him. He is an unwise son. For now he will not remain firm during the contrition of his sons.

14 I will free them from the hand of death; from death I will redeem them. Death, I will be your death. Hell, I will be your deadly wound. Consolation is hidden from my eyes.

15 For he will make a division among brothers. The Lord will bring a burning wind, rising up from the desert, and it will dry up his streams, and it will make his fountain desolate, and he will tear apart every collection of desirable useful things.

Hosea 14

1 Let Samaria perish, because she has urged her God towards bitterness. Let them perish by the sword, let their little ones be thrown down, and let their pregnant women be cut in two.

2 Israel, convert to the Lord your God. For you have been ruined by your own iniquity.

3 Take these words with you and return to the Lord. And say to him, "Remove all iniquity and accept the good. And we will repay the calves of our lips.

4 Assur will not save us; we will not ride on horses. Neither will we say any more, 'The works of our hands are our gods,' for those that are in you will have mercy on the orphan."

5 I will heal their contrition; I will love them spontaneously. For my wrath has been turned away from them.

6 I will be like the dew; Israel will spring forth like the lily, and his root will spread out like that of the cedars of Lebanon.

7 His branches will advance, and his glory will be like the olive tree, and his fragrance will be like that of the cedars of Lebanon.

8 They will be converted, sitting in his shadow. They will live on wheat, and they will grow like a vine. His memorial will be like the wine of the cedars of Lebanon.

9 Ephraim will say, "What are idols to me any more?" I will listen to him, and I will set him straight like a healthy spruce tree. Your fruit has been found by me.

10 Who is wise and will understand this? Who has understanding and will know these things? For the ways of the Lord are straight, and the just will walk in them, but truly, the traitors will fall in them.

Joel 1

1 The word of the Lord that came to Joel, the son of Pethuel.

2 Listen to this, elders, and pay close attention, all inhabitants of the land. Did this ever happen in your days or in the days of your fathers?

3 Talk this over with your sons, and your sons with their sons, and their sons with another generation.

4 The locust has eaten what the caterpillar has left, and the beetle has eaten what the locust has left, and the mildew has eaten what the beetle has left.

5 Rouse yourselves, you drunkards, and weep and wail, all you who delight in drinking wine; for it has been cut off from your mouth.

6 For a nation has ascended over my land: strong and without number. His teeth are like the teeth of a lion, and his molars are like that of a lion's young.

7 He has put my vineyard into desolation, and he has pulled off the bark of my fig tree. He has stripped it bare and cast it away; its branches have become white.

8 Lament like a betrothed virgin, wrapped in sackcloth at the loss of the husband of her youth.

9 Sacrifice and libation have perished from the house of the Lord; the priests who are ministers of the Lord have mourned.

10 The region has been depopulated, the soil has mourned. For the wheat has been devastated, the wine has been disfigured, the oil has languished.

11 The farmers have been confounded, the vineyard workers have wailed over the crop and the barley, because the harvest of the field has perished.

12 The vineyard is in ruin, and the fig tree has languished. The pomegranate tree, and the palm tree, and the fruit tree, and all the trees of the field have withered. For joy has been thrown into disorder before the sons of men.

13 Priests, gird yourselves and lament. Ministers of the altars, wail. Enter, ministers of my God, lie in sackcloth. For sacrifice and libation have passed away from the house of your God.

14 Sanctify a fast, call an assembly, gather the elders and all the inhabitants of the land into the house of your God. And cry out to the Lord:

15 "Ah, ah, ah, the day!" For the day of the Lord is near, and it will arrive, like a devastation, before the powerful.

16 Has not your nourishment perished from before your eyes, joy and gladness from the house of our God?

17 The mules have rotted in their own manure, the barns have been demolished, the wine cellars have been destroyed, because the grain has been ruined.

18 Why have the animals groaned, the herds of cattle bellowed? because there is no pasture for them. Yes, and even the flocks of sheep have been lost.

19 To you, O Lord, I will cry out, because fire has devoured the beauty of the wilderness, and the flame has burned all the trees of the countryside.

20 Yes, and even the beasts of the field have gazed up at you, like the dry ground thirsting for rain, because the fountains of waters have dried up, and fire has devoured the beauty of the wilderness.

Joel 2

1 Blow the trumpet in Zion, wail on my holy mountain, let all the inhabitants of the land be stirred up. For the day of the Lord is on its way; for it is near:

2 a day of darkness and gloom, a day of clouds and whirlwinds. Like the morning reaching over the mountains, they are a numerous and strong people. Nothing like them has existed since the beginning, nor will exist after them, even in the years of generation upon generation.

3 Before their face is a devouring fire, and behind them is a burning flame. The land before them is like a lush garden, and behind them is a desolate desert, and there is no one who can escape them.

4 Their appearance is like the appearance of horses, and they will rush forward like horsemen.

5 Like the sound of a four-horse chariot, they will leap over the tops of the mountains. Like the sound of a burning flame devouring stubble, they are as a strong people prepared for battle.

6 Before their face, the people will be tortured; each one's appearance will retreat, as if into a jar.

7 They will rush forward, as if they were strong. Like valiant warriors, they will ascend the wall. The men will advance, each one on his own way, and they will not turn aside from their path.

8 And each one will not hem in his brother; every one will walk in his own rough path. Moreover, they will drop through the breach and not be harmed.

9 They will advance into the city; they will rush through the wall. They will scale the houses; they will go in through the windows, like a thief.

10 Before their face, the earth has trembled, the heavens have been moved. The sun and moon have been obscured, and the stars have retracted their splendor.

11 And the Lord has bestowed his voice before the face of his army. For its military camps are very numerous; for they are strong and they carry out his word. For the day of the Lord is great and so very terrible, and who can withstand it?

12 Now, therefore, the Lord says: "Be converted to me with your whole heart, in fasting and weeping and mourning."

13 And rend your hearts, and not your garments, and convert to the Lord your God. For he is gracious and merciful, patient and full of compassion, and steadfast despite ill will.

14 Who knows if he might convert and forgive, and bequeath a blessing after him, a sacrifice and a libation to the Lord your God?

15 Blow the trumpet in Zion, sanctify a fast, call an assembly.

16 Gather the people, sanctify the church, unite the elders, gather together the little ones and infants at the breast. Let the bridegroom depart from his bed, and the bride from her bridal chamber.

17 Between the vestibule and the altar, the priests, the ministers of the Lord, will weep, and they will say: "Spare, O Lord, spare your people. And do not bequeath your inheritance into disgrace, so that the nations would rule over them. Why should they say among the peoples, 'Where is their God?' "

18 The Lord has been zealous for his land, and he has spared his people.

19 And the Lord responded, and he said to his people: "Behold, I will send you grain and wine and oil, and you will again be filled with them. And I will no longer give you disgrace among the Gentiles.

20 And he who is from the North, I will drive far from you. And I will expel him into an impassable land, and into the desert, with his face opposite the Eastern sea, and his furthest part towards the furthest sea. And his stench will ascend, and his rottenness will ascend, because he has acted arrogantly.

21 Earth, do not be afraid. Exult and rejoice. For the Lord has great esteem for what he has done.

22 Animals of the countryside, do not be afraid. For the beauty of the wilderness has sprung forth. For the tree has borne its fruit. The fig tree and the vine have bestowed their virtue.

23 And you, sons of Zion, exult and rejoice in the Lord your God. For he has given you a teacher of justice, and he will make the early and the late rains descend to you, just as it was in the beginning.

24 And the threshing floors will be filled with grain, and the presses will overflow with wine and oil.

25 And I will repay you for the years which the locust, and the beetle, and the mildew, and the caterpillar consumed: my great strength which I sent upon you.

26 And you will eat with enjoyment, and you will be satisfied, and you will praise the name of the Lord your God, who has worked miracles with you, and my people will not be confounded forever.

27 And you will know that I am in the midst of Israel, and I am the Lord your God, and there is no other, and my people will not be confounded forever.

28 And after this, it will happen that I will pour out my spirit upon all flesh, and your sons and your daughters will prophesy; your elders will dream dreams, and your youths will see visions.

29 Moreover, in those days I will pour out my spirit upon my servants and handmaids.

30 And I will grant wonders in the sky and on earth: blood and fire and the vapor of smoke.

31 The sun will be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood, before the great and terrible day of the Lord shall arrive.

32 And it will happen that everyone who will call upon the name of the Lord will be saved. For on Mount Zion, and in Jerusalem, and in the remnant whom the Lord will call, there will be salvation, just as the Lord has said.

Joel 3

1 For, behold, in those days and in that time, when I will have converted the captivity of Judah and Jerusalem,

2 I will gather all the Gentiles, and will lead them into the valley of Jehoshaphat. And there I will dispute with them over my people, and over Israel, my inheritance, for they have scattered them among the nations and have divided my land.

3 And they have cast lots over my people; and the boy they have placed in the brothel, and the girl they have sold for wine, so that they might drink.

4 Truly, what is there between you and me, Tyre and Sidon and all the distant places of the Philistines? How will you take vengeance on me? And if you were to revenge yourselves against me, I would deliver a repayment to you, quickly and soon, upon your head.

5 For you have carried away my silver and gold. And my desirable and most beautiful, you have taken into your shrines.

6 And you, sons of Judah and sons of Jerusalem, you have sold the sons of the Greeks, so that you might drive them far from their own territory.

7 Behold, I will raise them up from the place into which you have sold them, and I will turn back your retribution on your own head.

8 And I will sell your sons and your daughters into the hands of the sons of Judah, and they will sell them to the Sabeans, a distant nation, for the Lord has spoken.

9 Proclaim this among the Gentiles: "Sanctify a war, raise up the strong. Approach, ascend, all men of war.

10 Cut your ploughs into swords and your hoes into spears. Let the weak say, 'For I am strong.'

11 Break out and advance, all nations of the world, and gather together. There the Lord will cause all your strong ones to meet death."

12 Let them arise and ascend to the valley of Jehoshaphat. For there I will sit, so as to judge all the nations of the world.

13 Send forth the sickles, because the harvest has matured. Advance and descend, for the press is full, the pressing room is overflowing. For their malice has been increasing.

14 Nations, nations in the valley of being cut to pieces: for the day of the Lord fittingly takes place in the valley of being cut to pieces.

15 The sun and the moon have been darkened, and the stars have withdrawn their splendor.

16 And the Lord will roar from Zion and utter his voice from Jerusalem. And the heavens and the earth will be moved. And the Lord will be the hope of his people and the strength of the sons of Israel.

17 And you will know that I am the Lord your God, dwelling on Zion, my holy mountain. And Jerusalem will be holy, and strangers will not cross through it anymore.

18 And it will happen, in that day, that the mountains will drip sweetness, and the hills will flow with milk. And the waters will pass through all the rivers of Judah. And a fountain will go forth from the house of the Lord, and it will irrigate the desert of thorns.

19 Egypt will be in desolation, and Edom will be a wilderness destroyed, because of what they have unfairly done to the sons of Judah, and because they have shed innocent blood in their land.

20 And Judea will be inhabited forever, and Jerusalem for generation upon generation.

21 And I will cleanse their blood, which I had not cleansed. And the Lord will remain in Zion.

Amos 1

1 The words of Amos, who was among the shepherds of Tekoa, which he saw about Israel in the days of Uzziah king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash king of Israel, two years before the earthquake.

2 And he said: The Lord will roar from Zion, and from Jerusalem he will utter his voice. And the beautiful pastures have mourned, and the top of Carmel has become dry.

3 Thus says the Lord: For three wicked deeds of Damascus, and for four, I will not convert it, in so far as they have threshed Gilead into iron wagons.

4 And I will send fire onto the house of Hazael, and it will devour the houses of Ben-hadad.

5 And I will shatter the crowbar of Damascus, and I will destroy the inhabitants of the camp of the idol and the holder of the scepter of the house of pleasure; and the people of Syria will be transferred to Cyrene, says the Lord.

6 Thus says the Lord: For three wicked deeds of Gaza, and for four, I will not convert it, in so far as they have carried out an excellent captivity, so as to enclose them in Idumea.

7 And I will send a fire onto the wall of Gaza, and it will devour its buildings.

8 And I will destroy the inhabitant from Ashdod, and the holder of the scepter of Ashkelon. And I will turn my hand against Ekron, and the remainder of the Philistines will perish, says the Lord God.

9 Thus says the Lord: For three wicked deeds of Tyre, and for four, I will not convert it, in so far as they have completed an excellent captivity in Idumea and have not considered the bond among brothers.

10 And I will send a fire onto the wall of Tyre, and it will devour its buildings.

11 Thus says the Lord: For three wicked deeds of Edom, and for four, I will not convert him, in so far as he has been pursuing his brother with the sword and has outraged his brother's compassion, and he has gone beyond his anger and has held onto his indignation until the end.

12 I will send a fire onto Teman, and it will devour the buildings of Bozrah.

13 Thus says the Lord: For three wicked deeds of the sons of Ammon, and for four, I will not convert him, in so far as he has cut up the pregnant women of Gilead, so as to expand his limits.

14 And I will ignite a fire on the wall of Rabbah. And it will devour its buildings, with wailing on the day of war, and with a whirlwind on the day of commotion.

15 And Melchom will go into captivity, he and his leaders together, says the Lord.

Amos 2

1 Thus says the Lord: For three wicked deeds of Moab, and for four, I will not convert him, in so far as he has burned the bones of the king of Idumea, all the way to ashes.

2 And I will send a fire onto Moab, and it will devour the buildings of Kerioth. And Moab will die with a noise, with the blare of a trumpet.

3 And I will destroy the judge in their midst, and I will execute all his leaders with him, says the Lord.

4 Thus says the Lord: For three wicked deeds of Judah, and for four, I will not convert him, in so far as he has rejected the law of the Lord and has not kept his commandments. For their idols, which their fathers followed, have deceived them.

5 And I will send a fire onto Judah, and it will devour the buildings of Jerusalem.

6 Thus says the Lord: For three wicked deeds of Israel, and for four, I will not convert him, in so far as he has sold the just for silver and the poor for shoes.

7 They grind the heads of the poor into the dust of the earth, and they divert the way of the humble. And the son, as well as his father, have gone to the same girl, so that they outrage my holy name.

8 And they have lain on garments taken in pledge next to every altar. And they drank the wine of the damned in the house of their God.

9 Yet I exterminated the Amorites before their face, whose height was like the height of cedars, and whose strength was like the oak. And I crushed his fruit from above and his roots below.

10 It is I who caused you to ascend from the land of Egypt, and I led you in the wilderness for forty years, so that you might possess the land of the Amorite.

11 And I stirred up prophets from your sons, and Nazirites from your young men. Is it not so, sons of Israel, says the Lord?

12 Yet you would offer wine to the Nazirites, and you would command the prophets, saying: "Do not prophesy."

13 Behold, I will creak under you, just as a wagon creaks that is laden with hay.

14 And flight will perish from the swift, and the strong will not maintain his strength, and the healthy will not save his life.

15 And one holding the bow will not stand firm, and the swift of foot will not be saved, and the rider on the horse will not save his life.

16 And the stout of heart among the strong will flee away naked in that day, says the Lord.

Amos 3

1 Listen to the word which the Lord has spoken about you, sons of Israel, concerning the whole family that I led out of the land of Egypt, saying:

2 I have known only you in such a way, out of all the families of the earth. For this reason, I will visit upon you all your iniquities.

3 Will two walk together, unless they have agreed to do so?

4 Will a lion roar in the forest, unless he has prey? Will the lion's young cry out from his den, unless he has taken something?

5 Will a bird fall into a snare on the ground, if there is no bird-catcher? Will a snare be taken away from the ground, before it has caught something?

6 Will the trumpet sound in a city, and the people not become frightened? Will there be disaster in a city, which the Lord has not done?

7 For the Lord God does not fulfill his word, unless he has revealed his secret to his servants the prophets.

8 The lion will roar, who will not fear? The Lord God has spoken, who will not prophesy?

9 Let it be heard in the buildings of Ashdod and in the buildings of the land of Egypt, and say: Gather together across the mountains of Samaria, and see the many absurdities in its midst, and those who are suffering false accusations in its inner most places.

10 And they do not know how to make it right, says the Lord, storing up iniquity and plunder in their buildings.

11 Because of these things, thus says the Lord God: The land will be encircled and squeezed together. And your strength will be drawn away from you, and your buildings will be torn apart.

12 Thus says the Lord: Just as if a shepherd had rescued two legs from the mouth of a lion, or the tip of an ear, so also will the sons of Israel be rescued, who dwell in the sick bed of Samaria, and in the cot of Damascus.

13 Listen and give testimony in the house of Jacob, says the Lord God of hosts:

14 that in the day, when I will begin to visit the betrayals of Israel, I will visit upon him and upon the altars of Bethel. And the horns of the altars will be cut off and will fall to the ground.

15 And I will strike the winter house with the summer house; and the houses of ivory will perish, and many buildings will be torn apart, says the Lord.

Amos 4

1 Listen to this word, you fat cows that are on the mountain of Samaria, you who make false accusations against the destitute and crush the poor, who say to your nobles, "Bring, and we will drink."

2 The Lord God has sworn in his holiness: behold, the days that will overcome you and that will impale you on poles, and that will place what remains of you in boiling pots.

3 And you will go out through the breaches, one over another, and you will be cast out into Harmon, says the Lord.

4 Come to Bethel and behave impiously, to Gilgal and increase betrayals. And bring daybreak to your victims, your tithes in three days.

5 And offer a sacrifice of praise with leaven. And call for voluntary oblations, and announce it. For such is your will, sons of Israel, says the Lord God.

6 Therefore, because of this, I have given you dull teeth in every one of your cities, and a lack of bread in all your places. And you have not been turned back towards me, says the Lord.

7 Therefore, I have withheld the rains from you, when there were still three months left until the harvest. And I rained on one city, and I did not rain on another city; one part was rained on, and the part on which I did not rain, dried out.

8 And two and three cities went to one city, in order to drink water, and they were not satisfied. And you did not return to me, says the Lord.

9 I struck you with a burning wind and with yellowing; the caterpillar has consumed your many gardens and your vineyards, your olive groves and your fig groves. And you did not return to me, says the Lord.

10 I sent death to you by way of Egypt; I struck your youths with the sword, even bringing captivity to your horses. And I made the stench of your camp ascend into your nostrils. And you did not return to me, says the Lord.

11 I overturned you, just as God overturned Sodom and Gomorrah, and you became like an ember seized from the fire. And you did not return to me, says the Lord.

12 Because of this, I will do these things to you, Israel. But after I have done these things to you, Israel, be prepared to meet your God.

13 For behold, he who forms the mountains and creates the wind and announces his speech to man, who makes the morning mist and steps over the heights of the earth: the Lord God of hosts is his name.

Amos 5

1 Listen to this word, which I lift over you in lamentation. The house of Israel has fallen, and it will no longer rise again.

2 The virgin of Israel has been thrown onto her land, there is no one who can raise her up.

3 For thus says the Lord God: In the city from which a thousand departed, a hundred will remain, and in that from which a hundred departed, ten will remain, in the house of Israel.

4 For thus says the Lord to the house of Israel: Seek me and you will live.

5 But do not be willing to seek Bethel, and do not be willing to enter Gilgal, and you will not cross into Beer-sheba. For Gilgal will be led into captivity, and Bethel will be useless.

6 Seek the Lord and live. Otherwise, the house of Joseph may be destroyed with fire, and it will devour, and there will be no one who can extinguish Bethel.

7 You turn judgment into wormwood, and you abandon justice on earth.

8 The Maker of Arcturus and Orion, who turns darkness into daybreak and who changes day into night; who calls forth the waters of the sea and who pours them out over the face of the earth: The Lord is his name.

9 It is he who smiles destruction on the healthy, and who brings pillaging upon the powerful.

10 They held hatred for the one who corrects at the gate, and they have abhorred the one who speaks perfectly.

11 Therefore, on his behalf, because you have torn apart the poor and stolen choice prey from him: you will build houses with square stones and you will not dwell in them; you will plant the most delightful vineyards, and you will not drink wine from them.

12 For I know your many wicked deeds and the strength of your sins, you enemies of the just, accepting bribes, and depriving the poor at the gate.

13 Therefore, the prudent will be silent at that time, for it is an evil time.

14 Seek good and not evil, so that you may live. And the Lord God of hosts will be with you, just as you have asked.

15 Hate evil and love good, and establish judgment at the gate. Perhaps then the Lord God of hosts may have mercy on the remnant of Joseph.

16 Therefore, thus says the Lord God of hosts, the Sovereign: In all the streets, there will be wailing. And in every place where they are outdoors, they will say, "Woe, woe!" And they will call the farmer to mourn, and those who know mourning to lamentation.

17 And in all the vineyards there will be wailing. For I will cross through your midst, says the Lord.

18 Woe to those who desire the day of the Lord. What is it to you? The day of the Lord is this: darkness and not light.

19 It is as if a man flees from the face of a lion, only to have a bear meet him; or, he enters a house and leans with his hand against the wall, only to have a snake bite him.

20 Will not the day of the Lord be darkness and not light, and gloom with no brightness in it?

21 I hate and have rejected your feasts; and I will not accept the odor from your gatherings.

22 For if you offer me holocausts and your gifts, I will not receive them; and I will not look upon the vows of your fatness.

23 Take away from me the tumult of your songs, and I will not listen to the canticles of your lyre.

24 And judgment will be revealed like water, and justice like a mighty torrent.

25 Was it you who offered victims and sacrifices to me in the desert for forty years, house of Israel?

26 And you carried a tabernacle for your Moloch and the image of your idols: the star of your god, which you made for yourselves.

27 And I will cause you to go into captivity across Damascus, says the Lord. The God of hosts is his name.

Amos 6

1 Woe to you who have been wealthy in Zion, and to you who have confidence in the mountain of Samaria: aristocrats, heads of the people, who advance with a retinue into the house of Israel.

2 Cross over to Calneh and see, and go from there into Hamath the great, and descend into Gath of the Philistines, and to the best kingdoms of these, if their limits are wider than your limits.

3 You have been set aside for the day of disaster, and you approach the throne of iniquity.

4 You sleep on beds of ivory, and you are lustful on your couches. You devour lambs from the flock and calves from the midst of the herd.

5 You sing to the sound of stringed instruments; they consider themselves to have the musical abilities of David.

6 You drink wine in bowls, and you anoint with the best ointments; and they suffer nothing over the grief of Joseph.

7 Because of this, now they will depart at the head of those who go into captivity; and the faction of the lustful will be removed.

8 The Lord God has sworn by his own soul, the Lord God of hosts says: I detest the arrogance of Jacob, and I hate his houses, and I will hand over the city with its inhabitants.

9 For if there were ten men remaining in one house, even they will die.

10 And his closest relative will steal him away and will burn him, so that he may carry the bones out of the house. And he will say to him that is in the inner most rooms of the house, "Now is there any left that still belongs to you?"

11 And he will answer, "It is finished." And he will say to him, "Be silent and do not call to mind the name of the Lord."

12 For behold, the Lord has commanded, and he will strike the greater house with catastrophes, and the lesser house with divisions.

13 Can horses gallop across rocks, or is anyone able to plough with gazelles? For you have turned judgment into bitterness and the fruit of justice into wormwood.

14 You rejoice in emptiness. You say, "Have we not, by our own strength, taken horns for ourselves?"

15 For behold, house of Israel, I will raise up a people over you, says the Lord God of hosts, and they will crush you from the entrance of Hamath all the way to the burning of the desert.

Amos 7

1 These things the Lord God has revealed to me. And behold, the locust was formed at the beginning of the germination during the latter rains, and behold, the latter rains came after the thundering of the king.

2 And it happened, when they had finally eaten all the grass in the land, that I said, "Lord God, be gracious, I beg you. Who will raise up Jacob, for he is little?"

3 The Lord has been merciful about this. "It will not be," said the Lord.

4 These things the Lord God has revealed to me. And behold, the Lord God called for judgment unto fire, and it devoured the manifold abyss, and it consumed simultaneously in every direction.

5 And I said, "Lord God, cease, I beg you. Who will raise up Jacob, for he is little?"

6 The Lord has been merciful about this. "And even this will not be," said the Lord God.

7 These things the Lord revealed to me. And behold, the Lord was standing near a plastered wall, and in his hand was a mason's trowel.

8 And the Lord said to me, "What do you see, Amos?" And I said, "A mason's trowel." And the Lord said, "Behold, I will place the trowel in the midst of my people Israel. I will no longer plaster over them.

9 And the heights of the idol will be demolished, and the sanctuaries of Israel will be desolate. And I will rise up against the house of Jeroboam with the sword."

10 And Amaziah, the priest of Bethel, sent to Jeroboam king of Israel, saying: "Amos has rebelled against you in the midst of the house of Israel. The land is not able to withstand all his sermons.

11 For Amos says this: 'Jeroboam will die by the sword, and Israel will be taken captive out of their own land.' "

12 And Amaziah said to Amos, "You, seer, go out and flee into the land of Judah, and eat bread there, and prophesy there.

13 And in Bethel, do not prophesy any longer, because it is the king's sanctuary, and it is the house of the kingdom."

14 And Amos responded, and he said to Amasias, "I am not a prophet, and I am not the son of a prophet, but I am a herdsman plucking from wild fig trees.

15 And the Lord took me, when I was following the flock, and the Lord said to me, 'Go, prophesy to my people Israel.' "

16 And now, hear the word of the Lord: You say, "You will not prophesy about Israel, and you will not rain your words upon the house of the idol."

17 Because of that, the Lord says this: "Your wife will fornicate in the city, and your sons and your daughters will fall by the sword, and your soil will be measured with a string. And you will die on polluted land, and Israel will be taken into captivity out of their land."

Amos 8

1 These things the Lord has revealed to me. And behold, a hook to draw down fruit.

2 And he said, "What do you see, Amos?" And I said, "A hook to draw down fruit." And the Lord said to me, "The end has come for my people Israel. I will no longer pass through them."

3 And the hinges of the temple will creak in that day, says the Lord God. Many will die. Silence will be thrown away in all places.

4 Hear this, you who crush the poor and who make those in need of land to do without.

5 You say, "When will the first day of the month be over, so we can sell our wares, and the sabbath, so we can open the grain: in order that we may decrease the measure, and increase the price, and substitute deceitful scales,

6 in order that we may possess the destitute with money, and the poor for a pair of shoes, and may sell even the refuse of the grain?"

7 The Lord has sworn by the arrogance of Jacob: I will not forget, even to the end, all their works.

8 Will not the earth shudder over this, and all its inhabitants mourn, and all rise up like a river, and be cast out, and flow away like the river of Egypt?

9 And it will be in that day, says the Lord God, that the sun will decline at midday, and I will cause the earth to become dark on the day of light.

10 And I will turn your feasts into mourning, and all your hymns into lamentation. And I will put sackcloth over every one of your backs, and baldness on every head. And I will begin it like the mourning for an only-begotten son, and complete it like a bitter day.

11 Behold, the days pass, says the Lord, and I will send a famine on the earth: not a famine of bread, nor of thirst for water, but for hearing the word of the Lord.

12 And they will move even from sea to sea, and from the North all the way to the East. They will wander around seeking the word of the Lord, and they will not find it.

13 In that day, beautiful virgins, and young men, will fail because of thirst.

14 They swear by the offense of Samaria, and they say, "As your God lives, Dan," and "The way of Beer-sheba lives." And they will fall, and they will not rise up any more.

Obadiah 1

1 The vision of Obadiah. Thus says the Lord God to Edom: We have heard a report from the Lord, and he has sent an envoy to the nations: "Arise, and let us together rise up in battle against him."

2 Behold, I have made you little among the nations. You are greatly contemptible.

3 The arrogance of your heart has lifted you up, living in the clefts of the rocks, exalting your throne. You say in your heart, "Who will pull me down to the ground?"

4 Though you have been lifted high like an eagle, and though you have placed your nest among the stars, from there I will pull you down, says the Lord.

5 If thieves had approached you, if robbers by night, how would you have remained unnoticed? Would they not have stolen all that they wanted? If the grape-pickers had approached you, would they not have left you at least a cluster?

6 In what way have they been examining Esau? They investigated his secrets.

7 They have sent you out all the way to the limit. All the men of your alliance have deceived you. Your men of peace have prevailed against you. Those who eat with you will place snares under you. There is no foresight in him.

8 Shall I not, in that day, says the Lord, wipe away understanding from Idumea and foresight from the mount of Esau?

9 And your strong from the Meridian will be afraid, so that man may perish from the mount of Esau.

10 Because of the execution, and because of the iniquity against your brother Jacob, confusion will cover you, and you will pass away into eternity.

11 In the day when you stood against him, when strangers seized his army, and foreigners entered into his gates, and they cast lots over Jerusalem: you also were just like one of them.

12 But you shall not show disdain for the day of your brother in the day of his sojourn. And you shall not rejoice over the sons of Judah in the day of their perdition. And you shall not magnify your mouth in the day of anguish.

13 And neither shall you enter into the gate of my people in the day of their ruin. And neither shall you also show disdain for his troubles in the day of his desolation. And you shall not send out against his army in the day of his desolation.

14 Neither shall you stand at the exits to execute those who will flee. And you shall not enclose their remnant in the day of tribulation.

15 For the day of the Lord is near, over all nations. Just as you have done, so will it be done to you. He will turn back your retribution on your own head.

16 For in the manner that you drank on my holy mountain, so shall all nations drink continually. And they will drink, and they will absorb, and they will be as if they were not.

17 And on mount Zion there will be salvation, and it will be holy. And the house of Jacob will possess those who had possessed them.

18 And the house of Jacob will be a fire, and the house of Joseph a flame, and the house of Esau stubble. And they will be set on fire among them, and they will devour them. And there will be no remnant of the house of Esau, for the Lord has spoken.

19 And those who are towards the South, and who are in the camps of the Philistines, will inherit the mount of Esau. And they will possess the region of Ephraim, and the region of Samaria. And Benjamin will possess Gilead.

20 And the exiles of this army of the sons of Israel, all the places of the Canaanites all the way to Sarepta, and the exiles of Jerusalem who are in Bosphoro, will possess the cities of the South.

21 And the saviors will ascend to mount Zion to judge the mount of Esau. And the kingdom will be for the Lord.

Jonah 1

1 And the word of the Lord came to Jonah the son of Amittai, saying:

2 Rise and go to Nineveh, the great city, and preach in it. For its malice has ascended before my eyes.

3 And Jonah rose in order to flee from the face of the Lord to Tarshish. And he went down to Joppa and found a ship bound for Tarshish. And he paid its fare, and he went down into it, in order to go with them to Tarshish from the face of the Lord.

4 But the Lord sent a great wind into the sea. And a great tempest took place in the sea, and the ship was in danger of being crushed.

5 And the mariners were afraid, and the men cried out to their god. And they threw the containers that were in the ship into the sea in order to lighten it of them. And Jonah went down into the interior of the ship, and he fell into a painful deep sleep.

6 And the helmsman approached him, and he said to him, "Why are you weighed down with sleep? Rise, call upon your God, so perhaps God will be mindful of us and we might not perish."

7 And a man said to his shipmate, "Come, and let us cast lots, so that we may know why this disaster is upon us." And they cast lots, and the lot fell upon Jonah.

8 And they said to him: "Explain to us what is the reason that this disaster is upon us. What is your work? Which is your country? And where are you going? Or which people are you from?"

9 And he said to them, "I am Hebrew, and I fear the Lord God of heaven, who made the sea and the dry land."

10 And the men were greatly afraid, and they said to him, "Why have you done this?" (For the men knew that he was fleeing from the face of the Lord, because he had told them.)

11 And they said to him, "What are we to do with you, so that the sea will cease for us?" For the sea flowed and swelled.

12 And he said to them, "Take me, and cast me into the sea, and the sea will cease for you. For I know that it is because of me that this great tempest has come upon you."

13 And the men were rowing, so as to return to dry land, but they did not succeed. For the sea flowed and swelled against them.

14 And they cried out to the Lord, and they said, "We beseech you, Lord, do not let us perish for this man's life, and do not attribute to us innocent blood. For you, Lord, have done just as it pleased you."

15 And they took Jonah and cast him into the sea. And the sea was stilled from its fury.

16 And the men feared the Lord greatly, and they sacrificed victims to the Lord, and they made vows.

Jonah 2

1 And the Lord prepared a great fish to swallow Jonah. And Jonah was in the belly of the fish for three days and three nights.

2 And Jonah prayed to the Lord, his God, from the belly of the fish.

3 And he said: "I cried out to the Lord from my tribulation, and he heeded me. From the belly of hell, I cried out, and you heeded my voice.

4 And you have thrown me into the deep, in the heart of the sea, and a flood has encircled me. All your whirlpools and your waves have passed over me.

5 And I said: I am expelled from the sight of your eyes. Yet, truly, I will see your holy temple again.

6 The waters surrounded me, even to the soul. The abyss has walled me in. The ocean has covered my head.

7 I descended to the base of the mountains. The bars of the earth have enclosed me forever. And you will raise up my life from corruption, Lord, my God.

8 When my soul was in anguish within me, I called to mind the Lord, so that my prayer might come to you, to your holy temple.

9 Those who in vain observe vanities, abandon their own mercy.

10 But I, with a voice of praise, will sacrifice to you. I will repay whatever I have vowed to the Lord, because of my salvation."

11 And the Lord spoke to the fish, and it vomited Jonah onto dry land.

Jonah 3

1 And the word of the Lord came to Jonah a second time, saying:

2 Rise, and go to Nineveh, the great city. And preach in it the preaching that I say to you.

3 And Jonah rose, and he went to Nineveh in accordance with the word of the Lord. And Nineveh was a great city of three days' journey.

4 And Jonah began to enter into the city one day's journey. And he cried out and said, "Forty days more and Nineveh shall be destroyed."

5 And the men of Nineveh believed in God. And they proclaimed a fast, and they put on sackcloth, from the greatest all the way to the least.

6 And word reached the king of Nineveh. And he rose from his throne, and he threw off his robe from himself and was clothed in sackcloth, and he sat in ashes.

7 And he cried out and spoke: "In Nineveh, from the mouth of the king and of his princes, let it be said: Men and beasts and oxen and sheep may not taste anything. Neither shall they feed or drink water.

8 And let men and beasts be covered with sackcloth, and let them cry out to the Lord with strength, and may man be converted from his evil way, and from the iniquity that is in their hands.

9 Who knows if God may turn and forgive, and may turn away from his furious wrath, so that we might not perish?"

10 And God saw their works, that they had been converted from their evil way. And God took pity on them, concerning the harm that he had said he would do to them, and he did not do it.

Jonah 4

1 And Jonah was afflicted with a great affliction, and he was angry.

2 And he prayed to the Lord, and he said, "I beg you, Lord, was this not my word, when I was still in my own land? Because of this, I knew beforehand to flee into Tarshish. For I know that you are a lenient and merciful God, patient and great in compassion, and forgiving despite ill will.

3 And now, Lord, I ask you to take my life from me. For it is better for me to die than to live."

4 And the Lord said, "Do you really think you are right to be angry?"

5 And Jonah went out of the city, and he sat opposite the east of the city. And he made himself a shelter there, and he was sitting under it in the shadow, until he might see what would befall the city.

6 And the Lord God prepared an ivy, and it ascended over the head of Jonah so as to be a shadow over his head, and to protect him (for he had labored hard). And Jonah rejoiced because of the ivy, with great rejoicing.

7 And God prepared a worm, when dawn approached on the next day, and it struck the ivy, and it dried up.

8 And when the sun had risen, the Lord ordered a hot and burning wind. And the sun beat down on the head of Jonah, and he burned. And he petitioned for his soul that he might die, and he said, "It is better for me to die than to live."

9 And the Lord said to Jonah, "Do you really think that you are right to be angry because of the ivy?" And he said, "I am right to be angry even unto death."

10 And the Lord said, "You grieve for the ivy, for which you have not labored and which you did not cause to grow, though it had been born during one night, and during one night perished.

11 And shall I not spare Nineveh, the great city, in which there are more than one hundred and twenty thousand men, who do not know the difference between their right and their left, and many beasts?"

Micah 1

1 The word of the Lord that came to Micah the Moreshethite, in the days of Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, which he saw about Samaria and Jerusalem.

2 All peoples, listen. And may the earth and its fullness pay attention. And may the Lord God be a witness to you, the Lord from his holy temple.

3 For behold, the Lord will go forth from his place. And he will descend, and he will trample over the high places of the earth.

4 And the mountains will be consumed under him, and the valleys will be torn apart, like wax before the face of fire, and like waters that rush swiftly downward.

5 All this is for the wickedness of Jacob and for the sins of the house of Israel. What is the wickedness of Jacob? Is it not Samaria? And what is the loftiness of Judah? Is it not Jerusalem?

6 And I will place Samaria like a pile of stones in the field, when a vineyard is planted. And I will pull down its stones into the valley, and I will reveal her foundations.

7 And all her graven images will be cut to pieces, and all her rewards will be burned with fire, and I will place all her idols in perdition. For they have been gathered together from the pay of a kept woman, and even to the pay of a kept woman, they will return.

8 I will lament and wail about this. I will go out despoiled and naked. I will make a howl like the dragons, and a mourning like the ostriches.

9 For her wound has been in despair. For it has come even to Judah. It has touched the gate of my people, even to Jerusalem.

10 Do not be willing to announce it in Gath; may you not lament with tears. In the house of Dust, besprinkle yourselves with dust.

11 And cross over to your dwelling place, Beauty, bewildered by disgrace. She did not depart, who dwells at the place of departure. The House nearby, which remained firm by herself, will receive mourning from you.

12 For she has been weakened in goodness, who dwells in bitterness. For disaster has descended from the Lord to the gate of Jerusalem.

13 A tumult of four-horse chariots has stupefied the inhabitants of Lachish. The beginning has been sin for the daughter of Zion, because in you have been found the evil deeds of Israel.

14 Because of this, she will send emissaries to the inheritance of Gath: the house of Lying in order to deceive the kings of Israel.

15 Nevertheless, I will lead an heir to you, who dwell in Mareshah: the glory of Israel will reach all the way to Adullam.

16 Become bald and shaved for your delicate sons. Increase your baldness like the eagle. For they have been carried into captivity from you.

Micah 2

1 Woe to you who devise useless things and who work evil in your beds. In the morning light, they undertake it, because their hand is against God.

2 And they have desired fields and have taken them by violence, and they have stolen houses. And they have made false accusations against a man and his house, a man and his inheritance.

3 For this reason, thus says the Lord: Behold, I devise an evil against this family, from which you will not steal away your necks. And you will not walk in arrogance, because this is a most wicked time.

4 In that day, a parable will be taken up about you, and a song will be sung with sweetness, saying: "We have been devastated by depopulation." The fate of my people has been altered. How can he withdraw from me, when he might be turned back, he who might tear apart our country?

5 Because of this, there will be for you no casting of the cord of fate in the assembly of the Lord.

6 Do not speak by saying, "It will not drop on these ones; shame will not embrace them."

7 The house of Jacob says, "Has the Spirit of the Lord been weakened, or are such things his thoughts?" Are not my words good for him who walks uprightly?

8 But, to the contrary, my people have risen up in opposition. You have lifted the cover from the undergarment, and those who passed by harmlessly, you have converted into war.

9 You have evicted the women among my people from their delicate houses. You have taken my praise forever from their little ones.

10 Rise and depart, for there is no relief for you here. Because of its uncleanness, it will be corrupted with a most wicked decay.

11 I wish that I were not a man who has breath, and that I rather spoke a lie. I will drop it down to you in wine and in drunkenness. And it will be this people on whom it will rain down.

12 I will gather together in a congregation all of you, Jacob. I will lead together as one, the remnant of Israel. I will set them together like a flock in the fold, like a sheep in the midst of the sheep pen. They will cause a tumult before the multitude of men.

13 For he will ascend, opening the way before them. They will separate, and they will cross the gate and enter through it. And their king will pass by, before their very eyes, and the Lord will be at their head.

Micah 3

1 And I said: Listen, leaders of Jacob and chiefs of the house of Israel. Does it not belong to you to know judgment,

2 you who hold hatred for good, and love evil, who violently steal their skins from over them and their flesh from over their bones?

3 They have devoured the flesh of my people, and have stripped their skin from over them, and they have shattered and chopped their bones, as if for the kettle, and like flesh in the middle of the pot.

4 Then they will cry out to the Lord, and he will not heed them. And he will hide his face from them in that time, just as they have acted wickedly with their inventions.

5 Thus says the Lord about the prophets who seduce my people: They bite with their teeth and preach peace, and if anyone does not give something to their mouth, they sanctify a battle against him.

6 Because of this, night will be yours for vision, and darkness yours for divination, and the sun will meet with death over the prophets, and the day will be darkened over them.

7 And those who see visions will be confounded, and the diviners will be confounded. And they will all cover their faces, because there is no response from God.

8 Nevertheless, truly I have been filled with the strength of the Spirit of the Lord, with judgment and virtue, in order to announce to Jacob his wickedness and to Israel his sin.

9 Hear this, leaders of the house of Jacob and judges of the house of Israel, you who abominate judgment and who pervert all that is right.

10 You build up Zion with blood, and Jerusalem with iniquity.

11 Her leaders have judged for tributes, and her priests have taught for payment, and her prophets divined for money. And they leaned upon the Lord, saying: "Is not the Lord in our midst? No disaster will overcome us."

12 For this reason, because of you, Zion will be plowed under like a field, and Jerusalem will become like a pile of stones, and the mountain of the temple like the high places of the forests.

Micah 4

1 And this shall be: In the last days, the mountain of the house of the Lord will be prepared at the top of the mountains and high above the hills. And the people will flow to it.

2 And many nations will hurry, and will say: "Come, let us ascend to the mountain of the Lord and to the house of the God of Jacob. And he will teach us about his ways, and we will walk in his paths." For the law will go forth from Zion, and the word of the Lord from Jerusalem.

3 And he will judge among the many peoples, and he will correct strong nations, even from afar. And they will cut up their swords into plows, and their spears into hoes. Nation will not take up the sword against nation, and they will no longer learn to wage war.

4 And a man will sit under his vine and under his fig tree, and there will be no one to fear, for the mouth of the Lord of hosts has spoken.

5 For all people will walk, each one in the name of his god. But we will walk in the name of the Lord our God, forever and ever.

6 In that day, says the Lord, I will gather together the lame. And I will recover her whom I had rejected, and her whom I had afflicted.

7 And I will place the lame within the remnant, and she who had been in distress, within a healthy people. And the Lord will reign over them on Mount Zion, from the present time and even unto eternity.

8 And you, cloudy tower of the flock of the daughter of Zion, even to you it will come. And the first power will arrive, the kingdom to the daughter of Jerusalem.

9 Now, why have you come together in grief? Is there not a king in you, or has your counselor gone away? For sorrow has overtaken you, like the pain of giving birth.

10 Be grieved and overwhelmed, daughter of Zion, like a woman giving birth. For now you must depart from the city and dwell in the countryside, and you will approach even to Babylon. There you will be delivered. There the Lord will redeem you from the hand of your adversaries.

11 And now many peoples have been gathered together against you, and they say, "Let her be stoned and let our eyes gaze upon Zion."

12 But they have not known the thoughts of the Lord, and they have not understood his counsel. For he has gathered them together like hay on a threshing floor.

13 Rise and thresh, daughter of Zion. For I will set your horn like iron, and I will set your hoofs like brass. And you will shatter many peoples, and you will immolate their spoils for the Lord, and their strength for the Lord of the whole earth.

Micah 5

1 Now you will be devastated, you daughter of a robber. They have placed a blockade against us, with a rod they will strike the jaw of the judge of Israel.

2 And you, Bethlehem Ephrata, are a little one among the thousands of Judah. From you will go forth he who shall be the ruler in Israel, and his landing place has been set from the beginning, from the days of eternity.

3 Because of this, he will provide for them, even until the time in which she who bears him gives birth. And the remnant of his brothers will be converted to the sons of Israel.

4 And he will stand firm and feed on the strength of the Lord, according to the sublime name of the Lord his God. And they will be converted, for now he will be magnified, even to the ends of the earth.

5 And this man will be our peace, when the Assyrian will come into our land, and when he will trample on our houses; and we will raise against him seven shepherds and eight principal men.

6 And they will graze on the land of Assur with the sword, and the land of Nimrod with its spears; and he will free us from Assur, when he will come into our land, and when he will trample our borders.

7 And there will be a remnant of Jacob in the midst of many peoples, like a dew from the Lord and like drops upon the grass, which awaits no man and does not stand before the sons of men.

8 And there will be a remnant of Jacob within the Gentiles, in the midst of many peoples, like a lion among the beasts of the forests, and like a young lion among the flocks of sheep, who, when he will pass through and trample down and seize, there is none who can rescue.

9 Your hand will be exalted over your enemies, and all your adversaries will pass away.

10 And it will be in that day, says the Lord: I will take away your horses from your midst, and I will utterly ruin your four-horse chariots.

11 And I will destroy the cities of your land, and I will pull down all your fortifications, and I will take away evil-doing from your hand, and there will be no divinations among you.

12 And I will cause your graven images to perish, and your statues, from your midst. And you will no longer adore the works of your hands.

13 And I will root out your sacred groves from your midst, and I will crush your cities.

14 And I will exact vengeance, in fury and in indignation, among all the nations which have not listened.

Micah 6

1 Listen to what the Lord says: Rise, contend in judgment against the mountains, and let the hills hear your voice.

2 Let the mountains listen to the judgment of the Lord, and the strong foundations of the earth. For the judgment of the Lord is with his people, and he will enter into judgment with Israel.

3 My people, what have I done to you, or how have I assailed you? Respond to me.

4 For I led you out of the land of Egypt, and I freed you from the house of servitude, and I sent before your face Moses, and Aaron, and Miriam.

5 My people, remember, I ask you, what Balak the king of Moab planned, and how Balaam the son of Beor responded to him, from Shittim even to Gilgal, so that you may know the justice of the Lord.

6 What worthy thing might I offer to the Lord, as I bend the knee before God on high? How could I offer holocausts to him, and one year-old calves?

7 Would the Lord be pleased with thousands of rams, or with many thousands of fat he-goats? How could I give up my firstborn because of my evil deed, the fruit of my womb because of the sin of my soul?

8 I will reveal to you, O man, what is good, and what the Lord requires from you, and how to act with judgment, and to love mercy, and to walk carefully with your God.

9 The voice of the Lord cries out to the city, "Listen, you tribes," and who will confirm it? And salvation will be for those who fear your name.

10 Nevertheless, there is a fire in the house of the impious, the treasury of iniquity, and a small measure, filled with wrath.

11 Shall I justify unfaithful balances, and the deceitful weighing of a small bag?

12 By this, her wealthy have been filled with iniquity, and her inhabitants have spoken lies, and their tongue was deceitful in their mouth.

13 And I, therefore, began to strike you with perdition because of your sins.

14 You will consume and not be satisfied, and your humiliation will be in your midst. And you will take hold, and not save, and those whom you will save, I will deliver to the sword.

15 You will sow, and not reap. You will tread the olives, and not be anointed with oil, and crush the grapes, and not drink the wine.

16 For you have kept the precepts of Omri, and all the works of the house of Ahab. And you have walked according their wills, so that I should give you over to perdition and its hissing inhabitants, and you would carry the disgrace of my people.

Micah 7

1 Woe to me, for I have become just like one who gleans the clusters of the vintage in autumn. There is no cluster of grapes to consume; my soul desired figs out of season.

2 The holy ones pass away from the land, and there is no one righteous among men. All wait in ambush for blood; a man hunts his brother to death.

3 The evil of their hands, they call good. The leader is demanding, and the judge is yielding, and the great is speaking the desire of his soul, and they have confused it.

4 Whoever is best among them is like a thorny plant, and he who is righteous is like a thorny hedge. The day of your inspection, your visitation, arrives. Now will be their ruination.

5 Do not be willing to believe a friend. And do not be willing to confide in a commander. From her, who sleeps in your bosom, keep the doors of your mouth closed.

6 For the son acts with contempt for the father, and the daughter rises up against her mother, the daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law, and a man's enemies are those of his own household.

7 But I will look towards the Lord. I will wait for God, my Savior. My God will hear me.

8 You, my enemy, should not rejoice over me because I have fallen. I will rise up, when I sit in darkness. The Lord is my light.

9 I will carry the wrath of the Lord, because I have sinned against him, until he may judge my case and execute judgment for me. He will lead me into the light. I will behold his justice.

10 And my enemy will look, and she will be covered with confusion, she who says to me, "Where is the Lord your God?" My eyes will look upon her. Now she will be trampled under foot like the mud of the streets.

11 The day that your walls will be rebuilt, in that day the law will be far away.

12 In that day also, they will come towards you even from Assur, and even to the fortified cities, and from the fortified cities even to the river, and from sea to sea, and from mountain to mountain.

13 And the land will be in desolation, because of its inhabitants and because of the fruit of their intentions.

14 With your rod, pasture your people, the flock of your inheritance, living alone in the narrow forest, in the midst of Carmel. They will graze in Bashan and Gilead, as in the ancient days.

15 As in the days of your departure from the land of Egypt, I will reveal miracles to him.

16 The nations will look, and they will be confounded at the strength of them all. They will place hand over mouth; their ears will be deaf.

17 They will lick the dust like serpents, and, like the creeping things of the earth, they will be disturbed in their houses. They will dread the Lord our God, and they will fear you.

18 What God is like you, who takes away iniquity and passes over the sin of the remnant of your inheritance? No longer will he send forth his fury, because he is willing to be merciful.

19 He will turn back and have mercy on us. He will put away our iniquities, and he will cast all our sins into the depths of the sea.

20 You will give the truth to Jacob, mercy to Abraham, which you swore to our fathers from the ancient days.

Nahum 1

1 The burden of Nineveh. The book of the vision of Nahum the Elkoshite.

2 God is a rival, and the Lord is avenging. The Lord is avenging, and one who applies wrath. The Lord is avenging with his enemies, and he becomes angry with his adversaries.

3 The Lord is patient and great in strength, and those who are not clean, he makes innocent. The Lord is in a tempest, and his way is a whirlwind, and the clouds are dust at his feet.

4 He is the one who rebukes the sea, and who dries it up, and who leads all the rivers to the desert. Basan has been weakened, and also Carmel, and the flower of Lebanon has languished.

5 The mountains have trembled before him, and the hills have become desolate, and the earth has quaked before his face, both the world and all that dwells in it.

6 Who can stand firm before the face of his indignation? And who can continue against the fury of his wrath? His indignation has broken out like a fire, and the rocks have been dissolved before him.

7 The Lord is good, and a comforter in the day of tribulation, and he knows those who hope in him.

8 And in the flood that passes over, he brings to consummation the end of his place. And darkness shall pursue his adversaries.

9 What are you thinking up against the Lord? He will accomplish the consummation. There shall not rise up a double tribulation.

10 For just as thorns entwine one another, so also, while they are feasting and drinking together, they will be consumed like stubble that is completely dry.

11 Out of you will go forth one who thinks up evil against the Lord, dragging betrayals through his mind.

12 Thus says the Lord: If they had been perfect, and many of them so, yet still they would be pruned, and it will cross through them. I have afflicted you, and I shall afflict you no more.

13 And now I will shatter his rod from your back, and I will break open your bonds.

14 And the Lord will place a commandment over you; nothing more from your name will be sown. From the house of your God, I will order destroyed the graven image and the molten image. I will prepare your grave, because you are not honorable.

15 Behold, over the mountains, the feet of the Evangelizer and the Announcer of peace. Judah, celebrate your festivals and keep your vows. For Belial will never again pass through you; he has completely passed away.

Nahum 2

1 He ascends, who would scatter before your eyes, who would maintain the blockade. Contemplate the way, fortify your back, reinforce virtue greatly.

2 For the Lord has repaid the arrogance of Jacob, just like the arrogance of Israel. For the despoilers have scattered them, and they have corrupted their procreation.

3 The shield of his strong ones is fire, the men of war are in scarlet. The reins of the chariot are fiery in the day of his preparation, and the drivers have been drugged.

4 They have become confused on their journey. The four-horse chariots have collided in the streets. Their appearance is like torches, like lightning dashing around.

5 He will call to mind his strong ones; they will destroy along their journey. They will quickly ascend its walls, and a shelter will be prepared.

6 The gates of the rivers have been opened, and the temple has been pulled down to the ground.

7 And the foot soldier has been led away captive, and her handmaids were driven away, mourning like doves, murmuring in their hearts.

8 And Nineveh, her waters are like a fish pond. Yet truly, they have fled away: "Stand, stand!" But there is no one who will turn back.

9 Despoil the silver, despoil the gold. And there is no end to all the riches of desirable equipment.

10 She has been scattered, and cut, and torn apart. And the heart melts, and the knees buckle, and weakness is in every temperament. And the faces of them all are like a black kettle.

11 Where is the dwelling place of the lions, and the feeding ground of the young lions, to which the lion went, so as to open a way for the young lion, and so that there would be none to make them afraid?

12 The lion seized enough for his young, and killed enough for his lionesses, and he filled his caves with prey, and his den with spoils.

13 Behold, I will come to you, says the Lord of hosts, and I will burn your chariots even to smoke, and the sword will devour your young lions. And I will exterminate your prey from the land, and the voice of your messengers shall no longer be heard.

Nahum 3

1 Woe to the city of blood, filled with all manner of lies and violence. Crime shall not depart from you:

2 the voice of the whip, and the voice of the turning wheels, and of the neighing horse, and the burning chariot, and the horsemen who ride,

3 and of the flashing sword and the shining spear, and of a multitude executed and a grievous ruination. Neither is there an end to the dead bodies, and they will fall down upon their dead bodies.

4 Because of the multitude of fornications of the kept woman, beautiful and pleasing and practicing evil deeds, who sold nations by her fornications, and families by her evil doing:

5 behold, I will come to you, says the Lord of hosts, and I will reveal your shame to your face, and I will show your nakedness to the Gentiles, and your disgrace to kingdoms.

6 And I will cast abominations over you, and I will afflict you with abuse, and I will make an example of you.

7 And this shall be: everyone who sees you, will recoil from you, and he will say: "Nineveh has been devastated." Who will shake his head over you? Where might I seek consolation for you?

8 Are you better than the populous Alexandria, which dwells along the rivers? Waters encircle it: the sea, with its riches. The waters are its walls.

9 Ethiopia and Egypt were its strength, and there is no limit. Africa and Northern Africa have been your helpers.

10 Nevertheless, she has been led away with the transmigration into captivity. Her little ones have been dashed in pieces at the top of every street, and they have cast lots over her celebrities, and all her elite have been fastened together in shackles.

11 Therefore, you also will become inebriated, and you will be despised, and you will seek help from the opposition.

12 All your fortresses will be like fig trees with their green figs. If they are shaken violently, they will fall into the mouth of the one who devours.

13 Behold, women are at the center of your people. The gates of your land will be opened wide for your enemies; fire will devour your bars.

14 Draw in water because of the blockade; build up your fortresses. Go into the clay and tread; work it to make brick.

15 There, fire will devour you. You will perish by the sword; it will devour you like the beetle. Gather together like the beetle. Multiply like the locust.

16 You have made more negotiations than there are stars in the sky. The beetle has spread out and flown away.

17 Your guardians are like locusts, and your little ones are like locusts among locusts, which alight on hedges on a cold day. The sun rose up, and they flew away, and there was no way to know the place where they had been.

18 Your shepherds have become drowsy, king Assur. Your princes will be buried. Your people have remained hidden in the mountains, and there is no one to gather them.

19 Your destruction is not hidden; your wound is grievous. All who have heard of your fame have clenched their hands over you, because over whom has your wickedness not trampled continually?

Habakkuk 1

1 The burden that Habakkuk the prophet saw.

2 How long, O Lord, shall I cry out, and you will not heed? Shall I shout to you while suffering violence, and you will not save?

3 Why have you revealed to me iniquity and hardship, to see plunder and injustice opposite me? And there has been judgment, but the opposition is more powerful.

4 Because of this, the law has been torn apart, and judgment does not persevere to its conclusion. For the impious prevail against the just. Because of this, a perverse judgment is issued.

5 Gaze among the nations, and see. Admire, and be astounded. For a work has been done in your days, which no one will believe when it is told.

6 For behold, I will raise up the Chaldeans, a bitter and swift people, marching across the width of the earth, to possess tabernacles not their own.

7 It is dreadful and terrible. From themselves, judgment and their burden will issue.

8 Their horses are more nimble than leopards and swifter than wolves in the evening; their horsemen will spread out. And then their horsemen will approach from far away; they will fly like the eagle, hurrying to devour.

9 They will all approach towards the prey; their face is like a burning wind. And they will gather captives together like sand.

10 And concerning kings, he will triumph, and sovereign rulers will be his laughingstock, and he will laugh over every fortress, and he will transport a rampart and seize it.

11 Then his spirit will be altered, and he will cross over and fall. Such is his strength from his god.

12 Have you not existed from the beginning, Lord my God, my holy one, and so we shall not die? Lord, you have stationed him for judgment, and you have establish that his strength will be swept away.

13 Your eyes are pure, you do not behold evil, and you cannot look towards iniquity. Why do you look upon the agents of iniquity, and remain silent, while the impious is devouring one who is more just than himself?

14 And you will make men like the fish of the sea and like the creeping things that have no ruler.

15 He lifted up everything with his hook. He drew them in with his dragnet, and gathered them into his netting. Over this, he will rejoice and exult.

16 For this reason, he will offer victims to his dragnet, and he will sacrifice to his netting. For through them, his portion has been made fat, and his meals elite.

17 Because of this, therefore, he expands his dragnet and will not be lenient in continually putting to death the peoples.

Habakkuk 2

1 I will stand firm during my watch, and fix my position over the fortification. And I will observe carefully, to see what might be said to me and what I might respond to my opponent.

2 And the Lord responded to me and said: Write the vision and explain it on tablets, so that he who reads it may run through it.

3 For as yet the vision is far off, and it will appear in the end, and it will not lie. If it expresses any delay, wait for it. For it is arriving and it will arrive, and it will not be hindered.

4 Behold, he who is unbelieving, his soul will not be right within himself; but he who is just shall live in his faith.

5 And in the manner that wine deceives the heavy drinker, so will the arrogant man be deceived, and he will not be honored. He has enlarged his life like hellfire, and himself like death, and he is never fulfilled. And he will gather to himself all nations, and he will amass for himself all peoples.

6 Shall not all these take up a parable against him, and an enigmatic utterance about him? And it will be said, "Woe to him who increases what is not his own." How long, then, will he lay down dense clay against himself?

7 Shall they not suddenly rise up, who would bite you, and be stirred up, who would tear you, so that you will be a prey for them?

8 Because you have despoiled many peoples, all those who are left of the people shall despoil you, because of the blood of men, and the iniquity of the earth, of the city and all who dwell therein.

9 Woe to him who gathers together an evil greed for his house, so that his nest may be exalted, and thinking that he might free himself from the hand of evil.

10 You have devised confusion for your house, you have cut to pieces many peoples, and your soul has sinned.

11 For the stone will cry out from the wall, and the wood that is between the joints of the building will respond.

12 Woe to him who builds a town with blood and prepares a city by iniquity.

13 Are not these things before the Lord of hosts? For the people will labor amid a great fire, and the nations will labor in emptiness, and they will fail.

14 For the earth shall be filled, that they might know the glory of the Lord, like the waters spreading over the sea.

15 Woe to anyone who gives a drink to a friend, releasing a drug and inebriating, so as to look upon their nakedness.

16 You are filled with disgrace in place of glory. So then, drink and fall fast asleep, for the cup of the right hand of the Lord will surround you, and a disgraceful vomit will cover your glory.

17 For the iniquity of Lebanon will cover you, and the devastation of animals which will deter them from the blood of men, and the iniquity of the earth and the city, and of all who dwell therein.

18 Of what benefit is the graven image? For its maker has formed it, a molten and imaginary deception. For its maker has hoped in a figment of his own creation, so as to make a dumb likeness.

19 Woe to him who says to wood, "Awaken," to the silent stone, "Arise." Is it able to teach? Behold, it has been entirely covered with gold and silver; and there is no spirit at all in its inner workings.

20 But the Lord is in his holy temple. May all the earth be silent before his face.

Habakkuk 3

1 A Prayer of Habakkuk the Prophet on Behalf of Those Who Are Ignorant.

2 Lord, I heard what has been said about you, and I was afraid. Lord, your work, in the midst of years, revive it. In the midst of years, you will make it known. When you have become angry, you will remember mercy.

3 God will come from the south, and the Holy One from mount Pharan. His glory has covered the heavens, and the earth is full of his praise.

4 His brightness shall be like the light; horns are in his hands. There, his strength has been hidden.

5 Death will go forth before his face. And the devil shall depart before his feet.

6 He stood, and measured the earth. He looked, and dissolved the Gentiles. And the mountains of ages past have been shattered. The hills of the world became curved by the journeys of his eternity.

7 I saw the tents of Ethiopia for their iniquity; the tent-skins of the land of Midian will be thrown into confusion.

8 Could you have been angry with the rivers, Lord? Or was your fury within the rivers, or your indignation in the sea? He will ascend upon your horses, and your four-horse chariots are salvation.

9 Being stirred up, you will take up your bow, the oaths you have spoken to the tribes. You will split apart the Rivers of the earth.

10 They saw you, and the mountains grieved. The great body of waters crossed over. The abyss uttered its voice. The pinnacle lifted up its hands.

11 The sun and the moon have stood firm in their dwelling place; with the light of your arrows, they shall go forth in the splendor of your flashing spear.

12 With a roar, you will trample the earth. In your fury, you will cause the nations to be stupefied.

13 You have gone forth for the salvation of your people, for salvation with your Christ. You struck the head of the house of the impious. You have laid bare his foundation all the way to the neck.

14 You have cursed his scepters, the head of his warriors, those who approached like a whirlwind so as to scatter me. Their exultation was like one who devours the poor in secret.

15 You made a way in the sea for your horses, in the mud of great waters.

16 I heard, and my stomach became troubled. My lips trembled at the voice. Let decay enter into my bones and gush forth from within me. Then I may rest in the day of tribulation, so that I may ascend to our people well-prepared.

17 For the fig tree will not flower, and there will be no bud on the vines. The labor of the olive tree will be misleading, and the farmland will produce no food. The sheep will be cut off from the sheepfold, and there will be no herd at the manger.

18 But I will rejoice in the Lord; and I will exult in God my Jesus.

19 The Lord God is my strength. And he will set my feet like those of the stag. And he, the victor, will lead me beyond my high places while singing psalms.

Zephaniah 1

1 The word of the Lord that came to Zephaniah the son of Cushi, the son of Gedaliah, the son of Amariah, the son of Hezekiah, in the days of Josiah the son of Amon, king of Judah.

2 While gathering, I will gather together all things from the face of the earth, says the Lord.

3 I will gather man and cattle; I will gather the flying things of the air and the fish of the sea. And the impious will be a catastrophe. And I will disperse men before the face of the earth, says the Lord.

4 And I will extend my hand over Judah and over all the inhabitants of Jerusalem. And I will disperse from this place the remnant of Baal, and the names of the administrators along with the priests,

5 and those who adore the military campaign over the ceiling of the sky, both those who adore and swear by the Lord, and those who swear by Melchom,

6 both those who turn aside from following after the Lord, and those who have not sought the Lord, nor inquired about him.

7 Be silent before the face of the Lord God. For the day of the Lord is near; for the Lord has prepared a victim, he has sanctified those he has called.

8 And this shall be: in the day of the victim of the Lord, I will visit upon the leaders, and upon the sons of the king, and upon all who have been clothed with strange garments.

9 And I will visit upon all who enter arrogantly over the threshold in that day, those who fill the house of the Lord their God with iniquity and deceit.

10 And this shall be in that day, says the Lord: the voice of an outcry from the fish gate, and a howling from the Second, and a great contrition from the hills.

11 Howl, inhabitants of the Pillar. All the people of Canaan have fallen silent. All were ruined who had been wrapped in silver.

12 And this shall be in that time: I will scrutinize Jerusalem with lamps, and I will visit upon the men who have become stuck in the dregs, who say in their hearts, "The Lord will not do good, and he will not do evil."

13 And their strength will be in plundering, and their houses in the desert. And they will build houses and not dwell in them, and they will plant vineyards and not drink their wine.

14 The great day of the Lord is near; it is near and exceedingly swift. The voice of the day of the Lord is bitter; the strong will be tested there.

15 That day is a day of wrath, a day of tribulation and anguish, a day of calamity and misery, a day of darkness and gloom, a day of clouds and whirlwinds,

16 a day of the trumpet and the trumpet blast over fortified cities and over exalted ramparts.

17 And I will trouble men, and they will walk like the blind, because they have sinned against the Lord. And their blood will be poured out like soil, and their bodies like manure.

18 Neither their silver, nor their gold, will be able to free them in the day of the wrath of the Lord. All the land will be devoured in the fire of his zeal, for with all speed, he will bring to consummation every inhabitant of the land.

Zephaniah 2

1 Assemble, be gathered together, O people not worthy to be loved.

2 Until the decree settles accounts, the day like dust is passing away, before which the wrath of the fury of the Lord may overcome you, before which the day of the anger of the Lord may overcome you.

3 Seek the Lord, all you meek of the earth; you who have been working are his judgment. Seek the just, seek the meek. So then, in some way, you might be hidden in the day of the fury of the Lord.

4 For Gaza will be destroyed, and Ashkelon will be in the desert; they will expel Ashdod at midday, and Ekron will be eradicated.

5 Woe to you who inhabit the coast of the sea, you people of perdition. The word of the Lord is over you, Canaan, the land of the Philistines, and I will disperse you, so that not one inhabitant will be left.

6 And the coastline of the sea will be a resting place for shepherds and a fence line for cattle.

7 And it will be the line of him who will remain from the house of Judah. There they will pasture. In the houses of Ashkelon, they will rest towards evening. For the Lord their God will visit them, and he will turn away their captivity.

8 I have heard about the disgrace of Moab and the blasphemies of the sons of Ammon, by which they have defamed my people and have been magnified beyond their borders.

9 Because of this, as I live, says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, Moab will be like Sodom, and the sons of Ammon like Gomorrah, like the dryness of thorns, and piles of salt, and a desert, all the way to eternity. The remnant of my people will despoil them, and the residue of my nation will possess them.

10 This will come upon them for their arrogance, because they have blasphemed and have been magnified over the people of the Lord of hosts.

11 The Lord will be a horror over them, and he will reduce all the gods of the earth. And they will adore him, each man from his own place, all the islands of the Gentiles.

12 Even so, you Ethiopians, you will be executed by my sword.

13 And he will extend his hand over the North, and he will destroy Assur. And he will set the Beautiful in the wilderness, and in an impassable place, and like a desert.

14 And flocks will lie down in its midst, all the beasts of the Gentiles. And the pelican and the hedgehog will stay at its threshold; the voice of the singing bird will be at the window, with the crow above its threshold, for I will diminish her strength.

15 This is the glorious city, dwelling in trust, which said in her heart, "I am and there is no one other than me." How has she become a lair for beasts in the desert? All who pass through her will hiss and wag their hand.

Zephaniah 3

1 Woe to the provocatrix and the redeemed city, the dove.

2 She has not heeded the voice, nor has she accepted discipline. She has not trusted in the Lord; she did not draw near to her God.

3 Her leaders are in her midst like roaring lions. Her judges are evening wolves; they leave nothing for the morning.

4 Her prophets are crazed; men without faith. Her priests have polluted what is holy; they have acted unjustly against the law.

5 The just Lord is in their midst; he will not do iniquity. In the morning, in the morning, he will bring his judgment into the light, and it will not be hidden. But the impious one has not known shame.

6 I have dispersed the nations, and their towers have been torn down. I have made their ways deserts, until there were none who passed through. Their cities have become desolate, with no man remaining, nor any inhabitant.

7 I said: Nevertheless, you will fear me; you will accept discipline. And her dwelling place will not perish, despite all the things about which I have visited her. Yet truly, they arose with the dawn and corrupted all their thoughts.

8 Because of this, expect me, says the Lord, in the day of my resurrection in the future, for my judgment is to gather together the Gentiles, and to collect the kingdoms, and to pour out over them my indignation, all the fury of my anger. For by the fire of my zeal, all the earth will be devoured.

9 For then I will restore to the people a chosen lip, so that all may invoke the name of the Lord and may serve him with one shoulder.

10 From beyond the rivers of Ethiopia, my supplicants, the sons of my diaspora, will carry a gift to me.

11 In that day, you will not be ashamed over all of your inventions, by which you have transgressed against me. For then I will take away from your midst your arrogant boasters, and you will no longer be exalted on my holy mountain.

12 And I will bequeath into your midst a poor and needy people, and they will hope in the name of the Lord.

13 The remnant of Israel will not do iniquity, nor speak lies, and a deceitful tongue will not be found in their mouth. For they will pasture and will recline, and there will be no one to strike them with terror.

14 Give praise, daughter of Zion. Shout joyfully, Israel. Rejoice and exult with all your heart, daughter of Jerusalem.

15 The Lord has taken away your judgment; he has turned aside your foes. The king of Israel, the Lord, is in your midst; you shall no longer fear evil.

16 In that day, it will be said to Jerusalem, "Do not be afraid," and to Zion, "Do not let your hands be weakened."

17 The Lord your God is the strength in your midst; he will save. He will rejoice over you with gladness. In his love, he will be silent. He will exult over you with praise.

18 The triflers who withdrew from the law, I will gather together, because they were from you, so that you may no longer suffer disgrace over them.

19 Behold, I will execute all who have afflicted you in that time, and I will save those who are lame, and I will gather together her who had been cast out. And I will place them in praise and in renown, in all the land where they had been put to shame,

20 in that time, when I will lead to you, and in the time when I will gather for you. For I will deliver you into renown and into praise, among all the peoples of the earth, when I will have converted your captivity before your very eyes, says the Lord.

Haggai 1

1 In the second year of king Darius, in the sixth month, on the first day of the month, the word of the Lord came, by the hand of Haggai the prophet, to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Jesus the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, saying:

2 Thus says the Lord of hosts, saying: This people claims that the time has not yet arrived for building the house of the Lord.

3 But the word of the Lord came by the hand of Haggai the prophet, saying:

4 Is it time for you to dwell in paneled houses, while this house is deserted?

5 And now, thus says the Lord of hosts: Set your hearts upon your ways.

6 You sowed much and have brought in little. You consumed and have not been satisfied. You drank and have not been inebriated. You covered yourselves and have not been warmed. And whoever gathered wages, has put them in a bag with holes.

7 Thus says the Lord of hosts: Set your hearts upon your ways.

8 Ascend to the mountain, bring wood and build the house, and it shall be acceptable to me, and I shall be glorified, says the Lord.

9 You have looked for more, and behold, it became less, and you brought it home, and I blew it away. What is the cause of this, says the Lord of hosts? It is because my house is desolate, yet you have hurried, each one to his own house.

10 Because of this, the heavens over you have been prohibited from giving dew, and the earth has been prohibited from giving her sprouts.

11 And I called a drought over the land, and over the mountains, and over the wheat, and over the wine, and over the oil, and whatever the soil would bring forth, and over men, and over beasts of burden, and over all the labor of hands.

12 And Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jesus the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and all the remnant of the people heeded the voice of the Lord their God, and the words of Haggai the prophet, just as the Lord their God sent him to them. And the people were fearful before the face of the Lord.

13 And Haggai, a messenger of the Lord among messengers of the Lord, spoke to the people, saying: the Lord says, "I am with you."

14 And the Lord stirred the spirit of Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Jesus the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and the spirit of the remainder of all the people. And they entered and performed work in the house of the Lord of hosts their God,

Haggai 2

1 on the twenty-fourth day of the month, in the sixth month, in the second year of king Darius.

2 And in the seventh month, on the twenty-first of the month, the word of the Lord came, by the hand of Haggai the prophet, saying:

3 Speak to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, the governor of Judah, and to Jesus the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remainder of the people, saying:

4 Who is left among you, who saw this house in its first glory? And how do you see it now? Is it not, in comparison to that, as nothing in your eyes?

5 And now be strengthened, Zerubbabel, says the Lord. And be strengthened, Jesus the son of Jehozadak, the high priest. And be strengthened, all people of the land, says the Lord of hosts. For I am with you, says the Lord of hosts.

6 And act according to the word that I planted with you when you departed from the land of Egypt. And my Spirit will be in your midst. Do not be afraid.

7 For thus says the Lord of hosts: There is yet one brief time, and I will move heaven and earth, and the sea and the dry land.

8 And I will move all nations. And the Desired of all nations will arrive. And I will fill this house with glory, says the Lord of hosts.

9 Mine is the silver, and mine is the gold, says the Lord of hosts.

10 Great shall be the glory of this house, the last more than the first, says the Lord of hosts. And in this place, I will bestow peace, says the Lord of hosts.

11 On the twenty-fourth of the ninth month, in the second year of king Darius, the word of the Lord came to Haggai the prophet, saying:

12 Thus says the Lord of hosts: the priests question the law, saying:

13 If a man will have carried sanctified flesh in the pocket of his garment, and the top of it touches his bread, or appetizer, or wine, or oil, or any food, shall it be sanctified? But the priests responded by saying, "No."

14 And Haggai said, "If the polluted in soul will have touched any of all these things, shall it be contaminated?" And the priests responded and said, "It shall be contaminated."

15 And Haggai answered and he said: Such is this people, and such is this nation before my face, says the Lord, and such is all the work of their hands. And so all that they have offered there has been contaminated.

16 And now, consider in your hearts, from this day and beyond, before stone may be placed upon stone in the temple of the Lord:

17 when you approached a pile of twenty measures, and they became ten, and you entered to the press, to press out fifty bottles, and they became twenty,

18 how I struck you with a burning wind, and a mildew, and a hailstorm, all the works of your hand, yet there was no one among you who returned to me, says the Lord.

19 Set your hearts from this day and into the future, from the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month, from the day that the foundations of the temple of the Lord have been uttered, and place it upon your heart.

20 Has the seed been germinated yet? And has the vine, and the fig tree, and the pomegranate, and the olive tree still not flourished? From this day on, I will bless you.

21 And the word of the Lord came a second time to Haggai, on the twenty-fourth of the month, saying:

22 Speak to Zerubbabel the governor of Judah, saying: I will move both heaven and earth.

23 And I will overturn the throne of kingdoms, and I will crush the strength of the kingdom of the Gentiles. And I will overturn the four-horse chariot, and its rider; and the horses and their riders shall be brought down, a man by the sword of his brother.

24 In that day, says the Lord of hosts, I will take you, Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, my servant, says the Lord, and will set you like a seal, for I have chosen you, says the Lord of hosts.

Zechariah 1

1 In the eighth month, in the second year of king Darius, the word of the Lord came to Zechariah the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, the prophet, saying:

2 The Lord has become angry over the resentful anger of your fathers.

3 And you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord of hosts: Turn to me, says the Lord of hosts, and I will turn to you, says the Lord of hosts.

4 Do not be like your fathers, to whom the former prophets cried out, saying: Thus says the Lord of hosts: Turn from your evil ways and from your wicked thoughts. But they did not heed, and neither did they pay attention to me, says the Lord.

5 Your fathers, where are they? And will the prophets live unceasingly?

6 Yet truly my words and my lawfulness, which I entrusted to my servants the prophets, were indeed comprehended by your fathers, and so they were converted, and they said: Just as the Lord of hosts decided to do to us, according to our ways and according to our inventions, so has he done to us.

7 On the twenty-fourth day of the eleventh month, which is called Shevat, in the second year of Darius, the word of the Lord came to Zechariah the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, the prophet, saying:

8 I saw by night, and behold, a man riding on a red horse, and he stood among the myrtle trees, which were in the chasm. And behind him were horses: red, speckled, and white.

9 And I said, "What are these, my lord?" And the angel, who was speaking with me, said to me, "I will reveal to you what these are."

10 And the man that stood among the myrtle trees answered and said, "These are they, whom the Lord has sent in order to walk through the earth."

11 And those who stood among the myrtle trees answered the angel of the Lord, and they said, "We have walked through the earth, and behold, all the earth is inhabited and is at rest."

12 And the angel of the Lord answered and said, "Lord of hosts, how long will you not have mercy on Jerusalem and on the cities of Judah, with which you have been angry? This is now the seventieth year."

13 And the Lord answered the angel, who had been speaking with me, good words, consoling words.

14 And the angel, who was speaking with me, said to me: Cry out, saying: Thus says the Lord of hosts: I have been zealous for Jerusalem and for Zion with a great zeal.

15 And, with a great anger, I am angry with the wealthy nations. Though I had been angry a little, truly they advanced further in evil.

16 Because of this, thus says the Lord: I will be turned back, towards Jerusalem, with mercies; and my house will be built upon this, says the Lord of hosts. And the building line will be extended over Jerusalem.

17 Until then, cry out saying: Thus says the Lord of hosts: Until then, my cities will flow with good things, and, until then, the Lord will comfort Zion, and, until then, he will single out Jerusalem.

18 And I lifted up my eyes, and I saw. And behold: four horns.

19 And I said to the angel, who was speaking with me, "What are these?" And he said to me, "These are the horns that have winnowed Judah and Israel and Jerusalem."

20 And the Lord showed me four workmen.

21 And I said, "What have these come to do?" He spoke, saying, "These are the horns that have winnowed Judah, through every single man, and none of them lifted up his head. And these have come to frighten them away, so as to cast down the horns of the Gentiles, which have lifted up a horn over the land of Judah, so as to scatter it."

Zechariah 2

1 And I lifted up my eyes, and I saw, and behold, a man, and in his hand was a measuring line.

2 And I said, "Where are you going?" And he said to me, "To measure Jerusalem, so that I may see how great its width and how great its length may be."

3 And behold, the angel, who had been speaking with me, departed, and another angel went out to meet him.

4 And he said to him: Hurry, speak to this young man, saying: Jerusalem will be inhabited without walls, because of the multitude of men and beasts of burden in its midst.

5 And I will be to it, says the Lord, a wall of fire all around. And in glory, I will be in its midst.

6 O, O flee from the land of the North, says the Lord, for I have scattered you into the four winds of heaven, says the Lord.

7 O Zion, flee, you who dwell with the daughter of Babylon.

8 For thus says the Lord of hosts: After the glory, he has sent me to the Gentiles, which have despoiled you. For he who touches you, touches the pupil of my eye.

9 For behold, I lift up my hand over them, and they will be a prey to those who had served them. And you will know that the Lord of hosts has sent me.

10 Sing praise and rejoice, daughter of Zion. For behold, I approach, and I will dwell in your midst, says the Lord.

11 And many nations will be joined to the Lord in that day, and they will be my people, and I will dwell in your midst. And you will know that the Lord of hosts has sent me to you.

12 And the Lord will possess his portion, Judah, in the sanctified land, and still he will single out Jerusalem.

13 Let all flesh be silent before the face of the Lord: for he has arisen from his holy dwelling place.

Zechariah 3

1 And the Lord revealed to me: Jesus the high priest, standing in the sight of the angel of the Lord. And Satan stood before his right hand, so as to be his adversary.

2 And the Lord said to Satan, "May the Lord rebuke you, Satan! And may the Lord, who chose Jerusalem, rebuke you! Are you not a firebrand plucked from the fire?"

3 And Jesus was clothed with filthy garments. And he stood before the face of an angel.

4 He answered and spoke to those who stood before him, saying, "Take away the filthy garments from him." And he said to him, "Behold, I have taken away from you your iniquity, and I have clothed you with a change of clothing."

5 And he said, "Place a clean diadem on his head." And they placed a clean diadem on his head, and they clothed him with garments. And the angel of the Lord remained standing.

6 And the angel of the Lord contested with Jesus, saying:

7 Thus says the Lord of hosts: If you will walk in my ways and keep my charge, you likewise will judge my house and will keep my courts, and I will give you some of those who now attend here to walk with you.

8 Listen, Jesus the high priest, you and your friends, who dwell before you, who have been portending to men. For behold, I will lead my servant to the East.

9 For behold, the stone that I have bestowed before Jesus. Upon one stone, there are seven eyes. Behold, I will carve its engraving, says the Lord of hosts. And I will take away the iniquity of that land in one day.

10 On that day, says the Lord of hosts, every man will call his friend from under the vine and from under the fig tree.

Zechariah 4

1 And the angel who had been speaking with me returned, and he awakened me, like a man who is awakened from his sleep.

2 And he said to me, "What do you see?" And I said, "I looked, and behold, a candlestick entirely in gold, and its lamp was at its top, and seven oil lamps of it were upon it, and there were seven funnels for the oil lamps that were at its top.

3 And there were two olive trees upon it: one to the right of the lamp, and one to its left."

4 And I answered and spoke to the angel who was speaking with me, saying, "What are these, my lord?"

5 And the angel who was speaking with me answered, and he said to me, "Do you not know what these are?" And I said, "No, my lord."

6 And he answered and spoke to me, saying: This is the word of the Lord to Zerubbabel, saying: Not by an army, nor by might, but in my spirit, says the Lord of hosts.

7 What are you, great mountain, in the sight of Zerubbabel? You are among the plains. And he will lead out the primary stone, and he will give equal grace to its grace.

8 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

9 The hand of Zerubbabel has founded this house, and his hands will complete it. And you will know that the Lord of hosts has sent me to you.

10 For who has despised the little days? And they will rejoice and will see the silver and lead stone in the hand of Zerubbabel. These are the seven eyes of the Lord, which roam quickly through all the earth.

11 And I responded and said to him, "What are these two olive trees to the right of the candlestick, and to its left?"

12 And I responded a second time and said to him, "What are the two olive branches, which are next to the two golden ridges, in which are the pouring spouts of gold?"

13 And he spoke to me, saying, "Do you not know what these are?" And I said, "No, my lord."

14 And he said, "These are the two sons of oil, who attend before the Sovereign of all the earth."

Zechariah 5

1 And I turned and lifted up my eyes. And I saw, and behold, a book flying.

2 And he said to me, "What do you see?" And I said, "I see a book flying. Its length is twenty cubits, and its width is ten cubits."

3 And he said to me, "This is the curse that goes forth over the face of the whole earth. For every thief will be judged, just as it has been written there, and everyone who swears by this, will be judged in like manner."

4 I will bring it forth, says the Lord of hosts, and it will approach to the house of the thief, and to the house of him who swears falsely by my name, and it will remain in the midst of his house and will consume it, with its wood and its stones.

5 And the angel had departed, who was speaking with me. And he said to me, "Lift up your eyes, and see what this is, that goes forth."

6 And I said, "What, then, is it?" And he said, "This is a container going forth." And he said, "This is their eye in all the earth."

7 And behold, a talent of lead was being carried; and behold, one woman sitting in the middle of the container.

8 And he said, "This is impiety." And he cast her into the middle of the container, and he sent the weight of lead into its mouth.

9 And I lifted up my eyes and I saw. And behold, two women were departing, and a spirit was in their wings, and they had wings like the wings of a kite, and they lifted up the container between earth and heaven.

10 And I said to the angel who was speaking with me, "Where are they taking the container?"

11 And he said to me, "To a house that may be built for it in the land of Shinar, and so that it may be established and set there upon its own base."

Zechariah 6

1 And I turned, and I lifted up my eyes and I saw. And behold, four four-horse chariots went out from the middle of two mountains. And the mountains were mountains of brass.

2 In the first chariot were red horses, and in the second chariot were black horses,

3 and in the third chariot were white horses, and in the fourth chariot were speckled horses, and they were strong.

4 And I responded and said to the angel who was speaking with me, "What are these, my lord?"

5 And the angel answered and said to me, "These are the four winds of heaven, which go forth to stand in the presence of the Sovereign of all the earth."

6 The one with the black horses was departing into the land of the North, and the white went forth after them, and the speckled went forth towards the land of the South.

7 Yet those who were the most strong, went out, and sought to go and to roam quickly through all the earth. And he said, "Go, walk throughout the earth." And they walked throughout the earth.

8 And he called me and spoke with me, saying, "Behold, those who go forth to the land of the North, have quieted my spirit in the land of the North."

9 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

10 From those of the captivity, take from Heldai, and from Tobijah, and from Jedaiah. You will approach in that day, and you will go into the house of Josiah, the son of Zephaniah, who came from Babylon.

11 And you will take gold and silver; and you will make crowns, and you will set them on the head of Jesus the son of Jehozadak, the high priest.

12 And you will speak to him, saying: Thus says the Lord of hosts, saying: Behold, a man; the Rising is his name. And under him, he will rise up, and he will build a temple to the Lord.

13 And he will raise a temple to the Lord. And he will carry the glory, and he will sit and rule upon his throne. And he will be a priest upon his throne, and a counsel of peace will be between the two of them.

14 And the crowns will be to Heldai, and Tobijah, and Jedaiah, as well as to Hem, the son of Zephaniah, as a memorial in the temple of the Lord.

15 And those who are far away, will approach, and will build in the temple of the Lord. And you will know that the Lord of hosts sent me to you. Yet this shall be only if, when hearing, you will have heeded the voice of the Lord your God.

Zechariah 7

1 And it happened, in the fourth year of king Darius, that the word of the Lord came to Zechariah, on the fourth day of the ninth month, which is Kislev.

2 And Sharezer and Regemmelech, and the men who were with them, sent to the house of God, to entreat the face of the Lord,

3 to speak to the priests of the house of the Lord of hosts and to the prophets, saying: "Must there be weeping with me in the fifth month, and must I sanctify myself, as I have now done for many years?"

4 And the word of the Lord of hosts came to me, saying:

5 Speak to all the people of the land, and to the priests, saying: Although you may have fasted and mourned in the fifth and the seventh month for these seventy years, did you indeed keep a fast unto me?

6 And when you did eat and drink, did you not eat for yourselves, and drink only for yourselves?

7 Are not these the words that the Lord has spoken by the hand of the former prophets, when Jerusalem was still inhabited, so that it would prosper, itself and the cities around it, and those inhabitants towards the South and in the plains?

8 And the word of the Lord came to Zechariah, saying:

9 Thus says the Lord of hosts, saying: Judge with true judgment, and act with mercy and compassion, each and every one with his brother.

10 And do not find fault with the widow, and the orphan, and the newcomer, and the poor. And let not a man consider evil in his heart towards his brother.

11 But they were not willing to pay attention, and they turned aside their shoulder to depart, and they pressed upon their ears, so that they would not hear.

12 And they set their heart like the hardest stone, so that they would not hear the law and the words that the Lord of hosts has sent with his Spirit by the hand of the former prophets. And so a great indignation came from Lord of hosts.

13 And it happened, just as he had spoken, and they did not pay attention. So then, they shall cry out, and I will not heed, says the Lord of hosts.

14 And I dispersed them throughout all the kingdoms that they did not know. And the land was left desolate behind them, so that no one was passing through or returning. And they made the desirable land into a deserted place.

Zechariah 8

1 And the word of the Lord of hosts came, saying:

2 Thus says the Lord of hosts: I have been zealous for Zion with a great zeal, and with a great indignation have I been zealous for her.

3 Thus says the Lord of hosts: I have been turned back towards Zion, and I will dwell in the midst of Jerusalem. And Jerusalem will be called: "The City of Truth," and "The Mountain of the Lord of Hosts, the Sanctified Mountain."

4 Thus says the Lord of hosts: Then elderly men and elderly women will dwell in the streets of Jerusalem, and every man will be with his walking stick in his hand, because of the multitude of days.

5 And the streets of the city will be filled with toddlers and children, playing in its streets.

6 Thus says the Lord of hosts: If it seems difficult in the eyes of the remnant of this people in those days, could it indeed be difficult in my eyes, says the Lord of hosts?

7 Thus says the Lord of hosts: Behold, I will save my people from the land of the East, and from the land of the setting of the sun.

8 And I will lead them, and they will dwell in the midst of Jerusalem. And they will be my people, and I will be their God, in truth and in justice.

9 Thus says the Lord of hosts: Let your hands be strengthened, you who, in those days, are listening to these words by the mouth of the prophets, in the day that the house of the Lord of hosts has been founded, so that the temple may be built.

10 Indeed, before those days, there was no pay for men, nor was there pay for beasts of burden, and neither was there peace for those entering, nor for those exiting, because of the tribulation. And I had dismissed all men, each one against his neighbor.

11 But now, I will not act towards the remnant of this people according to the former days, says the Lord of hosts.

12 But there will be a seed of peace: the vine will give her fruit, and the earth will give her seedlings, and the heavens will give their dew. And I will cause the remnant of this people to possess all these things.

13 And this shall be: just as you were a curse among the Gentiles, O house of Judah and house of Israel, so will I save you, and you will be a blessing. Do not be afraid. Let your hands be strengthened.

14 For thus says the Lord of hosts: Just as I intended to afflict you, when your fathers had provoked me to wrath, says the Lord,

15 and I did not show mercy, so have I turned back, thinking in these days to do good to the house of Judah and to Jerusalem. Do not be afraid.

16 Therefore, these are the words that you shall do: Speak the truth, each one to his neighbor. With truth and a judgment of peace, judge at your gates.

17 And let not anyone think up evil against his friend in your hearts. And do not choose to swear falsely. For all these are things that I hate, says the Lord.

18 And the word of the Lord of hosts came to me, saying:

19 Thus says the Lord of hosts: The fast of the fourth, and the fast of the fifth, and the fast of the seventh, and the fast of the tenth will be for the house of Judah in joy and gladness and with bright solemnities. So then, love truth and peace.

20 Thus says the Lord of hosts, then the people may arrive and dwell in many cities,

21 and the inhabitants may hurry, one saying to another: "Let us go and entreat the face of the Lord, and let us seek the Lord of hosts. I will go also."

22 And many peoples and strong nations will approach, seeking the Lord of hosts in Jerusalem, and to entreat the face of the Lord.

23 Thus says the Lord of hosts: In those days, then, ten men from every language of the Gentiles will grasp and cling to the hem of one man of Judea, saying: "We will go with you. For we have heard that God is with you."

Zechariah 9

1 The burden of the word of the Lord in the land of Hadrach and its respite in Damascus. For the eye of man and of all the tribes of Israel is of the Lord.

2 Hamath also is at its limits, and Tyre and Sidon. For, of course, they have assumed themselves to be exceedingly wise.

3 And Tyre has built herself a fortress, and she has piled together silver, as if it were soil, and gold, as if it were the mud of the streets.

4 Behold, the Lord will possess her, and he will strike her strength in the sea, and she will be devoured by fire.

5 Ashkelon will see and be afraid. Both Gaza and he will be very sorrowful, as well as Ekron, because her hope has been confounded. And the king will pass away from Gaza, and Ashkelon will not be inhabited.

6 And the divider will sit in Ashdod, and I will scatter the arrogance of the Philistines.

7 And I will take away his blood from his mouth, and his abominations from between his teeth, and yet he will be left for our God, and he will be like a governor in Judah, and Ekron will be like a Jebusite.

8 And I will encircle my house with those who serve me in war, going and returning, and the exactor will no longer pass over them. For now I have seen with my eyes.

9 Rejoice well, daughter of Zion, shout for joy, daughter of Jerusalem. Behold, your King will come to you: the Just One, the Savior. He is poor and riding upon a donkey, and upon a colt, the son of a donkey.

10 And I will scatter the four-horse chariot out of Ephraim and the horse from Jerusalem, and the bow of war will be destroyed. And he will speak peace to the Gentiles, and his power will be from sea to sea, and from the rivers even to the end of the earth.

11 You, likewise, by the blood of your testimony, have sent forth your prisoners from the pit, in which there is no water.

12 Turn back to the fortress, prisoners of hope. Today, I also announce that I will repay you double,

13 because I have stretched out Judah for myself, like a bow; I have filled Ephraim. And I will raise up your sons, Zion, above your sons, Greece. And I will set you as the sword of the strength.

14 And the Lord God will be seen over them, and his arrow will go forth like lightning. And the Lord God will sound the trumpet, and he will go forth into the whirlwind of the South.

15 The Lord of hosts will protect them. And they will devour and subdue with the stones of the sling. And, when drinking, they will become inebriated, as if with wine, and they will be filled like bowls and like the horns of the altar.

16 And in that day, the Lord their God will save them as the flock of his people. For holy stones will be lifted up over his land.

17 For what is his goodness and what is his beauty, other than grain among the elect and wine springing forth virgins?

Zechariah 10

1 Petition before the Lord for rain in the latter time, and the Lord will produce snows and will give showers of rain to them, to each blade in the field.

2 For the images have been speaking what is useless, and the diviners have seen a lie, and the dreamers have been speaking false hope: they have comforted in vain. For this reason, they have been led away like a flock; they will be afflicted, because they have no shepherd.

3 My fury has been kindled over the shepherds, and I will visit upon the he-goats. For the Lord of hosts has visited his flock, the house of Judah, and he has set them like the horse of his glory in the war.

4 From him will go forth the angle, from him the wooden peg, from him the bow of battle, from him every exactor at the same time.

5 And they will be like the strong, trampling the mud of the ways in battle. And they will fight, for the Lord is with them. And the riders of the horses will be confounded.

6 And I will strengthen the house of Judah, and I will save the house of Joseph, and I will convert them, because I will have mercy on them. And they will be as they were when I had not cast them away. For I am the Lord their God, and I will hear them.

7 And they will be like the strong of Ephraim, and their heart will rejoice as if by wine, and their sons will see and will rejoice, and their heart will exult in the Lord.

8 I will whistle for them, and I will gather them together, because I have redeemed them. And I will multiply them, as they had been multiplied before.

9 And I will sow them among the peoples, and from far away they will remember me. And they will live with their sons, and they will return.

10 And I will lead them back from the land of Egypt, and I will gather them from among the Assyrians, and I will lead them to the land of Gilead and Lebanon, and no place will be left that has not been found by them.

11 And he will pass over the narrow passage of the sea, and he will strike the waves of the sea, and all the depths of the river will be confounded, and the arrogance of Assyria will be brought low, and the scepter of Egypt will withdraw.

12 I will strengthen them in the Lord, and they will walk in his name, says the Lord.

Zechariah 11

1 Open your gates, Lebanon, and let fire consume your cedars.

2 Howl, you fir tree, for the cedar has fallen, because the magnificent have been devastated. Howl, you oaks of Bashan, because the secure forest passage has been cut down.

3 The voice of the howling of the shepherds: for their magnificence has been devastated. The voice of the roaring of the lions: because the arrogance of the Jordan has been devastated.

4 Thus says the Lord my God: Feed the flock of the slaughter,

5 which those who possessed them cut down, and they did not feel sorrow, and they sold them, saying: "Blessed be the Lord; we have become wealthy. Even their shepherds did not spare them."

6 And so, I will no longer spare the inhabitants upon the earth, says the Lord. Behold, I will deliver men, each one into the hand of his neighbor and into the hand of his king. And they will cut down the land, and I will not rescue it from their hand.

7 And I will pasture the flock of the slaughter, because of this, O poor of the flock. And I took to myself two staffs: the one I called Handsome, and the other I called Rope, and I pastured the flock.

8 And I cut down three shepherds in one month. And my soul became contracted concerning them, just as their soul also varied concerning me.

9 And I said: I will not pasture you. Whatever dies, let it die. And whatever is cut down, let it be cut down. And let the rest of them devour, each one the flesh of his neighbor.

10 And I took my staff, which was called Handsome, and I tore it apart, so as to invalidate my pact, which I had struck with all of the people.

11 And it became invalid in that day. And so they understood, just like the poor of the flock who stay close to me, that this is the word of the Lord.

12 And I said to them: If it is good in your eyes, bring me my wages. And if not, remain still. And they weighed for my wages thirty silver coins.

13 And the Lord said to me: Cast it towards the statuary, the handsome price at which I have been valued by them. And I took the thirty silver coins, and I cast them into the house of the Lord, towards the statuary.

14 And I cut short my second staff, which was called Rope, so that I might dissolve the brotherhood between Judah and Israel.

15 And the Lord said to me: Still they are to you the equipment of a foolish shepherd.

16 For behold, I will raise up a shepherd in the land, who will not visit what is forsaken, nor seek what is scattered, nor heal what is broken, nor nourish what remains standing, and he will consume the flesh of the fatted ones and break their hoofs.

17 O shepherd and idol, abandoning the flock, with a sword upon his arm and over his right eye: his arm will be withered by drought, and his right eye will be obscured by darkness.

Zechariah 12

1 The burden of the word of the Lord upon Israel. The Lord, stretching forth the heavens and founding the earth and forming the spirit of man within him, says:

2 Behold, I will set Jerusalem as a lintel of the effects of drunkenness to all the surrounding peoples, yet even Judah will be in the blockade against Jerusalem.

3 And this shall be: In that day, I will set Jerusalem as a burdensome stone to every people. All who will lift it up will be torn to pieces. And all the kingdoms of the earth will be gathered together against her.

4 In that day, says the Lord, I will strike every horse with stupor and his rider with madness. And I will open my eyes upon the house of Judah, and I will strike every horse of the people with blindness.

5 And the governors of Judah will say in their heart, "Let the inhabitants of Jerusalem be strengthened for me, in the Lord of hosts, their God."

6 In that day, I will set the governors of Judah like a flaming furnace among wood, and like a flaming torch among hay. And they will devour, to the right and to the left, all the surrounding peoples. And Jerusalem will be inhabited again, in her own place, in Jerusalem.

7 And the Lord will save the tabernacles of Judah, just as in the beginning, so that the house of David and the glory of the inhabitants of Jerusalem may not glorify themselves boastfully against Judah.

8 In that day, the Lord will protect the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and even he who will have offended from them, in that day, will be like David, and the house of David will be like that of God, just like an angel of the Lord in their sight.

9 And this shall be in that day: I will seek to crush all the Gentiles that come against Jerusalem.

10 And I will pour out upon the house of David and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the spirit of grace and of prayers. And they will look upon me, whom they have pierced, and they will mourn for him as one mourns for an only son, and they will feel sorrow over him, as one would be sorrowful at the death of a firstborn.

11 In that day, there will be a great lamentation in Jerusalem, like the lamentation of Hadadrimmon in the plain of Megiddo.

12 And the earth will mourn: families and families separately; the families of the house of David separately, and their women separately;

13 the families of the house of Nathan separately, and their women separately; the families of the house of Levi separately, and their women separately; the families of Shimei separately, and their women separately;

14 all the rest of the families, families and families separately, and their women separately.

Zechariah 13

1 In that day, there will be a fountain open to the house of David and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, for the washing of the transgressor and of the defiled woman.

2 And this shall be in that day, says the Lord of hosts: I will disperse the names of the idols from the earth, and they will not be remembered any longer. And I will take away the false prophets and the unclean spirit from the earth.

3 And this shall be: when any devotee will continue to prophesy, his father and his mother, who conceived him, will say to him, "You shall not live, because you have been speaking a lie in the name of the Lord." And his father and his mother, his own parents, will pierce him, when he will prophesy.

4 And this shall be: In that day, the prophets will be confounded, each one by his own vision, when he will prophesy. Neither will they be covered with a garment of sackcloth in order to deceive.

5 But he will say, "I am not a prophet; I am a man of agriculture. For Adam has been my example from my youth."

6 And they will say to him, "What are these wounds in the middle of your hands?" And he will say, "I was wounded with these in the house of those who love me."

7 Awake, O spear, against my shepherd and against the man that clings to me, says the Lord of hosts. Strike the shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered. And I will turn my hand to the little ones.

8 And there will be in all the earth, says the Lord, two parts in it will be scattered and will pass away, and the third part will be left behind.

9 And I will lead the third part through fire, and I will burn them just as silver is burned, and I will test them just as gold is tested. They will call on my name, and I will heed them. I will say, "You are my people." And they will say, "The Lord is my God."

Zechariah 14

1 Behold, the days of the Lord will arrive, and your spoils will be divided in your midst.

2 And I will gather all the Gentiles in battle against Jerusalem, and the city will be captured, and the houses will be ravaged, and the women will be violated. And the central part of the city will go forth into captivity, and the remainder of the people will not be taken away from the city.

3 Then the Lord will go forth, and he will fight against those Gentiles, just as when he fought in the day of conflict.

4 And his feet will stand firm, in that day, upon the Mount of Olives, which is opposite Jerusalem towards the East. And the mount of Olives will be divided down its center part, towards the East and towards the West, with a very great rupture, and the center of the mountain will be separated towards the North, and its center towards the Meridian.

5 And you will flee to the valley of those mountains, because the valley of the mountains will be joined all the way to the next. And you will flee, just as you fled from the face of the earthquake in the days of Uzziah king of Judah. And the Lord my God will arrive, and all the saints with him.

6 And this shall be in that day: there will not be light, only cold and frost.

7 And there will be one day, which is known to the Lord, not day and not night. And in the time of the evening, there will be light.

8 And this shall be in that day: the living waters will go out from Jerusalem, half of them towards the East sea, and half of them towards the furthest sea. They will be in summer and in winter.

9 And the Lord will be King over all the earth. In that day, there will be one Lord, and his name will be one.

10 And all the land will return even to the desert, from the hill of Rimmon to the South of Jerusalem. And she will be exalted, and she will dwell in her own place, from the gate of Benjamin even to the place of the former gate, and even to the gate of the corners, and from the tower of Hananel even to the pressing room of the king.

11 And they will dwell in it, and there will be no further anathema, but Jerusalem shall sit securely.

12 And this will be the plague by which the Lord will strike all the Gentiles that have fought against Jerusalem. The flesh of each one will waste away while they are standing on their feet, and their eyes will be consumed in their sockets, and their tongue will be consumed in their mouth.

13 In that day, there will be a great tumult from the Lord among them. And a man will take the hand of his neighbor, and his hand will be clasped upon the hand of his neighbor.

14 And even Judah will fight against Jerusalem. And the riches of all the Gentiles will be gathered together around them: gold, and silver, and more than enough garments.

15 And, like the ruin of the horse, and the mule, and the camel, and the donkey, and all the beasts of burden, which will have been in those encampments, so will be this ruination.

16 And all those who will be the remnant of all the Gentiles that came against Jerusalem, will go up, from year to year, to adore the King, the Lord of hosts, and to celebrate the feast of tabernacles.

17 And this shall be: whoever will not go up, from the families of the earth to Jerusalem, so as to adore the King, the Lord of hosts, there will be no showers upon them.

18 But if even the family of Egypt will go not up, nor approach, neither will it be upon them, but there will be ruin, by which the Lord will strike all the Gentiles, who will not go up to celebrate the feast of tabernacles.

19 This will be the sin of Egypt, and this will be the sin of all the Gentiles, who will not go up to celebrate the feast of tabernacles.

20 In that day, that which is on the bridle of the horse will be holy to the Lord. And even the cooking pots in the house of the Lord will be like holy vessels before the altar.

21 And every cooking pot in Jerusalem and Judah will be sanctified to the Lord of hosts. And all those who make sacrifices will come and take from them, and will cook with them. And the merchant will no longer be in the house of the Lord of hosts, in that day.

Malachi 1

1 The burden of the word of the Lord to Israel by the hand of Malachi.

2 I have loved you, says the Lord, and you have said, "In what way have you loved us?" Was not Esau brother to Jacob, says the Lord? And have I not loved Jacob,

3 but held hatred for Esau? And I have set his mountains in solitude, and his inheritance with the serpents of the desert.

4 But if Idumea will say, "We have been destroyed, but when we return, we will build up what has been destroyed," thus says the Lord of hosts: They will build up, and I will destroy. And they will be called "The limits of impiety," and, "The people with whom the Lord has been angry, even to eternity."

5 And your eyes will see. And you will say, "May the Lord be magnified beyond the limits of Israel."

6 The son honors the father, and the servant his master. If, therefore, I am Father, where is my honor? And if I am Master, where is my fear? says the Lord of hosts to you, O priests, who despise my name. And you have said, "In what way, have we despised your name?"

7 You offer polluted bread upon my altar, and you say, "In what way, have we polluted you?" In that you say, "The table of the Lord has been despised."

8 If you offer the blind for sacrifice, is this not evil? And if you offer the lame and the sick, is this not evil? Offer it to your leader, if he will be pleased with it, or if he will accept your face, says the Lord of hosts.

9 And now, beseech the face of God, so that he may have mercy on you (for by your hand has this been done) if, in any way, he might accept your faces, says the Lord of hosts.

10 Who is there among you that would close the doors and enflame my altar without pay? I have no favor in you, says the Lord of hosts. And I will not accept a gift from your hand.

11 For, from the rising of the sun even to its setting, my name is great among the Gentiles, and in every place, a clean oblation is being sacrificed and offered to my name. For my name is great among the Gentiles, says the Lord of hosts.

12 And you have polluted it, in that you say, "The table of the Lord has been contaminated; and that which is placed upon it is contemptible, compared with the fire that devours it."

13 And you have said, "Behold our labor," and you have exhaled it away, says the Lord of hosts. And you brought in by plunder the lame, and the sick, and brought it in as a gift. How can I receive this from your hand, says the Lord?

14 Cursed is the deceitful, who holds in his flock a male, and, when making a vow, offers in sacrifice that which is feeble to the Lord. For I am a great King, says the Lord of hosts, and my name is dreadful among the Gentiles.

Malachi 2

1 And now, O priests, this command is to you.

2 If you will refuse to listen, and if you will refuse to take it to heart, so as to give glory to my name, says the Lord of hosts, I will send destitution upon you, and I will curse your blessings; yes, I will curse them. For you have not taken it to heart.

3 Behold, I will cast forth an arm to you, and I will scatter across your face the dung of your solemnities, and it will take you to itself.

4 And you will know that I sent you this commandment, so that my covenant might be with Levi, says the Lord of hosts.

5 My covenant was with him for life and peace. And I gave him fear, and he feared me, and he was afraid before the face of my name.

6 The law of truth was in his mouth, and iniquity was not found on his lips. He walked with me in peace and integrity, and he turned away many from iniquity.

7 For the lips of the priests will keep knowledge, and they will request the law from his mouth, because he is an angel of the Lord of hosts.

8 But you have withdrawn from the way, and you have scandalized very many in the law. You have nullified the covenant of Levi, says the Lord of hosts.

9 Because of this, I also have made you contemptible and debased to all the people, just as you have not served my ways, and you have accepted a face in the law.

10 Is there not one Father of us all? Did not one God create us? Why, then, does each one of us despise his brother, violating the covenant of our fathers?

11 Judah has transgressed, and abomination has been committed in Israel and in Jerusalem. For Judah has contaminated the sanctified of the Lord, which he loved, and has held the daughter of a strange god.

12 The Lord will drive away the man who has done this, both the teacher and the disciple, from the tabernacles of Jacob and from those offering a gift to the Lord of hosts.

13 And you have done this repeatedly: you have covered the altar of the Lord with tears, with weeping and bellowing, to such an extent that I no longer have respect towards the sacrifice, nor do I accept any appeasement that is from your hands.

14 And you have said, "What is the reason for this?" It is because the Lord has been a witness between you and the wife of your youth, whom you have despised. Yet she was your partner, and the wife of your covenant.

15 Did not One make her, and is she not the remainder of his spirit? And what does one seek, except offspring of God? So then, preserve your spirit, and do not despise the wife of your youth.

16 If you would hold hatred, dismiss her, says the Lord, the God of Israel. But iniquity will cover his garment, says the Lord of hosts. Preserve your spirit, and do not be willing to despise.

17 You have wearied the Lord with your speeches, and you have said, "In what way, have we wearied him?" In that you say, "Everyone who does evil is good in the sight of the Lord, and such as these please him," or certainly, "Where is the God of judgment?"

Malachi 3

1 Behold, I send my angel, and he will prepare the way before my face. And presently the Sovereign, whom you seek, and the angel of testimony, whom you desire, will arrive at his temple. Behold, he approaches, says the Lord of hosts.

2 And who will be able to consider the day of his advent, and who will stand firm in order to see him? For he is like a refining fire, and like the fuller's herb.

3 And he will sit refining and cleansing the silver, and he will purge the sons of Levi, and he will gather them like gold and like silver, and they will offer sacrifices to the Lord in justice.

4 And the sacrifice of Judah and of Jerusalem will please the Lord, just as in the days of past generations, and as in the ancient years.

5 And I will approach you in judgment, and I will be a swift witness against evil-doers, and adulterers, and perjurers, and those who cheat the hired hand in his wages, the widows and the orphans, and who oppress the traveler, and who have not feared me, says the Lord of hosts.

6 For I am the Lord, and I do not change. And you, the sons of Jacob, have not been consumed.

7 For, from the days of your fathers, you have withdrawn from my ordinances and have not kept them. Return to me, and I will return to you, says the Lord of hosts. And you have said, "In what way, shall we return?"

8 If a man will afflict God, then you greatly afflict me. And you have said, "In what way, do we afflict you?" In tithes and in first-fruits.

9 And you have been cursed with privation, and you greatly afflict me, even your entire people.

10 Bring all the tithes into the storehouse, and let there be food in my house. And test me about this, says the Lord, as to whether I will not open to you the floodgates of heaven, and pour out to you a blessing, all the way to abundance.

11 And I will rebuke for your sakes the devourer, and he will not corrupt the fruit of your land. Neither will the vine in the field be barren, says the Lord of hosts.

12 And all nations will call you blessed. For you will be a desirable land, says the Lord of hosts.

13 Your words have gathered strength over me, says the Lord.

14 And you have said, "What have we spoken against you?" You have said, "He labors in vain who serves God," and, "What advantage is it that we have kept his precepts, and that we have walked sorrowfully in the sight of the Lord of hosts?

15 Therefore, we now call the arrogant blessed, as if those who work impiety have been built up, and as if they have tempted God and been saved."

16 Then those who fear the Lord spoke, each one with his neighbor. And the Lord paid attention and heeded. And a book of remembrance was written in his sight, for those who fear the Lord and for those who consider his name.

17 And they will be my special possession, says the Lord of hosts, on the day that I act. And I will spare them, just as a man spares his son who serves him.

18 And you shall be converted, and you will see the difference between the just and the impious, and between those who serve God and those who do not serve him.

Matthew 1

1 The book of the lineage of Jesus Christ, the son of David, the son of Abraham.

2 Abraham conceived Isaac. And Isaac conceived Jacob. And Jacob conceived Judah and his brothers.

3 And Judah conceived Perez and Zerah by Tamar. And Perez conceived Hezron. And Hezron conceived Ram.

4 And Ram conceived Amminadab. And Amminadab conceived Nahshon. And Nahshon conceived Salmon.

5 And Salmon conceived Boaz by Rahab. And Boaz conceived Obed by Ruth. And Obed conceived Jesse.

6 And Jesse conceived king David. And king David conceived Solomon, by her who had been the wife of Uriah.

7 And Solomon conceived Rehoboam. And Rehoboam conceived Abijah. And Abijah conceived Asa.

8 And Asa conceived Jehoshaphat. And Jehoshaphat conceived Joram. And Joram conceived Uzziah.

9 And Uzziah conceived Jotham. And Jotham conceived Ahaz. And Ahaz conceived Hezekiah.

10 And Hezekiah conceived Manasseh. And Manasseh conceived Amos. And Amos conceived Josiah.

11 And Josiah conceived Jechoniah and his brothers in the transmigration of Babylon.

12 And after the transmigration of Babylon, Jechoniah conceived Shealtiel. And Shealtiel conceived Zerubbabel.

13 And Zerubbabel conceived Abiud. And Abiud conceived Eliakim. And Eliakim conceived Azor.

14 And Azor conceived Zadok. And Zadok conceived Achim. And Achim conceived Eliud.

15 And Eliud conceived Eleazar. And Eleazar conceived Matthan. And Matthan conceived Jacob.

16 And Jacob conceived Joseph, the husband of Mary, of whom was born Jesus, who is called Christ.

17 And so, all the generations from Abraham to David are fourteen generations; and from David to the transmigration of Babylon, fourteen generations; and from the transmigration of Babylon to the Christ, fourteen generations.

18 Now the procreation of the Christ occurred in this way. After his mother Mary had been betrothed to Joseph, before they lived together, she was found to have conceived in her womb by the Holy Spirit.

19 Then Joseph, her husband, since he was just and was not willing to hand her over, preferred to send her away secretly.

20 But while thinking over these things, behold, an Angel of the Lord appeared to him in his sleep, saying: "Joseph, son of David, do not be afraid to accept Mary as your wife. For what has been formed in her is of the Holy Spirit.

21 And she shall give birth to a son. And you shall call his name JESUS. For he shall accomplish the salvation of his people from their sins."

22 Now all this occurred in order to fulfill what was spoken by the Lord through the prophet, saying:

23 "Behold, a virgin shall conceive in her womb, and she shall give birth to a son. And they shall call his name Emmanuel, which means: God is with us."

24 Then Joseph, arising from sleep, did just as the Angel of the Lord had instructed him, and he accepted her as his wife.

25 And he knew her not, yet she bore her son, the firstborn. And he called his name JESUS.

Matthew 2

1 And so, when Jesus had been born in Bethlehem of Judah, in the days of king Herod, behold, Magi from the east arrived in Jerusalem,

2 saying: "Where is he who was born king of the Jews? For we have seen his star in the east, and we have come to adore him."

3 Now king Herod, hearing this, was disturbed, and all Jerusalem with him.

4 And gathering together all the leaders of the priests, and the scribes of the people, he consulted with them as to where the Christ would be born.

5 And they said to him: "In Bethlehem of Judea. For so it has been written by the prophet:

6 'And you, Bethlehem, the land of Judah, are by no means least among the leaders of Judah. For from you shall go forth the ruler who shall guide my people Israel.' "

7 Then Herod, quietly calling the Magi, diligently learned from them the time when the star appeared to them.

8 And sending them into Bethlehem, he said: "Go and diligently ask questions about the boy. And when you have found him, report back to me, so that I, too, may come and adore him."

9 And when they had heard the king, they went away. And behold, the star that they had seen in the east went before them, even until, arriving, it stood still above the place where the child was.

10 Then, seeing the star, they were gladdened by a very great joy.

11 And entering the home, they found the boy with his mother Mary. And so, falling prostrate, they adored him. And opening their treasures, they offered him gifts: gold, frankincense, and myrrh.

12 And having received a response in sleep that they should not return to Herod, they went back by another way to their own region.

13 And after they had gone away, behold, an Angel of the Lord appeared in sleep to Joseph, saying: "Rise up, and take the boy and his mother, and flee into Egypt. And remain there until I tell you. For it will happen that Herod will seek the boy to destroy him."

14 And getting up, he took the boy and his mother by night, and withdrew into Egypt.

15 And he remained there, until the death of Herod, in order to fulfill what was spoken by the Lord through the prophet, saying: "Out of Egypt, I called my son."

16 Then Herod, seeing that he had been fooled by the Magi, was very angry. And so he sent to kill all the boys who were in Bethlehem, and in all its borders, from two years of age and under, according to the time that he had learned by questioning the Magi.

17 Then what was spoken through the prophet Jeremiah was fulfilled, saying:

18 "A voice has been heard in Ramah, great weeping and wailing: Rachel crying for her sons. And she was not willing to be consoled, because they were no more."

19 Then, when Herod had passed away, behold, an Angel of the Lord appeared in sleep to Joseph in Egypt,

20 saying: "Rise up, and take the boy and his mother, and go into the land of Israel. For those who were seeking the life of the boy have passed away."

21 And rising up, he took the boy and his mother, and he went into the land of Israel.

22 Then, hearing that Archelaus reigned in Judea in place of his father Herod, he was afraid to go there. And being warned in sleep, he withdrew into parts of Galilee.

23 And arriving, he lived in a city which is called Nazareth, in order to fulfill what was spoken through the prophets: "For he shall be called a Nazarene."

Matthew 3

1 Now in those days, John the Baptist arrived, preaching in the desert of Judea,

2 and saying: "Repent. For the kingdom of heaven has drawn near."

3 For this is the one who was spoken of through the prophet Isaiah, saying: "A voice crying out in the desert: Prepare the way of the Lord. Make straight his paths."

4 Now the same John had a garment made from the hair of camels, and a leather belt around his waist. And his food was locusts and wild honey.

5 Then Jerusalem, and all Judea, and the entire region around the Jordan went out to him.

6 And they were baptized by him in the Jordan, acknowledging their sins.

7 Then, seeing many of the Pharisees and Sadducees arriving for his baptism, he said to them: "Progeny of vipers, who warned to you to flee from the approaching wrath?

8 Therefore, produce fruit worthy of repentance.

9 And do not choose to say within yourselves, 'We have Abraham as our father.' For I tell you that God has the power to raise up sons to Abraham from these stones.

10 For even now the axe has been placed at the root of the trees. Therefore, every tree that does not produce good fruit shall be cut down and cast into the fire.

11 Indeed, I baptize you with water for repentance, but he who will come after me is more powerful than me. I am not worthy to carry his shoes. He will baptize you with the fire of the Holy Spirit.

12 His winnowing fan is in his hand. And he will thoroughly cleanse his threshing floor. And he will gather his wheat into the barn. But the chaff he will burn with unquenchable fire."

13 Then Jesus came from Galilee, to John at the Jordan, in order to be baptized by him.

14 But John refused him, saying, "I ought to be baptized by you, and yet you come to me?"

15 And responding, Jesus said to him: "Permit this for now. For in this way it is fitting for us to fulfill all justice." Then he allowed him.

16 And Jesus, having been baptized, ascended from the water immediately, and behold, the heavens were opened to him. And he saw the Spirit of God descending like a dove, and alighting on him.

17 And behold, there was a voice from heaven, saying: "This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased."

Matthew 4

1 Then Jesus was led by the Spirit into the desert, in order to be tempted by the devil.

2 And when he had fasted for forty days and forty nights, afterwards he was hungry.

3 And approaching, the tempter said to him, "If you are the Son of God, tell these stones to become bread."

4 And in response he said, "It has been written: 'Not by bread alone shall man live, but by every word that proceeds from the mouth of God.' "

5 Then the devil took him up, into the holy city, and set him on the pinnacle of the temple,

6 and said to him: "If you are the Son of God, cast yourself down. For it has been written: 'For he has given charge of you to his angels, and they shall take you into their hands, lest perhaps you may hurt your foot against a stone.' "

7 Jesus said to him, "Again, it has been written: 'You shall not tempt the Lord your God.' "

8 Again, the devil took him up, onto a very high mountain, and showed him all the kingdoms of the world and their glory,

9 and said to him, "All these things I will give to you, if you will fall down and adore me."

10 Then Jesus said to him: "Go away, Satan. For it has been written: 'You shall adore the Lord your God, and him only shall you serve.' "

11 Then the devil left him. And behold, Angels approached and ministered to him.

12 And when Jesus had heard that John had been handed over, he withdrew into Galilee.

13 And leaving behind the city of Nazareth, he went and lived in Capernaum, near the sea, at the borders of Zebulun and of Naphtali,

14 in order to fulfill what was said through the prophet Isaiah:

15 "Land of Zebulun and land of Naphtali, the way of the sea across the Jordan, Galilee of the Gentiles:

16 A people who were sitting in darkness have seen a great light. And unto those sitting in the region of the shadow of death, a light has risen."

17 From that time, Jesus began to preach, and to say: "Repent. For the kingdom of heaven has drawn near."

18 And Jesus, walking near the Sea of Galilee, saw two brothers, Simon who is called Peter, and his brother Andrew, casting a net into the sea (for they were fishermen).

19 And he said to them: "Follow me, and I will make you fishers of men."

20 And at once, leaving behind their nets, they followed him.

21 And continuing on from there, he saw another two brothers, James of Zebedee, and his brother John, in a ship with their father Zebedee, repairing their nets. And he called them.

22 And immediately, leaving their nets and their father behind, they followed him.

23 And Jesus traveled throughout all of Galilee, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the Gospel of the kingdom, and healing every sickness and every infirmity among the people.

24 And reports of him went out to all of Syria, and they brought to him all those who had maladies, those who were in the grasp of various sicknesses and torments, and those who were in the hold of demons, and the mentally ill, and paralytics. And he cured them.

25 And a great crowd followed him from Galilee, and from the Ten Cities, and from Jerusalem, and from Judea, and from across the Jordan.

Matthew 5

1 Then, seeing the crowds, he ascended the mountain, and when he had sat down, his disciples drew near to him,

2 and opening his mouth, he taught them, saying:

3 "Blessed are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.

4 Blessed are the meek, for they shall possess the earth.

5 Blessed are those who mourn, for they shall be consoled.

6 Blessed are those who hunger and thirst for justice, for they shall be satisfied.

7 Blessed are the merciful, for they shall obtain mercy.

8 Blessed are the pure in heart, for they shall see God.

9 Blessed are the peacemakers, for they shall be called sons of God.

10 Blessed are those who endure persecution for the sake of justice, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.

11 Blessed are you when they have slandered you, and persecuted you, and spoken all kinds of evil against you, falsely, for my sake:

12 be glad and exult, for your reward in heaven is plentiful. For so they persecuted the prophets who were before you.

13 You are the salt of the earth. But if salt loses its saltiness, with what will it be salted? It is no longer useful at all, except to be cast out and trampled under by men.

14 You are the light of the world. A city set on a mountain cannot be hidden.

15 And they do not light a lamp and put it under a basket, but on a lampstand, so that it may shine to all who are in the house.

16 So then, let your light shine in the sight of men, so that they may see your good works, and may glorify your Father, who is in heaven.

17 Do not think that I have come to loosen the law or the prophets. I have not come to loosen, but to fulfill.

18 Amen I say to you, certainly, until heaven and earth pass away, not one iota, not one dot shall pass away from the law, until all is done.

19 Therefore, whoever will have loosened one of the least of these commandments, and have taught men so, shall be called the least in the kingdom of heaven. But whoever will have done and taught these, such a one shall be called great in the kingdom of heaven.

20 For I say to you, that unless your justice has surpassed that of the scribes and the Pharisees you shall not enter into the kingdom of heaven.

21 You have heard that it was said to the ancients: 'You shall not murder; whoever will have murdered shall be liable to judgment.'

22 But I say to you, that anyone who becomes angry with his brother shall be liable to judgment. But whoever will have called his brother, 'Idiot,' shall be liable to the council. Then, whoever will have called him, 'Worthless,' shall be liable to the fires of Hell.

23 Therefore, if you offer your gift at the altar, and there you remember that your brother has something against you,

24 leave your gift there, before the altar, and go first to be reconciled to your brother, and then you may approach and offer your gift.

25 Be reconciled with your adversary quickly, while you are still on the way with him, lest perhaps the adversary may hand you over to the judge, and the judge may hand you over to the officer, and you will be thrown in prison.

26 Amen I say to you, that you shall not go forth from there, until you have repaid the last quarter.

27 You have heard that it was said to the ancients: 'You shall not commit adultery.'

28 But I say to you, that anyone who will have looked at a woman, so as to lust after her, has already committed adultery with her in his heart.

29 And if your right eye causes you to sin, root it out and cast it away from you. For it is better for you that one of your members perish, than that your whole body be cast into Hell.

30 And if your right hand causes you to sin, cut it off and cast it away from you. For it is better for you that one of your members perish, than that your whole body go into Hell.

31 And it has been said: 'Whoever would dismiss his wife, let him give her a bill of divorce.'

32 But I say to you, that anyone who will have dismissed his wife, except in the case of fornication, causes her to commit adultery; and whoever will have married her who has been dismissed commits adultery.

33 Again, you have heard that it was said to the ancients: 'You shall not swear falsely. For you shall repay your oaths to the Lord.'

34 But I say to you, do not swear an oath at all, neither by heaven, for it is the throne of God,

35 nor by earth, for it is his footstool, nor by Jerusalem, for it is the city of the great king.

36 Neither shall you swear an oath by your own head, because you are not able to cause one hair to become white or black.

37 But let your word 'Yes' mean 'Yes,' and 'No' mean 'No.' For anything beyond that is of evil.

38 You have heard that it was said: 'An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth.'

39 But I say to you, do not resist one who is evil, but if anyone will have struck you on your right cheek, offer to him the other also.

40 And anyone who wishes to contend with you in judgment, and to take away your tunic, release to him your cloak also.

41 And whoever will have compelled you for one thousand steps, go with him even for two thousand steps.

42 Whoever asks of you, give to him. And if anyone would borrow from you, do not turn away from him.

43 You have heard that it was said, 'You shall love your neighbor, and you shall have hatred for your enemy.'

44 But I say to you: Love your enemies. Do good to those who hate you. And pray for those who persecute and slander you.

45 In this way, you shall be sons of your Father, who is in heaven. He causes his sun to rise upon the good and the bad, and he causes it to rain upon the just and the unjust.

46 For if you love those who love you, what reward will you have? Do not even tax collectors behave this way?

47 And if you greet only your brothers, what more have you done? Do not even the pagans behave this way?

48 Therefore, be perfect, even as your heavenly Father is perfect."

Matthew 6

1 "Pay attention, lest you perform your justice before men, in order to be seen by them; otherwise you shall not have a reward with your Father, who is in heaven.

2 Therefore, when you give alms, do not choose to sound a trumpet before you, as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the towns, so that they may be honored by men. Amen I say to you, they have received their reward.

3 But when you give alms, do not let your left hand know what your right hand is doing,

4 so that your almsgiving may be in secret, and your Father, who sees in secret, will repay you.

5 And when you pray, you should not be like the hypocrites, who love standing in the synagogues and at the corners of the streets to pray, so that they may be seen by men. Amen I say to you, they have received their reward.

6 But you, when you pray, enter into your room, and having shut the door, pray to your Father in secret, and your Father, who sees in secret, will repay you.

7 And when praying, do not choose many words, as the pagans do. For they think that by their excess of words they might be heeded.

8 Therefore, do not choose to imitate them. For your Father knows what your needs may be, even before you ask him.

9 Therefore, you shall pray in this way: Our Father, who is in heaven: May your name be kept holy.

10 May your kingdom come. May your will be done, as in heaven, so also on earth.

11 Give us this day our life-sustaining bread.

12 And forgive us our debts, as we also forgive our debtors.

13 And lead us not into temptation. But free us from evil. Amen.

14 For if you will forgive men their sins, your heavenly Father also will forgive you your offenses.

15 But if you will not forgive men, neither will your Father forgive you your sins.

16 And when you fast, do not choose to become gloomy, like the hypocrites. For they alter their faces, so that their fasting may be apparent to men. Amen I say to you, that they have received their reward.

17 But as for you, when you fast, anoint your head and wash your face,

18 so that your fasting will not be apparent to men, but to your Father, who is in secret. And your Father, who sees in secret, will repay you.

19 Do not choose to store up for yourselves treasures on earth: where rust and moth consume, and where thieves break in and steal.

20 Instead, store up for yourselves treasures in heaven: where neither rust nor moth consumes, and where thieves do not break in and steal.

21 For where your treasure is, there also is your heart.

22 The lamp of your body is your eye. If your eye is wholesome, your entire body will be filled with light.

23 But if your eye has been corrupted, your entire body will be darkened. If then the light that is in you is darkness, how great will that darkness be!

24 No one is able to serve two masters. For either he will have hatred for the one, and love the other, or he will persevere with the one, and despise the other. You cannot serve God and wealth.

25 And so I say to you, do not be anxious about your life, as to what you will eat, nor about your body, as to what you will wear. Is not life more than food, and the body more than clothing?

26 Consider the birds of the air, how they neither sow, nor reap, nor gather into barns, and yet your heavenly Father feeds them. Are you not of much greater value than they are?

27 And which of you, by thinking, is able to add one cubit to his stature?

28 And as for clothing, why are you anxious? Consider the lilies of the field, how they grow; they neither work nor weave.

29 But I say to you, that not even Solomon, in all his glory, was arrayed like one of these.

30 So if God so clothes the grass of the field, which is here today, and cast into the oven tomorrow, how much more will he care for you, O little in faith?

31 Therefore, do not choose to be anxious, saying: 'What shall we eat, and what shall we drink, and with what shall we be clothed?'

32 For the Gentiles seek all these things. Yet your Father knows that you need all these things.

33 Therefore, seek first the kingdom of God and his justice, and all these things shall be added to you as well.

34 Therefore, do not be anxious about tomorrow; for the future day will be anxious for itself. Sufficient for the day is its evil."

Matthew 7

1 "Do not judge, so that you may not be judged.

2 For with whatever judgment you judge, so shall you be judged; and with whatever measure you measure out, so shall it be measured back to you.

3 And how can you see the splinter in your brother's eye, and not see the board in your own eye?

4 Or how can you say to your brother, 'Let me take the splinter from your eye,' while, behold, a board is in your own eye?

5 Hypocrite, first remove the board from your own eye, and then you will see clearly enough to remove the splinter from your brother's eye.

6 Do not give what is holy to dogs, and do not cast your pearls before swine, lest perhaps they may trample them under their feet, and then, turning, they may tear you apart.

7 Ask, and it shall be given to you. Seek, and you shall find. Knock, and it shall be opened to you.

8 For everyone who asks, receives; and whoever seeks, finds; and to anyone who knocks, it will be opened.

9 Or what man is there among you, who, if his son were to ask him for bread, would offer him a stone;

10 or if he were to ask him for a fish, would offer him a snake?

11 Therefore, if you, though you are evil, know how to give good gifts to your sons, how much more will your Father, who is in heaven, give good things to those who ask him?

12 Therefore, all things whatsoever that you wish that men would do to you, do so also to them. For this is the law and the prophets.

13 Enter through the narrow gate. For wide is the gate, and broad is the way, which leads to perdition, and many there are who enter through it.

14 How narrow is the gate, and how straight is the way, which leads to life, and few there are who find it!

15 Beware of false prophets, who come to you in sheep's clothing, but inwardly are ravenous wolves.

16 You shall know them by their fruits. Can grapes be gathered from thorns, or figs from thistles?

17 So then, every good tree produces good fruit, and the evil tree produces evil fruit.

18 A good tree is not able to produce evil fruit, and an evil tree is not able to produce good fruit.

19 Every tree which does not produce good fruit shall be cut down and cast into the fire.

20 Therefore, by their fruits you will know them.

21 Not all who say to me, 'Lord, Lord,' will enter into the kingdom of heaven. But whoever does the will of my Father, who is in heaven, the same shall enter into the kingdom of heaven.

22 Many will say to me in that day, 'Lord, Lord, did we not prophesy in your name, and cast out demons in your name, and perform many powerful deeds in your name?'

23 And then will I disclose to them: 'I have never known you. Depart from me, you workers of iniquity.'

24 Therefore, everyone who hears these words of mine and does them shall be compared to a wise man, who built his house upon the rock.

25 And the rains descended, and the floods rose up, and the winds blew, and rushed upon that house, but it did not fall, for it was founded on the rock.

26 And everyone who hears these words of mine and does not do them shall be like a foolish man, who built his house upon the sand.

27 And the rains descended, and the floods rose up, and the winds blew, and rushed upon that house, and it did fall, and great was its ruin."

28 And it happened, when Jesus had completed these words, that the crowds were astonished at his doctrine.

29 For he was teaching them as one who has authority, and not like their scribes and Pharisees.

Matthew 8

1 And when he had descended from the mountain, great crowds followed him.

2 And behold, a leper, drawing near, adored him, saying, "Lord, if you are willing, you are able to cleanse me."

3 And Jesus, extending his hand, touched him, saying: "I am willing. Be cleansed." And immediately his leprosy was cleansed.

4 And Jesus said to him: "See to it that you tell no one. But go, show yourself to the priest, and offer the gift that Moses instructed, as a testimony for them."

5 And when he had entered into Capernaum, a centurion approached, petitioning him,

6 and saying, "Lord, my servant lies at home paralyzed and badly tormented."

7 And Jesus said to him, "I will come and heal him."

8 And responding, the centurion said: "Lord, I am not worthy that you should enter under my roof, but only say the word, and my servant shall be healed.

9 For I, too, am a man placed under authority, having soldiers under me. And I say to one, 'Go,' and he goes, and to another, 'Come,' and he comes, and to my servant, 'Do this,' and he does it."

10 And, hearing this, Jesus wondered. And he said to those following him: "Amen I say to you, I have not found so great a faith in Israel.

11 For I say to you, that many shall come from the east and the west, and they shall sit at table with Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven.

12 But the sons of the kingdom shall be cast into the outer darkness, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth."

13 And Jesus said to the centurion, "Go, and just as you have believed, so let it be done for you." And the servant was healed at that very hour.

14 And when Jesus had arrived at the house of Peter, he saw his mother-in-law lying ill with a fever.

15 And he touched her hand, and the fever left her, and she rose up and ministered to them.

16 And when evening arrived, they brought to him many who had demons, and he cast out the spirits with a word. And he healed all those having maladies,

17 in order to fulfill what was spoken through the prophet Isaiah, saying, "He took our infirmities, and he carried away our diseases."

18 Then Jesus, seeing the great crowds encircling him, gave orders to go across the sea.

19 And one scribe, approaching, said to him, "Teacher, I will follow you wherever you will go."

20 And Jesus said to him, "Foxes have dens, and the birds of the air have nests, but the Son of man has nowhere to rest his head."

21 Then another of his disciples said to him, "Lord, permit me first to go and bury my father."

22 But Jesus said to him, "Follow me, and allow the dead to bury their dead."

23 And climbing into a boat, his disciples followed him.

24 And behold, a great tempest occurred in the sea, so much so that the boat was covered with waves; yet truly, he was sleeping.

25 And his disciples drew near to him, and they awakened him, saying: "Lord, save us, we are perishing."

26 And Jesus said to them, "Why are you afraid, O little in faith?" Then rising up, he commanded the winds, and the sea. And a great tranquility occurred.

27 Moreover, the men wondered, saying: "What kind of man is this? For even the winds and the sea obey him."

28 And when he had arrived across the sea, into the region of the Gerasenes, he was met by two who had demons, who were so exceedingly savage, as they went out from among the tombs, that no one was able to cross by that way.

29 And behold, they cried out, saying: "What are we to you, O Jesus, the Son of God? Have you come here to torment us before the time?"

30 Now there was, not far from them, a herd of many swine feeding.

31 Then the demons petitioned him, saying: "If you cast us from here, send us into the herd of swine."

32 And he said to them, "Go." And they, going out, went into the swine. And behold, the entire herd suddenly rushed along a steep place into the sea. And they died in the waters.

33 Then the shepherds fled, and arriving in the city, they reported on all this, and on those who had had the demons.

34 And behold, the entire city went out to meet Jesus. And having seen him, they petitioned him, so that he would cross from their borders.

Matthew 9

1 And climbing into a boat, he crossed the sea, and he arrived at his own city.

2 And behold, they brought to him a paralytic, lying on a bed. And Jesus, seeing their faith, said to the paralytic, "Be strengthened in faith, son; your sins are forgiven you."

3 And behold, some of the scribes said within themselves, "He is blaspheming."

4 And when Jesus had perceived their thoughts, he said: "Why do you think such evil in your hearts?

5 Which is easier to say, 'Your sins are forgiven you,' or to say, 'Rise up and walk?'

6 But, so that you may know that the Son of man has authority on earth to forgive sins," he then said to the paralytic, "Rise up, take up your bed, and go into your house."

7 And he arose and went into his house.

8 Then the crowd, seeing this, was frightened, and they glorified God, who gave such power to men.

9 And when Jesus passed on from there, he saw, sitting at the tax office, a man named Matthew. And he said to him, "Follow me." And rising up, he followed him.

10 And it happened that, as he was sitting down to eat in the house, behold, many tax collectors and sinners arrived, and they sat down to eat with Jesus and his disciples.

11 And the Pharisees, seeing this, said to his disciples, "Why does your Teacher eat with tax collectors and sinners?"

12 But Jesus, hearing this, said: "It is not those who are healthy who are in need of a physician, but those who have maladies.

13 So then, go out and learn what this means: 'I desire mercy and not sacrifice.' For I have not come to call the just, but sinners."

14 Then the disciples of John drew near to him, saying, "Why do we and the Pharisees fast frequently, but your disciples do not fast?"

15 And Jesus said to them: "How can the sons of the groom mourn, while the groom is still with them? But the days will arrive when the groom will be taken away from them. And then they shall fast.

16 For no one would sew a patch of new cloth onto an old garment. For it pulls its fullness away from the garment, and the tear is made worse.

17 Neither do they pour new wine into old wineskins. Otherwise, the wineskins rupture, and the wine pours out, and the wineskins are destroyed. Instead, they pour new wine into new wineskins. And so, both are preserved."

18 As he was speaking these things to them, behold, a certain ruler approached and adored him, saying: "Lord, my daughter has recently passed away. But come and impose your hand upon her, and she will live."

19 And Jesus, rising up, followed him, with his disciples.

20 And behold, a woman, who had suffered from a flow of blood for twelve years, approached from behind and touched the hem of his garment.

21 For she said within herself, "If I will touch even his garment, I shall be saved."

22 But Jesus, turning and seeing her, said: "Be strengthened in faith, daughter; your faith has made you well." And the woman was made well from that hour.

23 And when Jesus had arrived in the house of the ruler, and he had seen the musicians and the tumultuous crowd,

24 he said, "Depart. For the girl is not dead, but asleep." And they derided him.

25 And when the crowd had been sent away, he entered. And he took her by the hand. And the girl rose up.

26 And the news of this went out to that entire land.

27 And as Jesus passed from there, two blind men followed him, crying out and saying, "Take pity on us, Son of David."

28 And when he had arrived at the house, the blind men approached him. And Jesus said to them, "Do you trust that I am able to do this for you?" They say to him, "Certainly, Lord."

29 Then he touched their eyes, saying, "According to your faith, so let it be done for you."

30 And their eyes were opened. And Jesus warned them, saying, "See to it that no one knows of this."

31 But going out, they spread the news of it to all that land.

32 Then, when they had departed, behold, they brought him a man who was mute, having a demon.

33 And after the demon was cast out, the mute man spoke. And the crowds wondered, saying, "Never has anything like this been seen in Israel."

34 But the Pharisees said, "By the prince of demons does he cast out demons."

35 And Jesus traveled throughout all of the cities and towns, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the Gospel of the kingdom, and healing every illness and every infirmity.

36 Then, seeing the multitudes, he had compassion on them, because they were distressed and were reclining, like sheep without a shepherd.

37 Then he said to his disciples: "The harvest indeed is great, but the laborers are few.

38 Therefore, petition the Lord of the harvest, so that he may sent out laborers to his harvest."

Matthew 10

1 And having called together his twelve disciples, he gave them authority over unclean spirits, to cast them out and to cure every sickness and every infirmity.

2 Now the names of the twelve Apostles are these: the First, Simon, who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother,

3 James of Zebedee, and John his brother, Philip and Bartholomew, Thomas and Matthew the tax collector, and James of Alphaeus, and Thaddaeus,

4 Simon the Canaanite, and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him.

5 Jesus sent these twelve, instructing them, saying: "Do not travel by the way of the Gentiles, and do not enter into the city of the Samaritans,

6 but instead go to the sheep who have fallen away from the house of Israel.

7 And going forth, preach, saying: 'For the kingdom of heaven has drawn near.'

8 Cure the infirm, raise the dead, cleanse lepers, cast out demons. You have received freely, so give freely.

9 Do not choose to possess gold, nor silver, nor money in your belts,

10 nor provisions for the journey, nor two tunics, nor shoes, nor a staff. For the laborer deserves his portion.

11 Now, into whatever city or town you will enter, inquire as to who is worthy within it. And stay there until you depart.

12 Then, when you enter into the house, greet it, saying, 'Peace to this house.'

13 And if, indeed, that house is worthy, your peace will rest upon it. But if it is not worthy, your peace will return to you.

14 And whoever has neither received you, nor listened to your words, departing from that house or city, shake off the dust from your feet.

15 Amen I say to you, it will be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of judgment, than for that city.

16 Behold, I am sending you like sheep in the midst of wolves. Therefore, be as prudent as serpents and as simple as doves.

17 But beware of men. For they will hand you over to councils, and they will scourge you in their synagogues.

18 And you shall be led before both rulers and kings for my sake, as a testimony to them and to the Gentiles.

19 But when they hand you over, do not choose to think about how or what to speak. For what to speak shall be given to you in that hour.

20 For it is not you who will be speaking, but the Spirit of your Father, who will speak in you.

21 And brother will hand over brother to death, and father will hand over son. And children will rise up against parents and bring about their deaths.

22 And you will be hated by all for the sake of my name. But whoever will have persevered, even to the end, the same shall be saved.

23 Now when they persecute you in one city, flee into another. Amen I say to you, you will not have exhausted all the cities of Israel, before the Son of man returns.

24 The disciple is not above the teacher, nor is the servant above his master.

25 It is sufficient for the disciple that he be like his teacher, and the servant, like his master. If they have called the Father of the family, 'Beelzebub,' how much more those of his household?

26 Therefore, do not fear them. For nothing is covered that shall not be revealed, nor hidden that shall not be known.

27 What I tell you in darkness, speak in the light. And what you hear whispered in the ear, preach above the rooftops.

28 And do not be afraid of those who kill the body, but are not able to kill the soul. But instead fear him who is able to destroy both soul and body in Hell.

29 Are not two sparrows sold for one small coin? And yet not one of them will fall to the ground without your Father.

30 For even the hairs of your head have all been numbered.

31 Therefore, do not be afraid. You are worth more than many sparrows.

32 Therefore, everyone who acknowledges me before men, I also will acknowledge before my Father, who is in heaven.

33 But whoever will have denied me before men, I also will deny before my Father, who is in heaven.

34 Do not think that I came to send peace upon the earth. I came, not to send peace, but the sword.

35 For I came to divide a man against his father, and a daughter against her mother, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law.

36 And the enemies of a man will be those of his own household.

37 Whoever loves father or mother more than me is not worthy of me. And whoever loves son or daughter above me is not worthy of me.

38 And whoever does not take up his cross, and follow me is not worthy of me.

39 Whoever finds his life, will lose it. And whoever will have lost his life because of me, shall find it.

40 Whoever receives you, receives me. And whoever receives me, receives him who sent me.

41 Whoever receives a prophet, in the name of a prophet, shall receive the reward of a prophet. And whoever receives the just in the name of the just shall receive the reward of the just.

42 And whoever shall give, even to one of the least of these, a cup of cold water to drink, solely in the name of a disciple: Amen I say to you, he shall not lose his reward."

Matthew 11

1 And it happened that, when Jesus had completed instructing his twelve disciples, he went away from there in order to teach and to preach in their cities.

2 Now when John had heard, in prison, about the works of Christ, sending two of his disciples, he said to him,

3 "Are you he who is to come, or should we expect another?"

4 And Jesus, responding, said to them: "Go and report to John what you have heard and seen.

5 The blind see, the lame walk, the lepers are cleansed, the deaf hear, the dead rise again, the poor are evangelized.

6 And blessed is he who has found no offense in me."

7 Then, after they departed, Jesus began to speak to the crowds about John: "What did you go out to the desert to see? A reed shaken by the wind?

8 So what did you go out to see? A man in soft garments? Behold, those who are clothed in soft garments are in the houses of kings.

9 Then what did you go out to see? A prophet? Yes, I tell you, and more than a prophet.

10 For this is he, of whom it is written: 'Behold, I send my Angel before your face, who shall prepare your way before you.'

11 Amen I say to you, among those born of women, there has arisen no one greater than John the Baptist. Yet the least in the kingdom of heaven is greater than he.

12 But from the days of John the Baptist, even until now, the kingdom of heaven has endured violence, and the violent carry it away.

13 For all the prophets and the law prophesied, even until John.

14 And if you are willing to accept it, he is the Elijah, who is to come.

15 Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear.

16 But to what shall I compare this generation? It is like children sitting in the marketplace,

17 who, calling out to their companions, say: 'We played music for you, and you did not dance. We lamented, and you did not mourn.'

18 For John came neither eating nor drinking; and they say, 'He has a demon.'

19 The Son of man came eating and drinking; and they say, 'Behold, a man who eats voraciously and who drinks wine, a friend of tax collectors and sinners.' But wisdom is justified by her sons."

20 Then he began to rebuke the cities in which many of his miracles were accomplished, for they still had not repented.

21 "Woe to you, Chorazin! Woe to you, Bethsaida! For if the miracles that were done in you had been done in Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago in haircloth and ashes.

22 Yet truly, I say to you, Tyre and Sidon shall be forgiven more than you, on the day of judgment.

23 And you, Capernaum, would you be exalted all the way to heaven? You shall descend all the way to Hell. For if the miracles that were done in you had been done in Sodom, perhaps it would have remained, even to this day.

24 Yet truly, I say to you, that the land of Sodom shall be forgiven more than you, on the day of judgment."

25 At that time, Jesus responded and said: "I acknowledge you, Father, Lord of Heaven and earth, because you have hidden these things from the wise and the prudent, and have revealed them to little ones.

26 Yes, Father, for this was pleasing before you.

27 All things have been delivered to me by my Father. And no one knows the Son except the Father, nor does anyone know the Father except the Son, and those to whom the Son is willing to reveal him.

28 Come to me, all you who labor and have been burdened, and I will refresh you.

29 Take my yoke upon you, and learn from me, for I am meek and humble of heart; and you shall find rest for your souls.

30 For my yoke is sweet and my burden is light."

Matthew 12

1 At that time, Jesus went out through the ripe grain on the Sabbath. And his disciples, being hungry, began to separate the grain and to eat.

2 Then the Pharisees, seeing this, said to him, "Behold, your disciples are doing what is not lawful to do on the Sabbaths."

3 But he said to them: "Have you not read what David did, when he was hungry, and those who were with him:

4 how he entered the house of God and ate the bread of the Presence, which was not lawful for him to eat, nor for those who were with him, but only for the priests?

5 Or have you not read in the law, that on the Sabbaths the priests in the temple violate the Sabbath, and they are without guilt?

6 But I say to you, that something greater than the temple is here.

7 And if you knew what this means, 'I desire mercy, and not sacrifice,' you would never have condemned the innocent.

8 For the Son of man is Lord even of the Sabbath."

9 And when he had passed from there, he went into their synagogues.

10 And behold, there was a man who had a withered hand, and they questioned him, so that they might accuse him, saying, "Is it lawful to cure on the Sabbaths?"

11 But he said to them: "Who is there among you, having even one sheep, if it will have fallen into a pit on the Sabbath, would not take hold of it and lift it up?

12 How much better is a man than a sheep? And so, it is lawful to do good on the Sabbaths."

13 Then he said to the man, "Extend your hand." And he extended it, and it was restored to health, just like the other one.

14 Then the Pharisees, departing, took council against him, as to how they might destroy him.

15 But Jesus, knowing this, withdrew from there. And many followed him, and he cured them all.

16 And he instructed them, lest they make him known.

17 Then what was spoken through the prophet Isaiah was fulfilled, saying:

18 "Behold, my servant whom I have chosen, my beloved in whom my soul is well pleased. I will place my Spirit over him, and he shall announce judgment to the nations.

19 He shall not contend, nor cry out, neither shall anyone hear his voice in the streets.

20 He shall not crush the bruised reed, and he shall not extinguish the smoking wick, until he sends forth judgment unto victory.

21 And the Gentiles shall hope in his name."

22 Then one who had a demon, who was blind and mute, was brought to him. And he cured him, so that he spoke and saw.

23 And all the crowds were stupefied, and they said, "Could this be the son of David?"

24 But the Pharisees, hearing it, said, "This man does not cast out demons, except by Beelzebub, the prince of the demons."

25 But Jesus, knowing their thoughts, said to them: "Every kingdom divided against itself will become desolate. And every city or house divided against itself will not stand.

26 So if Satan casts out Satan, then he is divided against himself. How then will his kingdom stand?

27 And if I cast out demons by Beelzebub, by whom do your own sons cast them out? Therefore, they shall be your judges.

28 But if I cast out demons by the Spirit of God, then the kingdom of God has arrived among you.

29 Or how can anyone enter into the house of a strong man, and plunder his belongings, unless he first restrains the strong man? And then he will plunder his house.

30 Whoever is not with me, is against me. And whoever does not gather with me, scatters.

31 For this reason, I say to you: Every sin and blasphemy shall be forgiven men, but blasphemy against the Spirit shall not be forgiven.

32 And anyone who will have spoken a word against the Son of man shall be forgiven. But whoever will have spoken against the Holy Spirit shall not be forgiven, neither in this age, nor in the future age.

33 Either make the tree good and its fruit good, or make the tree evil and its fruit evil. For certainly a tree is known by its fruit.

34 Progeny of vipers, how are you able to speak good things while you are evil? For out of the abundance of the heart, the mouth speaks.

35 A good man offers good things from a good storehouse. And an evil man offers evil things from an evil storehouse.

36 But I say to you, that for every idle word which men will have spoken, they shall render an account in the day of judgment.

37 For by your words shall you be justified, and by your words shall you be condemned."

38 Then certain ones from the scribes and the Pharisees responded to him, saying, "Teacher, we want to see a sign from you."

39 And answering, he said to them: "An evil and adulterous generation seeks a sign. But a sign will not be given to it, except the sign of the prophet Jonah.

40 For just as Jonah was in the belly of the whale for three days and three nights, so shall the Son of man be in the heart of the earth for three days and three nights.

41 The men of Nineveh shall arise in judgment with this generation, and they shall condemn it. For, at the preaching of Jonah, they repented. And behold, there is a greater than Jonah here.

42 The Queen of the South shall arise in judgment with this generation, and she shall condemn it. For she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon. And behold, there is a greater than Solomon here.

43 Now when an unclean spirit departs from a man, he walks through dry places, seeking rest, and he does not find it.

44 Then he says, 'I will return to my house, from which I departed'. And arriving, he finds it vacant, swept clean, and decorated.

45 Then he goes and takes with him seven other spirits more wicked than himself, and they enter in and live there. And in the end, the man becomes worse than he was at first. So, too, shall it be with this most wicked generation."

46 While he was still speaking to the crowds, behold, his mother and his brothers were standing outside, seeking to speak with him.

47 And someone said to him: "Behold, your mother and your brothers are standing outside, seeking you."

48 But responding to the one speaking to him, he said, "Which one is my mother, and who are my brothers?"

49 And extending his hand to his disciples, he said: "Behold: my mother and my brothers.

50 For anyone who does the will of my Father, who is in heaven, the same is my brother, and sister, and mother."

Matthew 13

1 In that day, Jesus, departing from the house, sat down beside the sea.

2 And such great crowds were gathered to him that he climbed into a boat and he sat down. And the entire multitude stood on the shore.

3 And he spoke many things to them in parables, saying: "Behold, a sower went out to sow seed.

4 And while he was sowing, some fell beside the road, and the birds of the air came and ate it.

5 Then others fell in a rocky place, where they did not have much soil. And they sprung up promptly, because they had no depth of soil.

6 But when the sun rose up, they were scorched, and because they had no roots, they withered.

7 Still others fell among thorns, and the thorns increased and suffocated them.

8 Yet some others fell upon good soil, and they produced fruit: some one hundred fold, some sixty fold, some thirty fold.

9 Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear."

10 And his disciples drew near to him and said, "Why do you speak to them in parables?"

11 Responding, he said to them: "Because it has been given to you to know the mysteries of the kingdom of heaven, but it has not been given to them.

12 For whoever has, it shall be given to him, and he shall have in abundance. But whoever has not, even what he has shall be taken away from him.

13 For this reason, I speak to them in parables: because seeing, they do not see, and hearing they do not hear, nor do they understand.

14 And so, in them is fulfilled the prophecy of Isaiah, who said, 'Hearing, you shall hear, but not understand; and seeing, you shall see, but not perceive.

15 For the heart of this people has grown fat, and with their ears they hear heavily, and they have closed their eyes, lest at any time they might see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and be converted, and then I would heal them.'

16 But blessed are your eyes, because they see, and your ears, because they hear.

17 Amen I say to you, certainly, that many of the prophets and the just desired to see what you see, and yet they did not see it, and to hear what you hear, and yet they did not hear it.

18 Listen, then, to the parable of the sower.

19 With anyone who hears the word of the kingdom and does not understand it, evil comes and carries away what was sown in his heart. This is he who received the seed by the side of the road.

20 Then whoever has received the seed upon a rocky place, this is one who hears the word and promptly accepts it with joy.

21 But he has no root in himself, so it is only for a time; then, when tribulation and persecution occur because of the word, he promptly stumbles.

22 And whoever has received the seed among thorns, this is he who hears the word, but the cares of this age and the falseness of riches suffocate the word, and he is effectively without fruit.

23 Yet truly, whoever has received the seed into good soil, this is he who hears the word, and understands it, and so he bears fruit, and he produces: some a hundred fold, and another sixty fold, and another thirty fold."

24 He proposed another parable to them, saying: "The kingdom of heaven is like a man who sowed good seed in his field.

25 But while the men were sleeping, his enemy came and sowed weeds amid the wheat, and then went away.

26 And when the plants had grown, and had produced fruit, then the weeds also appeared.

27 So the servants of the Father of the family, approaching, said to him: 'Lord, did you not sow good seed in your field? Then how is it that it has weeds?'

28 And he said to them, 'A man who is an enemy has done this.' So the servants said to him, 'Is it your will that we should go and gather them up?'

29 And he said: 'No, lest perhaps in gathering the weeds, you might also root out the wheat together with it.

30 Permit both to grow until the harvest, and at the time of the harvest, I will say to the reapers: Gather first the weeds, and bind them into bundles to burn, but the wheat gather into my storehouse.' "

31 He proposed another parable to them, saying: "The kingdom of heaven is like a grain of mustard seed, which a man took and sowed in his field.

32 It is, indeed, the least of all seeds, but when it has grown, it is greater than all the plants, and it becomes a tree, so much so that the birds of the air come and dwell in its branches."

33 He spoke another parable to them: "The kingdom of heaven is like leaven, which a woman took and hid in three measures of fine wheat flour, until it was entirely leavened."

34 All these things Jesus spoke in parables to the crowds. And he did not speak to them apart from parables,

35 in order to fulfill what was spoken through the prophet, saying: "I will open my mouth in parables. I will proclaim what has been hidden since the foundation of the world."

36 Then, dismissing the crowds, he went into the house. And his disciples drew near to him, saying, "Explain to us the parable of the weeds in the field."

37 Responding, he said to them: "He who sows the good seed is the Son of man.

38 Now the field is the world. And the good seeds are the sons of the kingdom. But the weeds are the sons of wickedness.

39 So the enemy who sowed them is the devil. And truly, the harvest is the consummation of the age; while the reapers are the Angels.

40 Therefore, just as weeds are gathered up and burned with fire, so shall it be at the consummation of the age.

41 The Son of man shall send out his Angels, and they shall gather from his kingdom all who lead astray and those who work iniquity.

42 And he shall cast them into the furnace of fire, where there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth.

43 Then the just ones shall shine like the sun, in the kingdom of their Father. Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear.

44 The kingdom of heaven is like a treasure hidden in a field. When a man finds it, he hides it, and, because of his joy, he goes and sells everything that he has, and he buys that field.

45 Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a merchant seeking good pearls.

46 Having found one pearl of great value, he went away and sold all that he had, and he bought it.

47 Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a net cast into the sea, which gathers together all kinds of fish.

48 When it has been filled, drawing it out and sitting beside the shore, they selected the good into vessels, but the bad they threw away.

49 So shall it be at the consummation of the age. The Angels shall go forth and separate the bad from the midst of the just.

50 And they shall cast them into the furnace of fire, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.

51 Have you understood all these things?" They say to him, "Yes."

52 He said to them, "Therefore, every scribe well-taught about the kingdom of heaven, is like a man, the father of a family, who offers from his storehouse both the new and the old."

53 And it happened that, when Jesus had completed these parables, he went away from there.

54 And arriving in his own country, he taught them in their synagogues, so much so that they wondered and said: "How can such wisdom and power be with this one?

55 Is this not the son of a workman? Is not his mother called Mary, and his brothers, James, and Joseph, and Simon, and Jude?

56 And his sisters, are they not all with us? Therefore, from where has this one obtained all these things?"

57 And they took offense at him. But Jesus said to them, "A prophet is not without honor, except in his own country and in his own house."

58 And he did not work many miracles there, because of their unbelief.

Matthew 14

1 In that time, Herod the Tetrarch heard the news about Jesus.

2 And he said to his servants: "This is John the Baptist. He has risen from the dead, and that is why miracles are at work in him."

3 For Herod had apprehended John, and bound him, and put him in prison, because of Herodias, the wife of his brother.

4 For John was telling him, "It is not lawful for you to have her."

5 And though he wanted to kill him, he feared the people, because they held him to be a prophet.

6 Then, on Herod's birthday, the daughter of Herodias danced in their midst, and it pleased Herod.

7 And so he promised with an oath to give her whatever she would ask of him.

8 But, having been advised by her mother, she said, "Give me here, on a platter, the head of John the Baptist."

9 And the king was greatly saddened. But because of his oath, and because of those who sat at table with him, he ordered it to be given.

10 And he sent and beheaded John in prison.

11 And his head was brought on a platter, and it was given to the girl, and she brought it to her mother.

12 And his disciples approached and took the body, and they buried it. And arriving, they reported it to Jesus.

13 When Jesus had heard it, he withdrew from there by boat, to a deserted place by himself. And when the crowds had heard of it, they followed him on foot from the cities.

14 And going out, he saw a great multitude, and he took pity on them, and he cured their sick.

15 And when evening had arrived, his disciples approached him, saying: "This is a deserted place, and the hour has now passed. Dismiss the crowds, so that, by going into the towns, they may buy food for themselves."

16 But Jesus said to them: "They have no need to go. Give them something to eat yourselves."

17 They answered him, "We have nothing here, except five loaves and two fish."

18 He said to them, "Bring them here to me."

19 And when he had ordered the multitude to sit down upon the grass, he took the five loaves and the two fish, and gazing up to heaven, he blessed and broke and gave the bread to the disciples, and then the disciples to the multitudes.

20 And they all ate and were satisfied. And they took up the remnants: twelve baskets full of fragments.

21 Now the number of those who ate was five thousand men, besides women and children.

22 And Jesus promptly compelled his disciples to climb into the boat, and to precede him in crossing the sea, while he dismissed the crowds.

23 And having dismissed the multitude, he ascended alone onto a mountain to pray. And when evening arrived, he was alone there.

24 But in the midst of the sea, the boat was being tossed about by the waves. For the wind was against them.

25 Then, in the fourth watch of the night, he came to them, walking upon the sea.

26 And seeing him walking upon the sea, they were disturbed, saying: "It must be an apparition." And they cried out, because of fear.

27 And immediately, Jesus spoke to them, saying: "Have faith. It is I. Do not be afraid."

28 Then Peter responded by saying, "Lord, if it is you, order me come to you over the waters."

29 And he said, "Come." And Peter, descending from the boat, walked over the water, so as to go to Jesus.

30 Yet truly, seeing that the wind was strong, he was afraid. And as he began to sink, he cried out, saying: "Lord, save me."

31 And immediately Jesus extended his hand and took hold of him. And he said to him, "O little in faith, why did you doubt?"

32 And when they had ascended into the boat, the wind ceased.

33 Then those who were in the boat drew near and adored him, saying: "Truly, you are the Son of God."

34 And having crossed the sea, they arrived in the land of Genesaret.

35 And when the men of that place had recognized him, they sent into all that region, and they brought to him all who had maladies.

36 And they petitioned him, so that they might touch even the hem of his garment. And as many as touched it were made whole.

Matthew 15

1 Then the scribes and the Pharisees came to him from Jerusalem, saying:

2 "Why do your disciples transgress the tradition of the elders? For they do not wash their hands when they eat bread."

3 But responding, he said to them: "And why do you transgress the commandment of God for the sake of your tradition? For God said:

4 'Honor your father and mother,' and, 'Whoever will have cursed father or mother shall die a death.'

5 But you say: 'If anyone will have said to father or mother, "It is dedicated, so that whatever is from me will benefit you,"

6 then he shall not honor his father or his mother.' So have you nullified the commandment of God, for the sake of your tradition.

7 Hypocrites! How well did Isaiah prophesy about you, saying:

8 'This people honors me with their lips, but their heart is far from me.

9 For in vain do they worship me, teaching the doctrines and commandments of men.' "

10 And having called the multitudes to him, he said to them: "Listen and understand.

11 A man is not defiled by what enters into the mouth, but by what proceeds from the mouth. This is what defiles a man."

12 Then his disciples drew near and said to him, "Do you know that the Pharisees, upon hearing this word, were offended?"

13 But in response he said: "Every plant which has not been planted by my heavenly Father shall be uprooted.

14 Leave them alone. They are blind, and they lead the blind. But if the blind are in charge of the blind, both will fall into the pit."

15 And responding, Peter said to him, "Explain this parable to us."

16 But he said: "Are you, even now, without understanding?

17 Do you not understand that everything that enters into the mouth goes into the gut, and is cast into the sewer?

18 But what proceeds from the mouth, goes forth from the heart, and those are the things that defile a man.

19 For from the heart go out evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, thefts, false testimonies, blasphemies.

20 These are the things that defile a man. But to eat without washing hands does not defile a man."

21 And departing from there, Jesus withdrew into the areas of Tyre and Sidon.

22 And behold, a woman of Canaan, going out from those parts, cried out, saying to him: "Take pity on me, Lord, Son of David. My daughter is badly afflicted by a demon."

23 He did not say a word to her. And his disciples, drawing near, petitioned him, saying: "Dismiss her, for she is crying out after us."

24 And responding, he said, "I was not sent except to the sheep who have fallen away from the house of Israel."

25 But she approached and adored him, saying, "Lord, help me."

26 And responding, he said, "It is not good to take the bread of the children and cast it to the dogs."

27 But she said, "Yes, Lord, but the young dogs also eat from the crumbs that fall from the table of their masters."

28 Then Jesus, responding, said to her: "O woman, great is your faith. Let it be done for you just as you wish." And her daughter was healed from that very hour.

29 And when Jesus had passed from there, he arrived beside the sea of Galilee. And ascending onto a mountain, he sat down there.

30 And great multitudes came to him, having with them the mute, the blind, the lame, the disabled, and many others. And they cast them down at his feet, and he cured them,

31 so much so that the crowds wondered, seeing the mute speaking, the lame walking, the blind seeing. And they magnified the God of Israel.

32 And Jesus, calling together his disciples, said: "I have compassion on the crowds, because they have persevered with me now for three days, and they do not have anything to eat. And I am not willing to dismiss them, fasting, lest they faint along the way."

33 And the disciples said to him: "From where, then, in the desert, would we obtain enough bread to satisfy so a great multitude?"

34 And Jesus said to them, "How many loaves of bread do you have?" But they said, "Seven, and a few little fish."

35 And he instructed the crowds to recline upon the ground.

36 And taking the seven loaves and the fish, and giving thanks, he broke and gave to his disciples, and the disciples gave to the people.

37 And they all ate and were satisfied. And, from what was left over of the fragments, they took up seven full baskets.

38 But those who ate were four thousand men, plus children and women.

39 And having dismissed the crowd, he climbed into a boat. And he went into the coastal region of Magadan.

Matthew 16

1 And Pharisees and Sadducees approached him to test him, and they asked him to show them a sign from heaven.

2 But he responded by saying to them: "When evening arrives, you say, 'It will be calm, for the sky is red,'

3 and in the morning, 'Today there will be a storm, for the sky is red and gloomy.' So then, you know how to judge the appearance of the sky, but you are unable to know the signs of the times?

4 An evil and adulterous generation seeks a sign. And a sign shall not be given to it, except the sign of the prophet Jonah." And leaving them behind, he went away.

5 And when his disciples went across the sea, they forgot to bring bread.

6 And he said to them, "Consider and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and the Sadducees."

7 But they were thinking within themselves, saying, "It is because we have not brought bread."

8 Then Jesus, knowing this, said: "Why do you consider within yourselves, O little in faith, that it is because you have no bread?

9 Do you not yet understand, nor remember, the five loaves among the five thousand men, and how many containers you took up?

10 Or the seven loaves among the four thousand men, and how many baskets you took up?

11 Why do you not understand that it was not because of bread that I said to you: Beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and the Sadducees?"

12 Then they understood that he was not saying that they should beware of the leaven of bread, but of the doctrine of the Pharisees and the Sadducees.

13 Then Jesus went into parts of Caesarea Philippi. And he questioned his disciples, saying, "Who do men say that the Son of man is?"

14 And they said, "Some say John the Baptist, and others say Elijah, still others say Jeremiah or one of the prophets."

15 Jesus said to them, "But who do you say that I am?"

16 Simon Peter responded by saying, "You are the Christ, the Son of the living God."

17 And in response, Jesus said to him: "Blessed are you, Simon son of Jonah. For flesh and blood has not revealed this to you, but my Father, who is in heaven.

18 And I say to you, that you are Peter, and upon this rock I will build my Church, and the gates of Hell shall not prevail against it.

19 And I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven. And whatever you shall bind on earth shall be bound, even in heaven. And whatever you shall release on earth shall be released, even in heaven."

20 Then he instructed his disciples that they should tell no one that he is Jesus the Christ.

21 From that time, Jesus began to reveal to his disciples that it was necessary for him to go to Jerusalem, and to suffer much from the elders and the scribes and the leaders of the priests, and to be killed, and to rise again on the third day.

22 And Peter, taking him aside, began to rebuke him, saying, "Lord, may it be far from you; this shall not happen to you."

23 And turning away, Jesus said to Peter: "Get behind me, Satan; you are an obstacle to me. For you are not behaving according to what is of God, but according to what is of men."

24 Then Jesus said to his disciples: "If anyone is willing to come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me.

25 For whoever would save his life, will lose it. But whoever will have lost his life for my sake, shall find it.

26 For how does it benefit a man, if he gains the whole world, yet truly suffers damage to his soul? Or what shall a man give in exchange for his soul?

27 For the Son of man will arrive in the glory of his Father, with his Angels. And then he will repay each one according to his works.

28 Amen I say to you, there are some among those standing here, who shall not taste death, until they see the Son of man arriving in his reign."

Matthew 17

1 And after six days, Jesus took Peter and James and his brother John, and he led them onto a lofty mountain separately.

2 And he was transfigured before them. And his face shined brightly like the sun. And his garments were made white like snow.

3 And behold, there appeared to them Moses and Elijah, speaking with him.

4 And Peter responded by saying to Jesus: "Lord, it is good for us to be here. If you are willing, let us make three tabernacles here, one for you, one for Moses, and one for Elijah."

5 And while he was still speaking, behold, a shining cloud overshadowed them. And behold, there was a voice from the cloud, saying: "This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased. Listen to him."

6 And the disciples, hearing this, fell prone on their face, and they were very afraid.

7 And Jesus drew near and touched them. And he said to them, "Rise up and do not be afraid."

8 And lifting up their eyes, they saw no one, except Jesus alone.

9 And as they were descending from the mountain, Jesus instructed them, saying, "Tell no one about the vision, until the Son of man has risen from the dead."

10 And his disciples questioned him, saying, "Why then do the scribes say that it is necessary for Elijah to arrive first?"

11 But in response, he said to them: "Elijah, indeed, shall arrive and restore all things.

12 But I say to you, that Elijah has already arrived, and they did not recognize him, but they did whatever they wanted to him. So also shall the Son of man suffer from them."

13 Then the disciples understood that he had spoken to them about John the Baptist.

14 And when he had arrived at the multitude, a man approached him, falling to his knees before him, saying: "Lord, take pity on my son, for he is an epileptic, and he suffers harm. For he frequently falls into fire, and often also into water.

15 And I brought him to your disciples, but they were not able to cure him."

16 Then Jesus responded by saying: "What an unbelieving and perverse generation! How long shall I be with you? How long shall I endure you? Bring him here to me."

17 And Jesus rebuked him, and the demon went out of him, and the boy was cured from that hour.

18 Then the disciples approached Jesus privately and said, "Why were we unable to cast him out?"

19 Jesus said to them: "Because of your unbelief. Amen I say to you, certainly, if you will have faith like a grain of mustard seed, you will say to this mountain, 'Move from here to there,' and it shall move. And nothing will be impossible for you.

20 But this kind is not cast out, except through prayer and fasting."

21 And when they were conversing together in Galilee, Jesus said to them: "The Son of man shall be delivered into the hands of men.

22 And they will kill him, but he will rise again on the third day." And they were extremely saddened.

23 And when they had arrived at Capernaum, those who collected the half shekel approached Peter, and they said to him, "Doesn't your Teacher pay the half shekel?"

24 He said, "Yes." And when he had entered into the house, Jesus went before him, saying: "How does it seem to you, Simon? The kings of the earth, from whom do they receive tribute or the census tax: from their own sons or from foreigners?"

25 And he said, "From foreigners." Jesus said to him: "Then the sons are free.

26 But so that we may not become an obstacle to them: go to the sea, and cast in a hook, and take the first fish that is brought up, and when you have opened its mouth, you will find a shekel. Take it and give it to them, for me and for you."

Matthew 18

1 In that hour, the disciples drew near to Jesus, saying, "Whom do you consider to be greater in the kingdom of heaven?"

2 And Jesus, calling to himself a little child, placed him in their midst.

3 And he said: "Amen I say to you, unless you change and become like little children, you shall not enter into the kingdom of heaven.

4 Therefore, whoever will have humbled himself like this little child, such a one is greater in the kingdom of heaven.

5 And whoever shall accept one such little child in my name, accepts me.

6 But whoever will have led astray one of these little ones, who trust in me, it would be better for him to have a great millstone hung around his neck, and to be submerged in the depths of the sea.

7 Woe to a world that leads people astray! Although it is necessary for temptations to arise, nevertheless: Woe to that man through whom temptation arises!

8 So if your hand or your foot leads you to sin, cut it off and cast it away from you. It is better for you to enter into life disabled or lame, than to be sent into eternal fire having two hands or two feet.

9 And if your eye leads you to sin, root it out and cast it away from you. It is better for you to enter into life with one eye, than to be sent into the fires of Hell having two eyes.

10 See to it that you do not despise even one of these little ones. For I say to you, that their Angels in heaven continually look upon the face of my Father, who is in heaven.

11 For the Son of man has come to save what had been lost.

12 How does it seem to you? If someone has one hundred sheep, and if one of them has gone astray, should he not leave behind the ninety-nine in the mountains, and go out to seek what has gone astray?

13 And if he should happen to find it: Amen I say to you, that he has more joy over that one, than over the ninety-nine which did not go astray.

14 Even so, it is not the will before your Father, who is in heaven, that one of these little ones should be lost.

15 But if your brother has sinned against you, go and correct him, between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you will have regained your brother.

16 But if he will not listen you, invite with you one or two more, so that every word may stand by the mouth of two or three witnesses.

17 And if he will not listen to them, tell the Church. But if he will not listen to the Church, let him be to you like the pagan and the tax collector.

18 Amen I say to you, whatever you will have bound on earth, shall be bound also in heaven, and whatever you will have released on earth, shall be released also in heaven.

19 Again I say to you, that if two of those among you have agreed on earth, about anything whatsoever that they have requested, it shall be done for them by my Father, who is in heaven.

20 For wherever two or three are gathered in my name, there am I, in their midst."

21 Then Peter, drawing near to him, said: "Lord, how many times shall my brother sin against me, and I forgive him? Even seven times?"

22 Jesus said to him: "I do not say to you, even seven times, but even seventy times seven times.

23 Therefore, the kingdom of heaven is compared to a man who was king, who wanted to take account of his servants.

24 And when he had begun taking account, one was brought to him who owed him ten thousand talents.

25 But since he did not have any way to repay it, his lord ordered him to be sold, with his wife and children, and all that he had, in order to repay it.

26 But that servant, falling prostrate, begged him, saying, 'Have patience with me, and I will repay it all to you.'

27 Then the lord of that servant, being moved with pity, released him, and he forgave his debt.

28 But when that servant departed, he found one of his fellow servants who owed him one hundred denarius. And taking hold of him, he choked him, saying: 'Repay what you owe.'

29 And his fellow servant, falling prostrate, petitioned him, saying: 'Have patience with me, and I will repay it all to you.'

30 But he was not willing. Instead, he went out and had him sent to prison, until he would repay the debt.

31 Now his fellow servants, seeing what was done, were greatly saddened, and they went and reported to their lord all that was done.

32 Then his lord called him, and he said to him: 'You wicked servant, I forgave you all your debt, because you pleaded with me.

33 Therefore, should you not also have had compassion on your fellow servant, just as I also had compassion on you?'

34 And his lord, being angry, handed him over to the torturers, until he repaid the entire debt.

35 So, too, shall my heavenly Father do to you, if each one of you will not forgive his brother from your hearts."

Matthew 19

1 And it happened that, when Jesus had completed these words, he moved away from Galilee, and he arrived within the borders of Judea, across the Jordan.

2 And great crowds followed him, and he healed them there.

3 And the Pharisees approached him, testing him, and saying, "Is it lawful for a man to separate from his wife, no matter what the cause?"

4 And he said to them in response, "Have you not read that he who made man from the beginning, made them male and female?" And he said:

5 "For this reason, a man shall separate from father and mother, and he shall cling to his wife, and these two shall become one flesh.

6 And so, now they are not two, but one flesh. Therefore, what God has joined together, let no man separate."

7 They said to him, "Then why did Moses command him to give a bill of divorce, and to separate?"

8 He said to them: "Although Moses permitted you to separate from your wives, due to the hardness of your heart, it was not that way from the beginning.

9 And I say to you, that whoever will have separated from his wife, except because of fornication, and who will have married another, commits adultery, and whoever will have married her who has been separated, commits adultery."

10 His disciples said to him, "If such is the case for a man with a wife, then it is not expedient to marry."

11 And he said to them: "Not everyone is able to grasp this word, but only those to whom it has been given.

12 For there are chaste persons who were born so from their mother's womb, and there are chaste persons who have been made so by men, and there are chaste persons who have made themselves chaste for the sake of the kingdom of heaven. Whoever is able to grasp this, let him grasp it."

13 Then they brought to him little children, so that he would place his hands upon them and pray. But the disciples rebuked them.

14 Yet truly, Jesus said to them: "Allow the little children to come to me, and do not choose to prohibit them. For the kingdom of heaven is among such as these."

15 And when he had imposed his hands upon them, he went away from there.

16 And behold, someone approached and said to him, "Good Teacher, what good should I do, so that I may have eternal life?"

17 And he said to him: "Why do you question me about what is good? One is good: God. But if you wish to enter into life, observe the commandments."

18 He said to him, "Which?" And Jesus said: "You shall not murder. You shall not commit adultery. You shall not steal. You shall not give false testimony.

19 Honor your father and your mother. And, you shall love your neighbor as yourself."

20 The young man said to him: "All these I have kept from my childhood. What is still lacking for me?"

21 Jesus said to him: "If you are willing to be perfect, go, sell what you have, and give to the poor, and then you will have treasure in heaven. And come, follow me."

22 And when the young man had heard this word, he went away sad, for he had many possessions.

23 Then Jesus said to his disciples: "Amen, I say to you, that the wealthy shall enter with difficulty into the kingdom of heaven.

24 And again I say to you, it is easier for a camel to pass through the eye of a needle, than for the wealthy to enter into the kingdom of heaven."

25 And upon hearing this, the disciples wondered greatly, saying: "Then who will be able to be saved?"

26 But Jesus, gazing at them, said to them: "With men, this is impossible. But with God, all things are possible."

27 Then Peter responded by saying to him: "Behold, we have left behind all things, and we have followed you. So then, what will be for us?"

28 And Jesus said to them: "Amen I say to you, that at the resurrection, when the Son of man shall sit on the seat of his majesty, those of you who have followed me shall also sit on twelve seats, judging the twelve tribes of Israel.

29 And anyone who has left behind home, or brothers, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or land, for the sake of my name, shall receive one hundred times more, and shall possess eternal life.

30 But many of those who are first shall be last, and the last shall be first."

Matthew 20

1 "The kingdom of heaven is like the father of a family who went out in early morning to lead workers into his vineyard.

2 Then, having made an agreement with the workers for one denarius per day, he sent them into his vineyard.

3 And going out about the third hour, he saw others standing idle in the marketplace.

4 And he said to them, 'You may go into my vineyard, too, and what I will give you will be just.'

5 So they went forth. But again, he went out about the sixth, and about the ninth hour, and he acted similarly.

6 Yet truly, about the eleventh hour, he went out and found others standing, and he said to them, 'Why have you stood here idle all day?'

7 They say to him, 'Because no one has hired us.' He said to them, 'You also may go into my vineyard.'

8 And when evening had arrived, the lord of the vineyard said to his manager, 'Call the workers and pay them their wages, beginning from the last, even to the first.'

9 And so, when those who had arrived about the eleventh hour came forward, each received a single denarius.

10 Then when the first ones also came forward, they considered that they would receive more. But they, too, received one denarius.

11 And upon receiving it, they murmured against the father of the family,

12 saying, 'These last have worked for one hour, and you have made them equal to us, who worked bearing the weight and heat of the day.'

13 But responding to one of them, he said: 'Friend, I caused you no injury. Did you not agree with me to one denarius?

14 Take what is yours and go. But it is my will to give to this last, just as to you.

15 And is it not lawful for me to do what I will? Or is your eye wicked because I am good?'

16 So then, the last shall be first, and the first shall be last. For many are called, but few are chosen."

17 And Jesus, ascending to Jerusalem, took the twelve disciples aside in private and said to them:

18 "Behold, we are ascending to Jerusalem, and the Son of man shall be handed over to the leaders of the priests and to the scribes. And they shall condemn him to death.

19 And they shall hand him over to the Gentiles to be mocked and scourged and crucified. And on the third day, he shall rise again."

20 Then the mother of the sons of Zebedee approached him, with her sons, adoring him, and petitioning something from him.

21 And he said to her, "What do you want?" She said to him, "Declare that these, my two sons, may sit, one at your right hand, and the other at your left, in your kingdom."

22 But Jesus, responding, said: "You do not know what you are asking. Are you able to drink from the chalice, from which I will drink?" They said to him, "We are able."

23 He said to them: "From my chalice, indeed, you shall drink. But to sit at my right or my left is not mine to give to you, but it is for those for whom it has been prepared by my Father."

24 And the ten, upon hearing this, became indignant with the two brothers.

25 But Jesus called them to himself and said: "You know that the first ones among the Gentiles are their rulers, and that those who are greater exercise power among them.

26 It shall not be this way among you. But whoever will want to be greater among you, let him be your minister.

27 And whoever will want to be first among you, he shall be your servant,

28 even as the Son of man has not come to be served, but to serve, and to give his life as a redemption for many."

29 And as they were departing from Jericho, a great crowd followed him.

30 And behold, two blind men, sitting by the way, heard that Jesus was passing by; and they cried out, saying, "Lord, Son of David, take pity on us."

31 But the crowd rebuked them to be quiet. But they cried out all the more, saying, "Lord, Son of David, take pity on us."

32 And Jesus stood still, and he called them and said, "What do you want, that I might do for you?"

33 They said to him, "Lord, that our eyes be opened."

34 Then Jesus, taking pity on them, touched their eyes. And immediately they saw, and they followed him.

Matthew 21

1 And when they had drawn near to Jerusalem, and had arrived at Bethphage, at the Mount of Olives, then Jesus sent two disciples,

2 saying to them: "Go into the town that is opposite you, and immediately you will find a donkey tied, and a colt with her. Release them, and lead them to me.

3 And if anyone will have said anything to you, say that the Lord has need of them. And he will promptly dismiss them."

4 Now all this was done in order to fulfill what was spoken through the prophet, saying,

5 "Tell the daughter of Zion: Behold, your king comes to you meekly, sitting on a donkey and on a colt, the son of one accustomed to the yoke."

6 Then the disciples, going out, did just as Jesus instructed them.

7 And they brought the donkey and the colt, and they laid their garments on them, and they helped him sit upon them.

8 Then a very numerous crowd spread their garments on the way. But others cut branches from the trees and scattered them on the way.

9 And the crowds that preceded him, and those that followed, cried out, saying: "Hosanna to the Son of David! Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord. Hosanna in the highest!"

10 And when he had entered into Jerusalem, the entire city was stirred up, saying, "Who is this?"

11 But the people were saying, "This is Jesus, the Prophet from Nazareth of Galilee."

12 And Jesus entered into the temple of God, and he cast out all who were selling and buying in the temple, and he overturned the tables of the money changers and the chairs of the vendors of doves.

13 And he said to them: "It is written: 'My house shall be called a house of prayer. But you have made it into a den of robbers.' "

14 And the blind and the lame drew near to him in the temple; and he healed them.

15 Then the leaders of the priests and the scribes became indignant, seeing the miracles that he wrought, and the children crying out in the temple, saying, "Hosanna to the Son of David!"

16 And they said to him, "Do you hear what these ones are saying?" But Jesus said to them, "Certainly. Have you never read: For out of the mouth of babes and infants, you have perfected praise?"

17 And leaving them behind, he went out, beyond the city, into Bethania, and he lodged here.

18 Then, as he was returning to the city in the morning, he was hungry.

19 And seeing a certain fig tree beside the way, he approached it. And he found nothing on it, except only leaves. And he said to it, "May fruit never spring forth from you, for all time." And immediately the fig tree was dried up.

20 And seeing this, the disciples wondered, saying, "How did it dry up so quickly?"

21 And Jesus responded to them by saying: "Amen I say to you, if you have faith and do not hesitate, not only shall you do this, concerning the fig tree, but even if you would say to this mountain, 'Take and cast yourself into the sea,' it shall be done.

22 And all things whatsoever that you shall ask for in prayer: believing, you shall receive."

23 And when he had arrived at the temple, as he was teaching, the leaders of the priests and the elders of the people approached him, saying: "By what authority do you do these things? And who has given this authority to you?"

24 In response, Jesus said to them: "I also will question you with one word: if you tell me this, I also will tell you by what authority I do these things.

25 The baptism of John, where was it from? Was it from heaven, or from men?" But they thought within themselves, saying:

26 "If we say, 'From heaven,' he will say to us, 'Then why did you not believe him?' But if we say, 'From men,' we have the crowd to fear, for they all hold John to be a prophet."

27 And so, they answered Jesus by saying, "We do not know." So he also said to them: "Neither will I tell you by what authority I do these things.

28 But how does it seem to you? A certain man had two sons. And approaching the first, he said: 'Son, go out today to work in my vineyard.'

29 And responding, he said, 'I am not willing.' But afterwards, being moved by repentance, he went.

30 And approaching the other, he spoke similarly. And answering, he said, 'I am going, lord.' And he did not go.

31 Which of the two did the will of the father?" They said to him, "The first." Jesus said to them: "Amen I say to you, that tax collectors and prostitutes shall precede you, into the kingdom of God.

32 For John came to you in the way of justice, and you did not believe him. But the tax collectors and the prostitutes believed him. Yet even after seeing this, you did not repent, so as to believe him.

33 Listen to another parable. There was a man, the father of a family, who planted a vineyard, and surrounded it with a hedge, and dug a press in it, and built a tower. And he loaned it out to farmers, and he set out to sojourn abroad.

34 Then, when the time of the fruits drew near, he sent his servants to the farmers, so that they might receive its fruits.

35 And the farmers apprehended his servants; they struck one, and killed another, and stoned yet another.

36 Again, he sent other servants, more than before; and they treated them similarly.

37 Then, at the very end, he sent his son to them, saying: 'They will revere my son.'

38 But the farmers, seeing the son, said among themselves: 'This is the heir. Come, let us kill him, and then we will have his inheritance.'

39 And apprehending him, they cast him outside the vineyard, and they killed him.

40 Therefore, when the lord of the vineyard arrives, what will he do to those farmers?"

41 They said to him, "He will bring those evil men to an evil end, and he will loan out his vineyard to other farmers, who shall repay to him the fruit in its time."

42 Jesus said to them: "Have you never read in the Scriptures: 'The stone that the builders have rejected has become the cornerstone. By the Lord has this been done, and it is wonderful in our eyes?'

43 Therefore, I say to you, that the kingdom of God will be taken away from you, and it shall be given to a people who shall produce its fruits.

44 And whoever will have fallen on this stone shall be broken, yet truly, on whomever it shall fall, it will crush him."

45 And when the leaders of the priests, and the Pharisees had heard his parables, they knew that he was speaking about them.

46 And though they sought to take hold of him, they feared the crowds, because they held him to be a prophet.

Matthew 22

1 And responding, Jesus again spoke to them in parables, saying:

2 "The kingdom of heaven is like a man who was king, who celebrated a wedding for his son.

3 And he sent his servants to call those who were invited to the wedding. But they were not willing to come.

4 Again, he sent other servants, saying, 'Tell the invited: Behold, I have prepared my meal. My bulls and fatlings have been killed, and all is ready. Come to the wedding.'

5 But they ignored this and they went away: one to his country estate, and another to his business.

6 Yet truly, the rest took hold of his servants and, having treated them with contempt, killed them.

7 But when the king heard this, he was angry. And sending out his armies, he destroyed those murderers, and he burned their city.

8 Then he said to his servants: 'The wedding, indeed, has been prepared. But those who were invited were not worthy.

9 Therefore, go out to the ways, and call whomever you will find to the wedding.'

10 And his servants, departing into the ways, gathered all those whom they found, bad and good, and the wedding was filled with guests.

11 Then the king entered to see the guests. And he saw a man there who was not clothed in a wedding garment.

12 And he said to him, 'Friend, how is it that you have entered here without having a wedding garment?' But he was dumbstruck.

13 Then the king said to the ministers: 'Bind his hands and feet, and cast him into the outer darkness, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.

14 For many are called, but few are chosen.' "

15 Then the Pharisees, going out, took counsel as to how they might entrap him in speech.

16 And they sent their disciples to him, with the Herodians, saying: "Teacher, we know that you are truthful, and that you teach the way of God in truth, and that the influence of others is nothing to you. For you do not consider the reputation of men.

17 Therefore, tell us, how does it seem to you? Is it lawful to pay the census tax to Caesar, or not?"

18 But Jesus, knowing their wickedness, said: "Why do you test me, you hypocrites?

19 Show me the coin of the census tax." And they offered him a denarius.

20 And Jesus said to them, "Whose image is this, and whose inscription?"

21 They said to him, "Caesar's." Then he said to them, "Then render to Caesar what is of Caesar; and to God what is of God."

22 And hearing this, they wondered. And having left him behind, they went away.

23 In that day, the Sadducees, who say there is to be no resurrection, approached him. And they questioned him,

24 saying: "Teacher, Moses said: If anyone will have died, having no son, his brother shall marry his wife, and he shall raise up offspring to his brother.

25 Now there were seven brothers with us. And the first, having taken a wife, died. And having no offspring, he left his wife to his brother:

26 similarly with the second, and the third, even to the seventh.

27 And last of all, the woman also passed away.

28 In the resurrection, then, whose wife of the seven will she be? For they all had her."

29 But Jesus responded to them by saying: "You have gone astray by knowing neither the Scriptures, nor the power of God.

30 For in the resurrection, they shall neither marry, nor be given in marriage. Instead, they shall be like the Angels of God in heaven.

31 But concerning the resurrection of the dead, have you not read what was spoken by God, saying to you:

32 'I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob?' He is not the God of the dead, but of the living."

33 And when the crowds heard this, they wondered at his doctrine.

34 But the Pharisees, hearing that he had caused the Sadducees to be silent, came together as one.

35 And one of them, a doctor of the law, questioned him, to test him:

36 "Teacher, which is the great commandment in the law?"

37 Jesus said to him: " 'You shall love the Lord your God from all your heart, and with all your soul and with all your mind.'

38 This is the greatest and first commandment.

39 But the second is similar to it: 'You shall love your neighbor as yourself.'

40 On these two commandments the entire law depends, and also the prophets."

41 Then, when the Pharisees were gathered together, Jesus questioned them,

42 saying: "What do you think about the Christ? Whose son is he?" They said to him, "David's."

43 He said to them: "Then how can David, in the Spirit, call him Lord, saying:

44 'The Lord said to my Lord: Sit at my right hand, until I make your enemies your footstool?'

45 So then, if David calls him Lord, how can he be his son?"

46 And no one was able to respond to him a word. And neither did anyone dare, from that day forward, to question him.

Matthew 23

1 Then Jesus spoke to the crowds, and to his disciples,

2 saying: "The scribes and the Pharisees have sat down in the chair of Moses.

3 Therefore, all things whatsoever that they shall say to you, observe and do. Yet truly, do not choose to act according to their works. For they say, but they do not do.

4 For they bind up heavy and unbearable burdens, and they impose them on men's shoulders. But they are not willing to move them with even a finger of their own.

5 Truly, they do all their works so that they may be seen by men. For they enlarge their phylacteries and glorify their hems.

6 And they love the first places at feasts, and the first chairs in the synagogues,

7 and greetings in the marketplace, and to be called Master by men.

8 But you must not be called Master. For One is your Master, and you are all brothers.

9 And do not choose to call anyone on earth your father. For One is your Father, who is in heaven.

10 Neither should you be called teachers. For One is your Teacher, the Christ.

11 Whoever is greater among you shall be your minister.

12 But whoever has exalted himself, shall be humbled. And whoever has humbled himself, shall be exalted.

13 So then: Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, you hypocrites! For you close the kingdom of heaven before men. For you yourselves do not enter, and those who are entering, you would not permit to enter.

14 Woe to you scribes and Pharisees, you hypocrites! For you consume the houses of widows, praying long prayers. Because of this, you shall receive the greater judgment.

15 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, you hypocrites! For you travel around by sea and by land, in order to make one convert. And when he has been converted, you make him twice the son of Hell that you are yourselves.

16 Woe to you, blind guides, who say: 'Whoever will have sworn by the temple, it is nothing. But whoever will have sworn by the gold of the temple is obligated.'

17 You are foolish and blind! For which is greater: the gold, or the temple that sanctifies the gold?

18 And you say: 'Whoever will have sworn by the altar, it is nothing. But whoever will have sworn by the gift that is on the altar is obligated.'

19 How blind you are! For which is greater: the gift, or the altar that sanctifies the gift?

20 Therefore, whoever swears by the altar, swears by it, and by all that is on it.

21 And whoever will have sworn by the temple, swears by it, and by him who dwells in it.

22 And whoever swears by heaven, swears by the throne of God, and by him who sits upon it.

23 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, you hypocrites! For you collect tithes on mint and dill and cumin, but you have abandoned the weightier things of the law: judgment and mercy and faith. These you ought to have done, while not omitting the others.

24 You blind guides, straining out a gnat, while swallowing a camel!

25 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, you hypocrites! For you clean what is outside the cup and the dish, but on the inside you are full of avarice and impurity.

26 You blind Pharisee! First clean the inside of the cup and the dish, and then what is outside becomes clean.

27 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, you hypocrites! For you are like whitewashed sepulchers, which outwardly appear brilliant to men, yet truly, inside, they are filled with the bones of the dead and with all filth.

28 So also, you certainly appear to men outwardly to be just. But inwardly you are filled with hypocrisy and iniquity.

29 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, you hypocrites, who build the sepulchers of the prophets and adorn the monuments of the just.

30 And then you say, 'If we had been there in the days of our fathers, we would not have joined with them in the blood of the prophets.'

31 And so you are witnesses against yourselves, that you are the sons of those who killed the prophets.

32 Complete, then, the measure of your fathers.

33 You serpents, you brood of vipers! How will you escape from the judgment of Hell?

34 For this reason, behold, I send to you prophets and wisemen, and scribes. And some of these you will put to death and crucify; and some you will scourge in your synagogues and persecute from city to city,

35 so that upon you may fall all the blood of the just, which has been shed upon the earth, from the blood of Abel the just, even to the blood of Zechariah the son of Barachiah, whom you killed between the temple and the altar.

36 Amen I say to you, all these things shall fall upon this generation.

37 Jerusalem, Jerusalem! You kill the prophets and stone those who have been sent to you. How often I have wanted to gather your children together, in the way that a hen gathers her young under her wings. But you were not willing!

38 Behold, your house shall be abandoned to you, having been deserted.

39 For I say to you, you shall not see me again, until you say: 'Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord.' "

Matthew 24

1 And Jesus departed from the temple and went away. And his disciples approached him, so as to show him the buildings of the temple.

2 But he said to them in response: "Do you see all these things? Amen I say to you, there shall not remain here stone upon stone, which is not torn down."

3 Then, when he was seated at the Mount of Olives, the disciples drew near to him privately, saying: "Tell us, when will these things be? And what will be the sign of your advent and of the consummation of the age?"

4 And answering, Jesus said to them: "Pay attention, lest someone lead you astray.

5 For many will come in my name saying, 'I am the Christ.' And they will lead many astray.

6 For you will hear of battles and rumors of battles. Take care not to be disturbed. For these things must be, but the end is not so soon.

7 For nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom. And there will be pestilences, and famines, and earthquakes in places.

8 But all these things are just the beginning of the sorrows.

9 Then they will hand you over to tribulation, and they will kill you. And you will be hated by all nations for the sake of my name.

10 And then many will be led into sin, and will betray one another, and will have hatred for one another.

11 And many false prophets will arise, and they will lead many astray.

12 And because iniquity has abounded, the charity of many will grow cold.

13 But whoever will have persevered until the end, the same shall be saved.

14 And this Gospel of the kingdom shall be preached throughout the entire world, as a testimony to all nations. And then the consummation will occur.

15 Therefore, when you will have seen the abomination of desolation, which was spoken of by the prophet Daniel, standing in the holy place, may he who reads understand,

16 then those who are in Judea, let them flee to the mountains.

17 And whoever is on the roof, let him not descend to take anything from his house.

18 And whoever is in the field, let him not turn back to take his tunic.

19 So then, woe to those who are pregnant or nursing in those days.

20 But pray that your flight may not be in winter, or on the Sabbath.

21 For then there will be a great tribulation, such as has not been from the beginning of the world until the present, and such as will not be.

22 And unless those days had been shortened, no flesh would be saved. But for the sake of the elect, those days shall be shortened.

23 Then if anyone will have said to you, 'Behold, here is the Christ,' or 'he is there,' do not be willing to believe it.

24 For there will arise false Christs and false prophets. And they will produce great signs and wonders, so much so as to lead into error even the elect (if this could be).

25 Behold, I have warned you beforehand.

26 Therefore, if they will have said to you, 'Behold, he is in the desert,' do not choose to go out, or, 'Behold, he is in the inner rooms,' do not be willing to believe it.

27 For just as lightning goes out from the east, and appears even in the west, so shall it be also at the advent of the Son of man.

28 Wherever the body shall be, there also will the eagles be gathered together.

29 And immediately after the tribulation of those days, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light, and the stars will fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens will be shaken.

30 And then the sign of the Son of man shall appear in heaven. And then all tribes of the earth shall mourn. And they shall see the Son of man coming on the clouds of heaven, with great power and majesty.

31 And he shall send out his Angels with a trumpet and a great voice. And they shall gather together his elect from the four winds, from the heights of the heavens, even to their furthest limits.

32 So, from the fig tree learn a parable. When its branch has now become tender and the leaves have sprung forth, you know that summer is near.

33 So also, when you will have seen all these things, know that it is near, even at the threshold.

34 Amen I say to you, that this lineage shall not pass away, until all these things have been done.

35 Heaven and earth shall pass away, but my words shall not pass away.

36 But concerning that day and hour, no one knows, not even the Angels of the heavens, but only the Father.

37 And just as in the days of Noah, so also will be the advent of the Son of man.

38 For it will be just as it was in the days before the flood: eating and drinking, marrying and being given in marriage, even until that day when Noah entered into the ark.

39 And they did not realize it, until the flood came and took them all away. So also will the advent of the Son of man be.

40 Then two men will be in a field: one will be taken up, and one will be left behind.

41 Two women will be grinding at a millstone: one will be taken up, and one will be left behind.

42 Therefore, be vigilant. For you do not know at what hour your Lord will return.

43 But know this: if only the father of the family knew at what hour the thief would arrive, he would certainly keep vigil and not permit his house to be broken into.

44 For this reason, you also must be prepared, for you do not know at what hour the Son of man will return.

45 Consider this: who is a faithful and prudent servant, who has been appointed by his lord over his family, to give them their portion in due time?

46 Blessed is that servant, if, when his lord has arrived, he shall find him doing so.

47 Amen I say to you, he shall appoint him over all of his goods.

48 But if that evil servant has said in his heart, 'My lord has been delayed in returning,'

49 and so, he begins to strike his fellow servants, and he eats and drinks with the inebriated:

50 then the lord of that servant will arrive on a day that he does not expect, and at an hour that he does not know.

51 And he shall separate him, and he shall place his portion with the hypocrites, where there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth."

Matthew 25

1 "Then the kingdom of heaven shall be like ten virgins, who, taking their lamps, went out to meet the groom and the bride.

2 But five of them were foolish, and five were prudent.

3 For the five foolish, having brought their lamps, did not take oil with them.

4 Yet truly, the prudent ones brought the oil, in their containers, with the lamps.

5 Since the bridegroom was delayed, they all fell asleep, and they were sleeping.

6 But in the middle of the night, a cry went out: 'Behold, the groom is arriving. Go out to meet him.'

7 Then all those virgins rose up and trimmed their lamps.

8 But the foolish ones said to the wise, 'Give to us from your oil, for our lamps are being extinguished.'

9 The prudent responded by saying, 'Lest perhaps there may not be enough for us and for you, it would be better for you to go to the vendors and buy some for yourselves.'

10 But while they were going to buy it, the groom arrived. And those who were prepared entered with him to the wedding, and the door was closed.

11 Yet truly, at the very end, the remaining virgins also arrived, saying, 'Lord, Lord, open to us.'

12 But he responded by saying, 'Amen I say to you, I do not know you.'

13 And so you must be vigilant, because you do not know the day or the hour.

14 For it is like a man setting out on a long journey, who called his servants and delivered to them his goods.

15 And to one he gave five talents, and to another two, yet to another he gave one, to each according to his own ability. And promptly, he set out.

16 Then he who had received five talents went out, and he made use of these, and he gained another five.

17 And similarly, he who had received two gained another two.

18 But he who had received one, going out, dug into the earth, and he hid the money of his lord.

19 Yet truly, after a long time, the lord of those servants returned and he settled accounts with them.

20 And when he who had received five talents approached, he brought another five talents, saying: 'Lord, you delivered five talents to me. Behold, I have increased it by another five.'

21 His lord said to him: 'Well done, good and faithful servant. Since you have been faithful over a few things, I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the gladness of your lord.'

22 Then he who had received two talents also approached, and he said: 'Lord, you delivered two talents to me. Behold, I have gained another two.'

23 His lord said to him: 'Well done, good and faithful servant. Since you have been faithful over a few things, I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the gladness of your lord.'

24 Then he who had received one talent, approaching, said: 'Lord, I know that you are a hard man. You reap where you have not sown, and gather where you have not scattered.

25 And so, being afraid, I went out and hid your talent in the earth. Behold, you have what is yours.'

26 But his lord said to him in response: 'You evil and lazy servant! You knew that I reap where I have not sown, and gather where I have not scattered.

27 Therefore, you should have deposited my money with the bankers, and then, at my arrival, at least I would have received what is mine with interest.

28 And so, take the talent away from him and give it the one who has ten talents.

29 For to everyone who has, more shall be given, and he shall have in abundance. But from him who has not, even what he seems to have, shall be taken away.

30 And cast that useless servant into the outer darkness, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.'

31 But when the Son of man will have arrived in his majesty, and all the Angels with him, then he will sit upon the seat of his majesty.

32 And all the nations shall be gathered together before him. And he shall separate them from one another, just as a shepherd separates the sheep from the goats.

33 And he shall station the sheep, indeed, on his right, but the goats on his left.

34 Then the King shall say to those who will be on his right: 'Come, you blessed of my Father. Possess the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world.

35 For I was hungry, and you gave me to eat; I was thirsty, and you gave me to drink; I was a stranger, and you took me in;

36 naked, and you covered me; sick, and you visited me; I was in prison, and you came to me.'

37 Then the just will answer him, saying: 'Lord, when have we see you hungry, and fed you; thirsty, and given you drink?

38 And when have we seen you a stranger, and taken you in? Or naked, and covered you?

39 Or when did we see you sick, or in prison, and visit to you?'

40 And in response, the King shall say to them, 'Amen I say to you, whenever you did this for one of these, the least of my brothers, you did it for me.'

41 Then he shall also say, to those who will be on his left: 'Depart from me, you accursed ones, into the eternal fire, which was prepared for the devil and his angels.

42 For I was hungry, and you did not give me to eat; I was thirsty, and you did not give me to drink;

43 I was a stranger and you did not take me in; naked, and you did not cover me; sick and in prison, and you did not visit me.'

44 Then they will also answer him, saying: 'Lord, when did we see you hungry, or thirsty, or a stranger, or naked, or sick, or in prison, and did not minister to you?'

45 Then he shall respond to them by saying: 'Amen I say to you, whenever you did not do it to one of these least, neither did you do it to me.'

46 And these shall go into eternal punishment, but the just shall go into eternal life."

Matthew 26

1 And it happened that, when Jesus had completed all these words, he said to his disciples,

2 "You know that after two days the Passover will begin, and the Son of man will be handed over to be crucified."

3 Then the leaders of the priests and the elders of the people were gathered together in the court of the high priest, who was called Caiaphas.

4 And they took counsel so that by deceitfulness they might take hold of Jesus and kill him.

5 But they said, "Not on the feast day, lest perhaps there may be a tumult among the people."

6 And when Jesus was in Bethania, in the house of Simon the leper,

7 a woman drew near to him, holding an alabaster box of precious ointment, and she poured it over his head while he was reclining at table.

8 But the disciples, seeing this, were indignant, saying: "What is the purpose of this waste?

9 For this could have been sold for a great deal, so as to be given to the poor."

10 But Jesus, knowing this, said to them: "Why are you bothering this woman? For she has done a good deed to me.

11 For the poor you will always have with you. But you will not always have me.

12 For in pouring this ointment on my body, she has prepared for my burial.

13 Amen I say to you, wherever this Gospel will be preached in the whole world, what she has done also shall be told, in memory of her."

14 Then one of the twelve, who was called Judas Iscariot, went to the leaders of the priests,

15 and he said to them, "What are you willing to give me, if I hand him over to you?" So they appointed thirty pieces of silver for him.

16 And from then on, he sought an opportunity to betray him.

17 Then, on the first day of Unleavened Bread, the disciples approached Jesus, saying, "Where do you want us to prepare for you to eat the Passover?"

18 So Jesus said, "Go into the city, to a certain one, and say to him: 'The Teacher said: My time is near. I am observing the Passover with you, along with my disciples.' "

19 And the disciples did just as Jesus appointed to them. And they prepared the Passover.

20 Then, when evening arrived, he sat at table with his twelve disciples.

21 And while they were eating, he said: "Amen I say to you, that one of you is about to betray me."

22 And being greatly saddened, each one of them began to say, "Surely, it is not I, Lord?"

23 But he responded by saying: "He who dips his hand with me into the dish, the same will betray me.

24 Indeed, the Son of man goes, just as it has been written about him. But woe to that man by whom the Son of man will be betrayed. It would be better for that man if he had not been born."

25 Then Judas, who betrayed him, responded by saying, "Surely, it is not I, Master?" He said to him, "You have said it."

26 Now while they were eating the meal, Jesus took bread, and he blessed and broke and gave it to his disciples, and he said: "Take and eat. This is my body."

27 And taking the chalice, he gave thanks. And he gave it to them, saying: "Drink from this, all of you.

28 For this is my blood of the new covenant, which shall be shed for many as a remission of sins.

29 But I say to you, I will not drink again from this fruit of the vine, until that day when I will drink it new with you in the kingdom of my Father."

30 And after a hymn was sung, they went out to the Mount of Olives.

31 Then Jesus said to them: "You will all fall away from me in this night. For it has been written: 'I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock will be scattered.'

32 But after I have risen again, I will go before you to Galilee."

33 Then Peter responded by saying to him, "Even if everyone else has fallen away from you, I will never fall away."

34 Jesus said to him, "Amen I say to you, that in this night, before the rooster crows, you will deny me three times."

35 Peter said to him, "Even if it is necessary for me to die with you, I will not deny you." And all the disciples spoke similarly.

36 Then Jesus went with them to a garden, which is called Gethsemani. And he said to his disciples, "Sit down here, while I go there and pray."

37 And taking with him Peter and the two sons of Zebedee, he began to be sorrowful and saddened.

38 Then he said to them: "My soul is sorrowful, even unto death. Stay here and keep vigil with me."

39 And continuing on a little further, he fell prostrate on his face, praying and saying: "My Father, if it is possible, let this chalice pass away from me. Yet truly, let it not be as I will, but as you will."

40 And he approached his disciples and found them sleeping. And he said to Peter: "So, were you not able to keep vigil with me for one hour?

41 Be vigilant and pray, so that you may not enter into temptation. Indeed, the spirit is willing, but the flesh is weak."

42 Again, a second time, he went and prayed, saying, "My Father, if this chalice cannot pass away, unless I drink it, let your will be done."

43 And again, he went and found them sleeping, for their eyes were heavy.

44 And leaving them behind, again he went and prayed for the third time, saying the same words.

45 Then he approached his disciples and said to them: "Sleep now and rest. Behold, the hour has drawn near, and the Son of man will be delivered into the hands of sinners.

46 Rise up; let us go. Behold, he who will betray me draws near."

47 While he was still speaking, behold, Judas, one of the twelve, arrived, and with him was a large crowd with swords and clubs, sent from the leaders of the priests and the elders of the people.

48 And he who betrayed him gave them a sign, saying: "Whomever I will kiss, it is he. Take hold of him."

49 And quickly drawing close to Jesus, he said, "Hail, Master." And he kissed him.

50 And Jesus said to him, "Friend, for what purpose have you come?" Then they approached, and they put their hands on Jesus, and they held him.

51 And behold, one of those who were with Jesus, extending his hand, drew his sword and struck the servant of the high priest, cutting off his ear.

52 Then Jesus said to him: "Put your sword back in its place. For all who take up the sword shall perish by the sword.

53 Or do you think that I cannot ask my Father, so that he would give me, even now, more than twelve legions of Angels?

54 How then would the Scriptures be fulfilled, which say that it must be so?"

55 In that same hour, Jesus said to the crowds: "You went out, as if to a robber, with swords and clubs to seize me. Yet I sat daily with you, teaching in the temple, and you did not take hold of me.

56 But all this has happened so that the Scriptures of the prophets may be fulfilled." Then all the disciples fled, abandoning him.

57 But those who were holding Jesus led him to Caiaphas, the high priest, where the scribes and the elders had joined together.

58 Then Peter followed him from a distance, as far as the court of the high priest. And going inside, he sat down with the servants, so that he might see the end.

59 Then the leaders of the priests and the entire council sought false testimony against Jesus, so that they might deliver him to death.

60 And they did not find any, even though many false witnesses had come forward. Then, at the very end, two false witnesses came forward,

61 and they said, "This man said: 'I am able to destroy the temple of God, and, after three days, to rebuild it.' "

62 And the high priest, rising up, said to him, "Have you nothing to respond to what these ones testify against you?"

63 But Jesus was silent. And the high priest said to him, "I bind you by an oath to the living God to tell us if you are the Christ, the Son of God."

64 Jesus said to him: "You have said it. Yet truly I say to you, hereafter you shall see the Son of man sitting at the right hand of the power of God, and coming on the clouds of heaven."

65 Then the high priest tore his garments, saying: "He has blasphemed. Why do we still need witnesses? Behold, you have now heard the blasphemy.

66 How does it seem to you?" So they responded by saying, "He is guilty unto death."

67 Then they spit in his face, and they struck him with fists. And others struck his face with the palms of their hands,

68 saying: "Prophesy for us, O Christ. Who is the one that struck you?"

69 Yet truly, Peter sat outside in the courtyard. And a maidservant approached him, saying, "You also were with Jesus the Galilean."

70 But he denied it in the sight of them all, saying, "I do not know what you are saying."

71 Then, as he exited by the gate, another maidservant saw him. And she said to those who were there, "This man also was with Jesus of Nazareth."

72 And again, he denied it with an oath, "For I do not know the man."

73 And after a little while, those who were standing nearby came and said to Peter: "Truly, you also are one of them. For even your manner of speaking reveals you."

74 Then he began to curse and to swear that he had not known the man. And immediately the rooster crowed.

75 And Peter remembered the words of Jesus, which he had said: "Before the rooster crows, you will deny me three times." And going outside, he wept bitterly.

Matthew 27

1 Then, when morning arrived, all the leaders of the priests and the elders of the people took counsel against Jesus, so that they might deliver him to death.

2 And they led him, bound, and handed him over to Pontius Pilate, the procurator.

3 Then Judas, who betrayed him, seeing that he had been condemned, regretting his conduct, brought back the thirty pieces of silver to the leaders of the priests and the elders,

4 saying, "I have sinned in betraying just blood." But they said to him: "What is that to us? See to it yourself."

5 And throwing down the pieces of silver in the temple, he departed. And going out, he hanged himself with a snare.

6 But the leaders of the priests, having taken up the pieces of silver, said, "It is not lawful to put them into the temple offerings, because it is the price of blood."

7 Then, having taken counsel, they bought the potter's field with it, as a burying place for sojourners.

8 For this reason, that field is called Haceldama, that is, 'The Field of Blood,' even to this very day.

9 Then what was spoken by the prophet Jeremiah was fulfilled, saying, "And they took the thirty pieces of silver, the price of the one being appraised, whom they appraised before the sons of Israel,

10 and they gave it for the potter's field, just as the Lord appointed to me."

11 Now Jesus stood before the procurator, and the procurator questioned him, saying, "You are the king of the Jews?" Jesus said to him, "You are saying so."

12 And when he was accused by the leaders of the priests and the elders, he responded nothing.

13 Then Pilate said to him, "Do you not hear how much testimony they speak against you?"

14 And he did not respond any word to him, so that the procurator wondered greatly.

15 Now on the solemn day, the procurator was accustomed to release to the people one prisoner, whomever they wished.

16 And at that time, he had a notorious prisoner, who was called Barabbas.

17 Therefore, having been gathered together, Pilate said to them, "Who is it that you want me to release to you: Barabbas, or Jesus, who is called Christ?"

18 For he knew that it was out of envy they had handed him over.

19 But as he was sitting in the place for the tribunal, his wife sent to him, saying: "It is nothing to you, and he is just. For I have experienced many things today through a vision for his sake."

20 But the leaders of the priests and the elders persuaded the people, so that they would ask for Barabbas, and so that Jesus would perish.

21 Then, in response, the procurator said to them, "Which of the two do you want to be released to you?" But they said to him, "Barabbas."

22 Pilate said to them, "Then what shall I do about Jesus, who is called Christ?" They all said, "Let him be crucified."

23 The procurator said to them, "But what evil has he done?" But they cried out all the more, saying, "Let him be crucified."

24 Then Pilate, seeing that he was able to accomplish nothing, but that a greater tumult was occurring, taking water, washed his hands in the sight of the people, saying: "I am innocent of the blood of this just man. See to it yourselves."

25 And the entire people responded by saying, "May his blood be upon us and upon our children."

26 Then he released Barabbas to them. But Jesus, having been scourged, he handed over to them, so that he would be crucified.

27 Then the soldiers of the procurator, taking Jesus up to the praetorium, gathered the entire cohort around him.

28 And stripping him, they put a scarlet cloak around him.

29 And plaiting a crown of thorns, they placed it on his head, with a reed in his right hand. And genuflecting before him, they mocked him, saying, "Hail, King of the Jews."

30 And spitting on him, they took the reed and struck his head.

31 And after they had mocked him, they stripped him of the cloak, and clothed him with his own garments, and they led him away to crucify him.

32 But as they were going out, they came upon a man of Cyrene, named Simon, whom they compelled to take up his cross.

33 And they arrived at the place which is called Golgotha, which is the place of Calvary.

34 And they gave him wine to drink, mixed with gall. And when he had tasted it, he refused to drink it.

35 Then, after they had crucified him, they divided his garments, casting lots, in order to fulfill what was spoken by the prophet, saying: "They divided my garments among them, and over my vestment they cast lots."

36 And sitting down, they observed him.

37 And they set his accusation above his head, written as: THIS IS JESUS, KING OF THE JEWS.

38 Then two robbers were crucified with him: one on the right and one on the left.

39 But those passing by blasphemed him, shaking their heads,

40 and saying: "Ah, so you would destroy the temple of God and in three days rebuild it! Save your own self. If you are the Son of God, descend from the cross."

41 And similarly, the leaders of the priests, with the scribes and the elders, mocking him, said:

42 "He saved others; he cannot save himself. If he is the King of Israel, let him descend now from the cross, and we will believe in him.

43 He trusted in God; so now, let God free him, if he wills him. For he said, 'I am the Son of God.' "

44 Then, the robbers who were crucified with him also reproached him with the very same thing.

45 Now from the sixth hour, there was darkness over the entire earth, even until the ninth hour.

46 And about the ninth hour, Jesus cried out with a loud voice, saying: "Eli, Eli, lamma sabacthani?" that is, "My God, My God, why have you forsaken me?"

47 Then certain ones who were standing and listening there said, "This man calls upon Elijah."

48 And one of them, running quickly, took a sponge and filled it with vinegar, and he set it on a reed and he gave it to him to drink.

49 Yet truly, the others said, "Wait. Let us see whether Elijah will come to free him."

50 Then Jesus, crying out again with a loud voice, gave up his life.

51 And behold, the veil of the temple was torn into two parts, from top to bottom. And the earth was shaken, and the rocks were split apart.

52 And the tombs were opened. And many bodies of the saints, which had been sleeping, arose.

53 And going out from the tombs, after his resurrection, they went into the holy city, and they appeared to many.

54 Now the centurion and those who were with him, guarding Jesus, having seen the earthquake and the things that were done, were very fearful, saying: "Truly, this was the Son of God."

55 And in that place, there were many women, at a distance, who had followed Jesus from Galilee, ministering to him.

56 Among these were Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of James and Joseph, and the mother of the sons of Zebedee.

57 Then, when evening had arrived, a certain wealthy man from Arimathea, named Joseph, arrived, who himself was also a disciple of Jesus.

58 This man approached Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus. Then Pilate ordered the body to be released.

59 And Joseph, taking the body, wrapped it in a clean finely-woven linen cloth,

60 and he placed it in his own new tomb, which he had hewn out of a rock. And he rolled a great stone to the door of the tomb, and he went away.

61 Now Mary Magdalene and the other Mary were there, sitting opposite the sepulcher.

62 Then the next day, which is after the Preparation day, the leaders of the priests and the Pharisees went to Pilate together,

63 saying: "Lord, we have remembered that that this seducer said, while he was still alive, 'After three days, I will rise again.'

64 Therefore, order the sepulcher to be guarded until the third day, lest perhaps his disciples may come and steal him, and say to the people, 'He has risen from the dead.' And this last error would be worse than the first."

65 Pilate said to them: "You have a guard. Go, guard it as you know how."

66 Then, going out, they secured the sepulcher with guards, sealing the stone.

Matthew 28

1 Now on the morning of the Sabbath, when it began to grow light on the first Sabbath, Mary Magdalene and the other Mary went to see the sepulcher.

2 And behold, a great earthquake occurred. For an Angel of the Lord descended from heaven, and as he approached, he rolled back the stone and sat down on it.

3 Now his appearance was like lightning, and his vestment was like snow.

4 Then, out of fear of him, the guards were terrified, and they became like dead men.

5 Then the Angel responded by saying to the women: "Do not be afraid. For I know that you are seeking Jesus, who was crucified.

6 He is not here. For he has risen, just as he said. Come and see the place where the Lord was placed.

7 And then, go quickly, and tell his disciples that he has risen. And behold, he will precede you to Galilee. There you shall see him. Lo, I have told you beforehand."

8 And they went out of the tomb quickly, with fear and in great joy, running to announce it to his disciples.

9 And behold, Jesus met them, saying, "Hail." But they drew near and took hold of his feet, and they adored him.

10 Then Jesus said to them: "Do not be afraid. Go, announce it to my brothers, so that they may go to Galilee. There they shall see me."

11 And when they had departed, behold, some of the guards went into the city, and they reported to the leaders of the priests all that had happened.

12 And gathering together with the elders, having taken counsel, they gave an abundant sum of money to the soldiers,

13 saying: "Say that his disciples arrived at night and stole him away, while we were sleeping.

14 And if the procurator hears about this, we will persuade him, and we will protect you."

15 Then, having accepted the money, they did as they were instructed. And this word has been spread among the Jews, even to this day.

16 Now the eleven disciples went on to Galilee, to the mountain where Jesus had appointed them.

17 And, seeing him, they worshipped him, but certain ones doubted.

18 And Jesus, drawing near, spoke to them, saying: "All authority has been given to me in heaven and on earth.

19 Therefore, go forth and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit,

20 teaching them to observe all that I have ever commanded you. And behold, I am with you always, even to the consummation of the age."

Mark 1

1 The beginning of the Gospel of Jesus Christ, the Son of God.

2 As it has been written by the prophet Isaiah: "Behold, I send my Angel before your face, who shall prepare your way before you.

3 The voice of one crying out in the desert: Prepare the way of the Lord; make straight his paths."

4 John was in the desert, baptizing and preaching a baptism of repentance, as a remission of sins.

5 And there went out to him all the region of Judea and all those of Jerusalem, and they were baptized by him in the river Jordan, confessing their sins.

6 And John was clothed with camel's hair and with a leather belt around his waist. And he ate locusts and wild honey.

7 And he preached, saying: "A stronger one comes after me. I am not worthy to reach down and loosen the laces of his shoes.

8 I have baptized you with water. Yet truly, he will baptize you with the Holy Spirit."

9 And it happened that, in those days, Jesus arrived from Nazareth of Galilee. And he was baptized by John in the Jordan.

10 And immediately, upon ascending from the water, he saw the heavens opened and the Spirit, like a dove, descending, and remaining with him.

11 And there was a voice from heaven: "You are my beloved Son; in you I am well pleased."

12 And immediately the Spirit prompted him into the desert.

13 And he was in the desert for forty days and forty nights. And he was tempted by Satan. And he was with the wild animals, and the Angels ministered to him.

14 Then, after John was handed over, Jesus went into Galilee, preaching the Gospel of the kingdom of God,

15 and saying: "For the time has been fulfilled and the kingdom of God has drawn near. Repent and believe in the Gospel."

16 And passing by the shore of the Sea of Galilee, he saw Simon and his brother Andrew, casting nets into the sea, for they were fishermen.

17 And Jesus said to them, "Come after me, and I will make you fishers of men."

18 And at once abandoning their nets, they followed him.

19 And continuing on a little ways from there, he saw James of Zebedee and his brother John, and they were mending their nets in a boat.

20 And immediately he called them. And leaving behind their father Zebedee in the boat with his hired hands, they followed him.

21 And they entered into Capernaum. And entering into the synagogue promptly on the Sabbaths, he taught them.

22 And they were astonished over his doctrine. For he was teaching them as one who has authority, and not like the scribes.

23 And in their synagogue, there was a man with an unclean spirit; and he cried out,

24 saying: "What are we to you, Jesus of Nazareth? Have you come to destroy us? I know who you are: the Holy One of God."

25 And Jesus admonished him, saying, "Be silent, and depart from the man."

26 And the unclean spirit, convulsing him and crying out with a loud voice, departed from him.

27 And they were all so amazed that they inquired among themselves, saying: "What is this? And what is this new doctrine? For with authority he commands even the unclean spirits, and they obey him."

28 And his fame went out quickly, throughout the entire region of Galilee.

29 And soon after departing from the synagogue, they went into the house of Simon and Andrew, with James and John.

30 But the mother-in-law of Simon lay ill with a fever. And at once they told him about her.

31 And drawing near to her, he raised her up, taking her by the hand. And immediately the fever left her, and she ministered to them.

32 Then, when evening arrived, after the sun had set, they brought to him all who had maladies and those who had demons.

33 And the entire city was gathered together at the door.

34 And he healed many who were troubled with various illnesses. And he cast out many demons, but he would not permit them to speak, because they knew him.

35 And rising up very early, departing, he went out to a deserted place, and there he prayed.

36 And Simon, and those who were with him, followed after him.

37 And when they had found him, they said to him, "For everyone is seeking you."

38 And he said to them: "Let us go into the neighboring towns and cities, so that I may preach there also. Indeed, it was for this reason that I came."

39 And he was preaching in their synagogues and throughout all of Galilee, and casting out demons.

40 And a leper came to him, begging him. And kneeling down, he said to him, "If you are willing, you are able to cleanse me."

41 Then Jesus, taking pity on him, reached out his hand. And touching him, he said to him: "I am willing. Be cleansed."

42 And after he had spoken, immediately the leprosy departed from him, and he was cleansed.

43 And he admonished him, and he promptly sent him away.

44 And he said to him: "See to it that you tell no one. But go and show yourself to the high priest, and offer for your cleansing that which Moses instructed, as a testimony for them."

45 But having departed, he began to preach and to disseminate the word, so that he was no longer able to openly enter a city, but had to remain outside, in deserted places. And they were gathered to him from every direction.

Mark 2

1 And after some days, he again entered into Capernaum.

2 And it was heard that he was in the house. And so many gathered that there was no room left, not even at the door. And he spoke the word to them.

3 And they came to him, bringing a paralytic, who was being carried by four men.

4 And when they were not able to present him to him because of the crowd, they uncovered the roof where he was. And opening it, they lowered down the stretcher on which the paralytic was lying.

5 Then, when Jesus had seen their faith, he said to the paralytic, "Son, your sins are forgiven you."

6 But some of the scribes were sitting in that place and thinking in their hearts:

7 "Why is this man speaking in this way? He is blaspheming. Who can forgive sins, but God alone?"

8 At once, Jesus, realizing in his spirit that they were thinking this within themselves, said to them: "Why are you thinking these things in your hearts?

9 Which is easier, to say to the paralytic, 'Your sins are forgiven you,' or to say, 'Rise up, take up your stretcher, and walk?'

10 But so that you may know that the Son of man has authority on earth to forgive sins," he said to the paralytic:

11 "I say to you: Rise up, take up your stretcher, and go into your house."

12 And immediately he got up, and lifting up his stretcher, he went away in the sight of them all, so that they all wondered. And they honored God, by saying, "We have never seen anything like this."

13 And he departed again to the sea. And the entire crowd came to him, and he taught them.

14 And as he was passing by, he saw Levi of Alphaeus, sitting at the customs office. And he said to him, "Follow me." And rising up, he followed him.

15 And it happened that, as he sat at table in his house, many tax collectors and sinners sat at table together with Jesus and his disciples. For those who followed him were many.

16 And the scribes and the Pharisees, seeing that he ate with tax collectors and sinners, said to his disciples, "Why does your Teacher eat and drink with tax collectors and sinners?"

17 Jesus, having heard this, said to them: "The healthy have no need of a doctor, but those who have maladies do. For I came not to call the just, but sinners."

18 And the disciples of John, and the Pharisees, were fasting. And they arrived and said to him, "Why do the disciples of John and of the Pharisees fast, but your disciples do not fast?"

19 And Jesus said to them: "How can the sons of the wedding fast while the groom is still with them? During whatever time they have the groom with them, they are not able to fast.

20 But the days will arrive when the groom will be taken away from them, and then they shall fast, in those days.

21 No one sews a patch of new cloth onto an old garment. Otherwise, the new addition pulls away from the old, and the tear becomes worse.

22 And no one puts new wine into old wineskins. Otherwise, the wine will burst the wineskins, and the wine will pour out, and the wineskins will be lost. Instead, new wine must be put into new wineskins."

23 And again, while the Lord was walking through the ripe grain on the Sabbath, his disciples, as they advanced, began to separate the ears of grains.

24 But the Pharisees said to him, "Behold, why are they doing what is not lawful on the Sabbaths?"

25 And he said to them: "Have you never read what David did, when he had need and was hungry, both he and those who were with him?

26 How he went into the house of God, under the high priest Abiathar, and ate the bread of the Presence, which it was not lawful to eat, except for the priests, and how he gave it to those who were with him?"

27 And he said to them: "The Sabbath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath.

28 And so, the Son of man is Lord, even of the Sabbath."

Mark 3

1 And again, he entered into the synagogue. And there was a man there who had a withered hand.

2 And they observed him, to see if he would cure on the Sabbaths, so that they might accuse him.

3 And he said to the man who had the withered hand, "Stand up in the middle."

4 And he said to them: "Is it lawful to do good on the Sabbaths, or to do evil, to give health to a life, or to destroy?" But they remained silent.

5 And looking around at them with anger, being very saddened over the blindness of their hearts, he said to the man, "Extend your hand." And he extended it, and his hand was restored to him.

6 Then the Pharisees, going out, immediately took counsel with the Herodians against him, as to how they might destroy him.

7 But Jesus withdrew with his disciples to the sea. And a great crowd followed him from Galilee and Judea,

8 and from Jerusalem, and from Idumea and across the Jordan. And those around Tyre and Sidon, upon hearing what he was doing, came to him in a great multitude.

9 And he told his disciples that a small boat would be useful to him, because of the crowd, lest they press upon him.

10 For he healed so many, that as many of them as had wounds would rush toward him in order to touch him.

11 And the unclean spirits, when they saw him, fell prostrate before him. And they cried out, saying,

12 "You are the Son of God." And he strongly admonished them, lest they make him known.

13 And ascending onto a mountain, he called to himself those whom he willed, and they came to him.

14 And he acted so that the twelve would be with him, and so that he might send them out to preach.

15 And he gave them authority to cure infirmities, and to cast out demons:

16 and he imposed on Simon the name Peter;

17 and also he imposed on James of Zebedee, and John the brother of James, the name 'Boanerges,' that is, 'Sons of Thunder;'

18 and Andrew, and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and James of Alphaeus, and Thaddeus, and Simon the Canaanite,

19 and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him.

20 And they went to a house, and the crowd gathered together again, so much so that they were not even able to eat bread.

21 And when his own had heard of it, they went out to take hold of him. For they said: "Because he has gone mad."

22 And the scribes who had descended from Jerusalem said, "Because he has Beelzebub, and because by the prince of demons does he cast out demons."

23 And having called them together, he spoke to them in parables: "How can Satan cast out Satan?

24 For if a kingdom is divided against itself, that kingdom is not able to stand.

25 And if a house is divided against itself, that house is not able to stand.

26 And if Satan has risen up against himself, he would be divided, and he would not be able to stand; instead he reaches the end.

27 No one is able to plunder the goods of a strong man, having entered into the house, unless he first binds the strong man, and then he shall plunder his house.

28 Amen I say to you, that all sins will be forgiven the sons of men, and the blasphemies by which they will have blasphemed.

29 But he who will have blasphemed against the Holy Spirit shall not have forgiveness in eternity; instead he shall be guilty of an eternal offense."

30 For they said: "He has an unclean spirit."

31 And his mother and brothers arrived. And standing outside, they sent to him, calling him.

32 And the crowd was sitting around him. And they said to him, "Behold, your mother and your brothers are outside, seeking you."

33 And responding to them, he said, "Who is my mother and my brothers?"

34 And looking around at those who were sitting all around him, he said: "Behold, my mother and my brothers.

35 For whoever has done the will of God, the same is my brother, and my sister and mother."

Mark 4

1 And again, he began to teach by the sea. And a great crowd was gathered to him, so much so that, climbing into a boat, he was seated on the sea. And the entire crowd was on the land along the sea.

2 And he taught them many things in parables, and he said to them, in his doctrine:

3 "Listen. Behold, the sower went out to sow.

4 And while he was sowing, some fell along the way, and the birds of the air came and ate it.

5 Yet truly, others fell upon stony ground, where it did not have much soil. And it rose up quickly, because it had no depth of soil.

6 And when the sun was risen, it was scorched. And because it had no root, it withered away.

7 And some fell among thorns. And the thorns grew up and suffocated it, and it did not produce fruit.

8 And some fell on good soil. And it brought forth fruit that grew up, and increased, and yielded: some thirty, some sixty, and some one hundred."

9 And he said, "Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear."

10 And when he was alone, the twelve, who were with him, questioned him about the parable.

11 And he said to them: "To you, it has been given to know the mystery of the kingdom of God. But to those who are outside, everything is presented in parables:

12 'so that, seeing, they may see, and not perceive; and hearing, they may hear, and not understand; lest at any time they may be converted, and their sins would be forgiven them.' "

13 And he said to them: "Do you not understand this parable? And so, how will you understand all the parables?

14 He who sows, sows the word.

15 Now there are those who are along the way, where the word is sown. And when they have heard it, Satan quickly comes and takes away the word, which was sown in their hearts.

16 And similarly, there are those who were sown upon stony ground. These, when they have heard the word, immediately accept it with gladness.

17 But they have no root in themselves, and so they are for a limited time. And when next tribulation and persecution arises because of the word, they quickly fall away.

18 And there are others who are sown among thorns. These are those who hear the word,

19 but worldly tasks, and the deception of riches, and desires about other things enter in and suffocate the word, and it is effectively without fruit.

20 And there are those who are sown upon good soil, who hear the word and accept it; and these bear fruit: some thirty, some sixty, and some one hundred."

21 And he said to them: "Would someone enter with a lamp in order to place it under a basket or under a bed? Would it not be placed upon a lampstand?

22 For there is nothing hidden that will not be revealed. Neither was anything done in secret, except that it may be made public.

23 If anyone has ears to hear, let him hear."

24 And he said to them: "Consider what you hear. With whatever measure you have measured out, it shall be measured back to you, and more shall be added to you.

25 For whoever has, to him it shall be given. And whoever has not, from him even what he has shall be taken away."

26 And he said: "The kingdom of God is like this: it is as if a man were to cast seed on the land.

27 And he sleeps and he arises, night and day. And the seed germinates and grows, though he does not know it.

28 For the earth bears fruit readily: first the plant, then the ear, next the full grain in the ear.

29 And when the fruit has been produced, immediately he sends out the sickle, because the harvest has arrived."

30 And he said: "To what should we compare the kingdom of God? Or to what parable should we compare it?

31 It is like a grain of mustard seed which, when it has been sown in the earth, is less than all the seeds which are in the earth.

32 And when it is sown, it grows up and becomes greater than all the plants, and it produces great branches, so much so that the birds of the air are able to live under its shadow."

33 And with many such parables he spoke the word to them, as much as they were able to hear.

34 But he did not speak to them without a parable. Yet separately, he explained all things to his disciples.

35 And on that day, when evening had arrived, he said to them, "Let us cross over."

36 And dismissing the crowd, they brought him, so that he was in one boat, and other boats were with him.

37 And a great wind storm occurred, and the waves broke over the boat, so that the boat was being filled.

38 And he was in the stern of the boat, sleeping on a pillow. And they woke him and said to him, "Teacher, does it not concern you that we are perishing?"

39 And rising up, he rebuked the wind, and he said to the sea: "Silence. Be stilled." And the wind ceased. And a great tranquility occurred.

40 And he said to them: "Why are you afraid? Do you still lack faith?" And they were struck with a great fear. And they said to one another, "Who do you think this is, that both wind and sea obey him?"

Mark 5

1 And they went across the strait of the sea into the region of the Gerasenes.

2 And as he was departing from the boat, he was immediately met, from among the tombs, by a man with an unclean spirit,

3 who had his dwelling place with the tombs; neither had anyone been able to bind him, even with chains.

4 For having been bound often with shackles and chains, he had broken the chains and smashed the shackles; and no one had been able to tame him.

5 And he was always, day and night, among the tombs, or in the mountains, crying out and cutting himself with stones.

6 And seeing Jesus from afar, he ran and adored him.

7 And crying out with a loud voice, he said: "What am I to you, Jesus, the Son of the Most High God? I beseech you by God, that you not torment me."

8 For he said to him, "Depart from the man, you unclean spirit."

9 And he questioned him: "What is your name?" And he said to him, "My name is Legion, for we are many."

10 And he entreated him greatly, so that he would not expel him from the region.

11 And in that place, near the mountain, there was a great herd of swine, feeding.

12 And the spirits entreated him, saying: "Send us into the swine, so that we may enter into them."

13 And Jesus promptly gave them permission. And the unclean spirits, departing, entered into the swine. And the herd of about two thousand rushed down with great force into the sea, and they were drowned in the sea.

14 Then those who pastured them fled, and they reported it in the city and in the countryside. And they all went out to see what was happening.

15 And they came to Jesus. And they saw the man who had been troubled by the demon, sitting, clothed and with a sane mind, and they were afraid.

16 And those who had seen it explained to them how he had dealt with the man who had the demon, and about the swine.

17 And they began to petition him, so that he would withdraw from their borders.

18 And as he was climbing into the boat, the man who had been troubled by the demons began to beg him, so that he might be with him.

19 And he did not permit him, but he said to him, "Go to your own people, in your own house, and announce to them how great are the things that Lord has done for you, and how he has taken pity on you."

20 And he went away and began to preach in the Ten Cities, how great were the things that Jesus had done for him. And everyone wondered.

21 And when Jesus had crossed in the boat, over the strait again, a great crowd came together before him. And he was near the sea.

22 And one of the rulers of the synagogue, named Jairus, approached. And seeing him, he fell prostrate at his feet.

23 And he beseeched him greatly, saying: "For my daughter is near the end. Come and lay your hand on her, so that she may be healthy and may live."

24 And he went with him. And a great crowd followed him, and they pressed upon him.

25 And there was a woman who had a flow of blood for twelve years.

26 And she had endured much from several physicians, and she had spent everything she owned with no benefit at all, but instead she became worse.

27 Then, when she had heard of Jesus, she approached through the crowd behind him, and she touched his garment.

28 For she said: "Because if I touch even his garment, I will be saved."

29 And immediately, the source of her bleeding was dried up, and she sensed in her body that she had been healed from the wound.

30 And immediately Jesus, realizing within himself that power that had gone out from him, turning to the crowd, said, "Who touched my garments?"

31 And his disciples said to him, "You see that the crowd presses around you, and yet you say, 'Who touched me?' "

32 And he looked around to see the woman who had done this.

33 Yet truly, the woman, in fear and trembling, knowing what had happened within her, went and fell prostrate before him, and she told him the whole truth.

34 And he said to her: "Daughter, your faith has saved you. Go in peace, and be healed from your wound."

35 While he was still speaking, they arrived from the ruler of the synagogue, saying: "Your daughter is dead. Why trouble the Teacher any further?"

36 But Jesus, having heard the word that was spoken, said to the ruler of the synagogue: "Do not be afraid. You need only believe."

37 And he would not permit anyone to follow him, except Peter, and James, and John the brother of James.

38 And they went to the house of the ruler of the synagogue. And he saw a tumult, and weeping, and much wailing.

39 And entering, he said to them: "Why are you disturbed and weeping? The girl is not dead, but is asleep."

40 And they derided him. Yet truly, having put them all out, he took the father and mother of the girl, and those who were with him, and he entered to where the girl was lying.

41 And taking the girl by the hand, he said to her, "Talitha koumi," which means, "Little girl, (I say to you) arise.

42 And immediately the young girl rose up and walked. Now she was twelve years old. And they were suddenly struck with a great astonishment.

43 And he instructed them sternly, so that no one would know about it. And he told them to give her something to eat.

Mark 6

1 And departing from there, he went away to his own country; and his disciples followed him.

2 And when the Sabbath arrived, he began to teach in the synagogue. And many, upon hearing him, were amazed at his doctrine, saying: "Where did this one get all these things?" and, "What is this wisdom, which has been given to him?" and, "Such powerful deeds, which are wrought by his hands!"

3 "Is this not the carpenter, the son of Mary, the brother of James, and Joseph, and Jude, and Simon? Are not his sisters also here with us?" And they took great offense at him.

4 And Jesus said to them, "A prophet is not without honor, except in his own country, and in his own house, and among his own kindred."

5 And he was not able to perform any miracles there, except that he cured a few of the infirm by laying his hands on them.

6 And he wondered, because of their unbelief, and he traveled around in the villages, teaching.

7 And he called the twelve. And he began to send them out in twos, and he gave them authority over unclean spirits.

8 And he instructed them not to take anything for the journey, except a staff: no traveling bag, no bread, and no money belt,

9 but to wear sandals, and not to wear two tunics.

10 And he said to them: "Whenever you have entered into a house, stay there until you depart from that place.

11 And whoever will neither receive you, nor listen to you, as you go away from there, shake off the dust from your feet as a testimony against them."

12 And going out, they were preaching, so that people would repent.

13 And they cast out many demons, and they anointed many of the sick with oil and healed them.

14 And king Herod heard of it, (for his name had become well-known) and he said: "John the Baptist has risen again from the dead, and because of this, miracles are at work in him."

15 But others were saying, "Because it is Elijah." Still others were saying, "Because he is a prophet, like one of the prophets."

16 When Herod had heard it, he said, "John whom I beheaded, the same has risen again from the dead."

17 For Herod himself had sent to capture John, and had chained him in prison, because of Herodias, the wife of his brother Philip; for he had married her.

18 For John was saying to Herod, "It is not lawful for you to have your brother's wife."

19 Now Herodias was devising treachery against him; and she wanted to kill him, but she was unable.

20 For Herod was apprehensive of John, knowing him to be a just and holy man, and so he guarded him. And he heard that he was accomplishing many things, and so he listened to him willingly.

21 And when an opportune time had arrived, Herod held a feast on his birthday, with the leaders, and the tribunes, and the first rulers of Galilee.

22 And when the daughter of the same Herodias had entered, and danced, and pleased Herod, along with those who were at table with him, the king said to the girl, "Request from me whatever you want, and I will give it to you."

23 And he swore to her, "Anything that you request, I will give to you, even up to half my kingdom."

24 And when she had gone out, she said to her mother, "What shall I request?" But her mother said, "The head of John the Baptist."

25 And immediately, when she had entered with haste to the king, she petitioned him, saying: "I want you to give me at once the head of John the Baptist on a platter."

26 And the king was greatly saddened. But because of his oath, and because of those who were sitting with him at table, he was not willing to disappoint her.

27 So, having sent an executioner, he instructed that his head be brought on a platter.

28 And he beheaded him in prison, and he brought his head on a platter. And he gave it to the girl, and the girl gave it her mother.

29 When his disciples heard about it, they came and took his body, and they placed it in a tomb.

30 And the Apostles, returning to Jesus, reported to him everything that they had done and taught.

31 And he said to them, "Go out alone, into a deserted place, and rest for a little while." For there were so many who were coming and going, that they did not even have time to eat.

32 And climbing into a boat, they went away to a deserted place alone.

33 And they saw them going away, and many knew about it. And together they ran by foot from all the cities, and they arrived before them.

34 And Jesus, going out, saw a great multitude. And he took pity on them, because they were like sheep without a shepherd, and he began to teach them many things.

35 And when many hours had now passed, his disciples drew near to him, saying: "This is a deserted place, and the hour is now late.

36 Send them away, so that by going out to nearby villages and towns, they might buy provisions for themselves to eat."

37 And responding, he said to them, "Give them something to eat yourselves." And they said to him, "Let us go out and buy bread for two hundred denarii, and then we will give them something to eat."

38 And he said to them: "How many loaves do you have? Go and see." And when they had found out, they said, "Five, and two fish."

39 And he instructed them to make them all sit down in groups on the green grass.

40 And they sat down in divisions by hundreds and by fifties.

41 And having received the five loaves and the two fish, gazing up to heaven, he blessed and broke the bread, and he gave it to his disciples to set before them. And the two fish he divided among them all.

42 And they all ate and were satisfied.

43 And they brought together the remainder: twelve baskets full of fragments and of fish.

44 Now those who ate were five thousand men.

45 And without delay he urged his disciples to climb into the boat, so that they might precede him across the sea to Bethsaida, while he dismissed the people.

46 And when he had dismissed them, he went to the mountain to pray.

47 And when it was late, the boat was in the midst of the sea, and he was alone on the land.

48 And seeing them struggling to row, (for the wind was against them,) and about the fourth watch of the night, he came to them, walking upon the sea. And he intended to pass by them.

49 But when they saw him walking upon the sea, they thought it was an apparition, and they cried out.

50 For they all saw him, and they were very disturbed. And immediately he spoke with them, and he said to them: "Be strengthened in faith. It is I. Do not be afraid."

51 And he climbed into the boat with them, and the wind ceased. And they became even more astonished within themselves.

52 For they did not understand about the bread. For their heart had been blinded.

53 And when they had crossed over, they arrived in the land of Genesaret, and they reached the shore.

54 And when they had disembarked from the boat, the people immediately recognized him.

55 And running throughout that entire region, they began to carry on beds those who had maladies, to where they heard that he would be.

56 And in whichever place he entered, in towns or villages or cities, they placed the infirm in the main streets, and they pleaded with him that they might touch even the hem of his garment. And as many as touched him were made healthy.

Mark 7

1 And the Pharisees and some of the scribes, arriving from Jerusalem, gathered together before him.

2 And when they had seen certain ones from his disciples eating bread with common hands, that is, with unwashed hands, they disparaged them.

3 For the Pharisees, and all the Jews, do not eat without repeatedly washing their hands, holding to the tradition of the elders.

4 And when returning from the market, unless they wash, they do not eat. And there are many other things which have been handed down to them to observe: the washings of cups, and pitchers, and bronze containers, and beds.

5 And so the Pharisees and the scribes questioned him: "Why do your disciples not walk according to the tradition of the elders, but they eat bread with common hands?"

6 But in response, he said to them: "So well did Isaiah prophesy about you hypocrites, just as it has been written: 'This people honors me with their lips, but their heart is far from me.

7 And in vain do they worship me, teaching the doctrines and precepts of men.'

8 For abandoning the commandment of God, you hold to the tradition of men, to the washing of pitchers and cups. And you do many other things similar to these."

9 And he said to them: "You effectively nullify the precept of God, so that you may observe your own tradition.

10 For Moses said: 'Honor your father and your mother,' and, 'Whoever will have cursed father or mother, let him die a death.'

11 But you say, 'If a man will have said to his father or mother: Korban, (which is a gift) whatever is from me will be to your benefit,'

12 then you do not release him to do anything for his father or mother,

13 rescinding the word of God through your tradition, which you have handed down. And you do many other similar things in this way."

14 And again, calling the crowd to him, he said to them: "Listen to me, all of you, and understand.

15 There is nothing from outside a man which, by entering into him, is able to defile him. But the things which procede from a man, these are what pollute a man.

16 Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear."

17 And when he had entered into the house, away from the crowd, his disciples questioned him about the parable.

18 And he said to them: "So, are you also without prudence? Do you not understand that everything entering to a man from outside is not able to pollute him?

19 For it does not enter into his heart, but into the gut, and it exits into the sewer, purging all foods."

20 "But," he said "the things which go out from a man, these pollute a man.

21 For from within, from the heart of men, proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, fornications, murders,

22 thefts, avarice, wickedness, deceitfulness, homosexuality, an evil eye, blasphemy, self-exaltation, foolishness.

23 All these evils procede from within and pollute a man."

24 And rising up, he went from there to the area of Tyre and Sidon. And entering into a house, he intended no one to know about it, but he was not able to remain hidden.

25 For a woman whose daughter had an unclean spirit, as soon as she heard about him, entered and fell prostrate at his feet.

26 For the woman was a Gentile, by birth a Syro-Phoenician. And she petitioned him, so that he would cast the demon from her daughter.

27 And he said to her: "First allow the sons to have their fill. For it is not good to take away the bread of the sons and throw it to the dogs."

28 But she responded by saying to him: "Certainly, Lord. Yet the young dogs also eat, under the table, from the crumbs of the children."

29 And he said to her, "Because of this saying, go; the demon has gone out of your daughter."

30 And when she had gone to her house, she found the girl lying on the bed; and the demon had gone away.

31 And again, departing from the borders of Tyre, he went by way of Sidon to the sea of Galilee, through the midst of the area of the Ten Cities.

32 And they brought someone who was deaf and mute to him. And they begged him, so that he would lay his hand upon him.

33 And taking him away from the crowd, he put his fingers into his ears; and spitting, he touched his tongue.

34 And gazing up to heaven, he groaned and said to him: "Ephphatha," which is, "Be opened."

35 And immediately his ears were opened, and the impediment of his tongue was released, and he spoke correctly.

36 And he instructed them not to tell anyone. But as much as he instructed them, so much more did they preach about it.

37 And so much more did they wonder, saying: "He has done all things well. He has caused both the deaf to hear and the mute to speak."

Mark 8

1 In those days, again, when there was a great crowd, and they did not have anything to eat, calling together his disciples, he said to them:

2 "I have compassion for the multitude, because, behold, they have persevered with me now for three days, and they do not have anything to eat.

3 And if I were to send them away fasting to their home, they might faint on the way." For some of them came from far away.

4 And his disciples answered him, "From where would anyone be able to obtain enough bread for them in the wilderness?"

5 And he questioned them, "How many loaves do you have?" And they said, "Seven."

6 And he instructed the crowd to sit down to eat on the ground. And taking the seven loaves, giving thanks, he broke and gave it to his disciples in order to place before them. And they placed these before the crowd.

7 And they had a few small fish. And he blessed them, and he ordered them to be placed before them.

8 And they ate and were satisfied. And they took up what had been leftover from the fragments: seven baskets.

9 And those who ate were about four thousand. And he dismissed them.

10 And promptly climbing into a boat with his disciples, he went into the parts of Dalmanutha.

11 And the Pharisees went out and began to contend with him, seeking from him a sign from heaven, testing him.

12 And sighing deeply in spirit, he said: "Why does this generation seek a sign? Amen, I say to you, if only a sign will be given to this generation!"

13 And sending them away, he climbed into the boat again, and he went away across the sea.

14 And they forgot to take bread. And they did not have any with them in the boat, except one loaf.

15 And he instructed them, saying: "Consider and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and of the leaven of Herod."

16 And they discussed this with one another, saying, "For we have no bread."

17 And Jesus, knowing this, said to them: "Why do you consider that it is because you have no bread? Do you not yet know or understand? Do you still have blindness in your heart?

18 Having eyes, do you not see? And having ears, do you not hear? Do you not remember,

19 when I broke the five loves among the five thousand, how many baskets full of fragments you took up?" They said to him, "Twelve."

20 "And when the seven loaves were among the four thousand, how many baskets of fragments did you take up?" And they said to him, "Seven."

21 And he said to them, "How is it that you do not yet understand?"

22 And they went to Bethsaida. And they brought a blind man to him. And they petitioned him, so that he would touch him.

23 And taking the blind man by the hand, he led him beyond the village. And putting spit on his eyes, laying his hands on him, he asked him if he could see anything.

24 And looking up, he said, "I see men but they are like walking trees."

25 Next he placed his hands again over his eyes, and he began to see. And he was restored, so that he could see everything clearly.

26 And he sent him to his house, saying, "Go into your own house, and if you enter into the town, tell no one."

27 And Jesus departed with his disciples into the towns of Caesarea Philippi. And on the way, he questioned his disciples, saying to them, "Who do men say that I am?"

28 And they answered him by saying: "John the Baptist, others Elijah, still others perhaps one of the prophets."

29 Then he said to them, "Yet truly, who do you say that I am?" Peter responded by saying to him, "You are the Christ."

30 And he admonished them, not to tell anyone about him.

31 And he began to teach them that the Son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected by the elders, and by the high priests, and the scribes, and be killed, and after three days rise again.

32 And he spoke the word openly. And Peter, taking him aside, began to correct him.

33 And turning away and looking at his disciples, he admonished Peter, saying, "Get behind me, Satan, for you do not prefer the things that are of God, but the things that are of men."

34 And calling together the crowd with his disciples, he said to them, "If anyone chooses to follow me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me.

35 For whoever will have chosen to save his life, will lose it. But whoever will have lost his life, for my sake and for the Gospel, shall save it.

36 For how does it benefit a man, if he gains the whole world, and yet causes harm to his soul?

37 Or, what will a man give in exchange for his soul?

38 For whoever has been ashamed of me and of my words, among this adulterous and sinful generation, the Son of man also will be ashamed of him, when he will arrive in the glory of his Father, with the holy Angels."

39 And he said to them, "Amen I say to you, that there are some among those standing here who shall not taste death until they see the kingdom of God arriving in power."

Mark 9

1 And after six days, Jesus took with him Peter, and James, and John; and he led them separately to a lofty mountain alone; and he was transfigured before them.

2 And his vestments became radiant and exceedingly white like snow, with such a brilliance as no fuller on earth is able to achieve.

3 And there appeared to them Elijah with Moses; and they were speaking with Jesus.

4 And in response, Peter said to Jesus: "Master, it is good for us to be here. And so let us make three tabernacles, one for you, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah."

5 For he did not know what he was saying. For they were overwhelmed by fear.

6 And there was a cloud overshadowing them. And a voice came from the cloud, saying: "This is my most beloved Son. Listen to him."

7 And immediately, looking around, they no longer saw anyone, except Jesus alone with them.

8 And as they were descending from the mountain, he instructed them not to relate to anyone what they had seen, until after the Son of man will have risen again from the dead.

9 And they kept the word to themselves, arguing about what "after he will have risen from the dead" might mean.

10 And they questioned him, saying: "Then why do the Pharisees and the scribes say that Elijah must arrive first?"

11 And in response, he said to them: "Elijah, when he will arrive first, shall restore all things. And in the manner that it has been written about the Son of man, so must he suffer many things and be condemned.

12 But I say to you, that Elijah also has arrived, (and they have done to him whatever they wanted) just as it has been written about him."

13 And approaching his disciples, he saw a great crowd surrounding them, and the scribes were arguing with them.

14 And soon all the people, seeing Jesus, were astonished and struck with fear, and hurrying to him, they greeted him.

15 And he questioned them, "What are you arguing about among yourselves?"

16 And one from the crowd responded by saying: "Teacher, I have brought to you my son, who has a mute spirit.

17 And whenever it takes hold of him, it throws him down, and he foams and gnashes with his teeth, and he becomes unconscious. And I asked your disciples to cast him out, and they could not."

18 And answering them, he said: "O unbelieving generation, how long must I be with you? How long shall I endure you? Bring him to me."

19 And they brought him. And when he had seen him, immediately the spirit disturbed him. And having been thrown to the ground, he rolled around foaming.

20 And he questioned his father, "How long has this been happening to him?" But he said: "From infancy.

21 And often it casts him into fire or into water, in order to destroy him. But if you are able to do anything, help us and take pity on us."

22 But Jesus said to him, "If you are able to believe: all things are possible to one who believes."

23 And immediately the father of the boy, crying out with tears, said: "I do believe, Lord. Help my unbelief."

24 And when Jesus saw the crowd rushing together, he admonished the unclean spirit, saying to him, "Deaf and mute spirit, I command you, leave him; and do not enter into him anymore."

25 And crying out, and convulsing him greatly, he departed from him. And he became like one who is dead, so much so that many said, "He is dead."

26 But Jesus, taking him by the hand, lifted him up. And he arose.

27 And when he had entered into the house, his disciples questioned him privately, "Why were we unable to cast him out?"

28 And he said to them, "This kind is able to be expelled by nothing other than prayer and fasting."

29 And setting out from there, they passed through Galilee. And he intended that no one know about it.

30 Then he taught his disciples, and he said to them, "For the Son of man shall be delivered into the hands of men, and they will kill him, and having been killed, on the third day he will rise again."

31 But they did not understand the word. And they were afraid to question him.

32 And they went to Capernaum. And when they were in the house, he questioned them, "What did you discuss on the way?"

33 But they were silent. For indeed, on the way, they had disputed among themselves as to which of them was greater.

34 And sitting down, he called the twelve, and he said to them, "If anyone wants to be first, he shall be the last of all and the minister of all."

35 And taking a child, he set him in their midst. And when he had embraced him, he said to them:

36 "Whoever receives one such child in my name, receives me. And whoever receives me, receives not me, but him who sent me."

37 John responded to him by saying, "Teacher, we saw someone casting out demons in your name; he does not follow us, and so we prohibited him."

38 But Jesus said: "Do not prohibit him. For there is no one who can act with virtue in my name and soon speak evil about me.

39 For whoever is not against you is for you.

40 For whoever, in my name, will give you a cup of water to drink, because you belong to Christ: Amen I say to you, he shall not lose his reward.

41 And whoever will have scandalized one of these little ones who believe in me: it would be better for him if a great millstone were placed around his neck and he were thrown into the sea.

42 And if your hand causes you to sin, cut it off: it is better for you to enter into life disabled, than having two hands to go into Hell, into the unquenchable fire,

43 where their worm does not die, and the fire is not extinguished.

44 But if your foot causes you to sin, chop it off: it is better for you to enter into eternal life lame, than having two feet to be cast into the Hell of unquenchable fire,

45 where their worm does not die, and the fire is not extinguished.

46 But if your eye causes you to sin, pluck it out: it is better for you to enter into the kingdom of God with one eye, than having two eyes to be cast into the Hell of fire,

47 where their worm does not die, and the fire is not extinguished.

48 For all shall be salted with fire, and every victim shall be salted with salt.

49 Salt is good: but if the salt has become bland, with what will you season it? Have salt in yourselves, and have peace among yourselves."

Mark 10

1 And rising up, he went from there into the area of Judea beyond the Jordan. And again, the crowd came together before him. And just as he was accustomed to do, again he taught them.

2 And approaching, the Pharisees questioned him, testing him: "Is it lawful for a man to dismiss his wife?"

3 But in response, he said to them, "What did Moses instruct you?"

4 And they said, "Moses gave permission to write a bill of divorce and to dismiss her."

5 But Jesus responded by saying: "It was due to the hardness of your heart that he wrote that precept for you.

6 But from the beginning of creation, God made them male and female.

7 Because of this, a man shall leave behind his father and mother, and he shall cling to his wife.

8 And these two shall be one in flesh. And so, they are now, not two, but one flesh.

9 Therefore, what God has joined together, let no man separate."

10 And again, in the house, his disciples questioned him about the same thing.

11 And he said to them: "Whoever dismisses his wife, and marries another, commits adultery against her.

12 And if a wife dismisses her husband, and is married to another, she commits adultery."

13 And they brought to him the little children, so that he might touch them. But the disciples admonished those who brought them.

14 But when Jesus saw this, he took offense, and he said to them: "Allow the little ones to come to me, and do not prohibit them. For of such as these is the kingdom of God.

15 Amen I say to you, whoever will not accept the kingdom of God like a little child, will not enter into it."

16 And embracing them, and laying his hands upon them, he blessed them.

17 And when he had departed on the way, a certain one, running up and kneeling before him, asked him, "Good Teacher, what shall I do, so that I may secure eternal life?"

18 But Jesus said to him, "Why call me good? No one is good except the one God.

19 You know the precepts: "Do not commit adultery. Do not kill. Do not steal. Do not speak false testimony. Do not deceive. Honor your father and mother."

20 But in response, he said to him, "Teacher, all these I have observed from my youth."

21 Then Jesus, gazing at him, loved him, and he said to him: "One thing is lacking to you. Go, sell whatever you have, and give to the poor, and then you will have treasure in heaven. And come, follow me."

22 But he went away grieving, having been greatly saddened by the word. For he had many possessions.

23 And Jesus, looking around, said to his disciples, "How difficult it is for those who have riches to enter into the kingdom of God!"

24 And the disciples were astonished at his words. But Jesus, answering again, said to them: "Little sons, how difficult it is for those who trust in money to enter into the kingdom of God!

25 It is easier for a camel to pass through the eye of a needle, than for the rich to enter into the kingdom of God."

26 And they wondered even more, saying among themselves, "Who, then, can be saved?"

27 And Jesus, gazing at them, said: "With men it is impossible; but not with God. For with God all things are possible."

28 And Peter began to say to him, "Behold, we have left all things and have followed you."

29 In response, Jesus said: "Amen I say to you, There is no one who has left behind house, or brothers, or sisters, or father, or mother, or children, or land, for my sake and for the Gospel,

30 who will not receive one hundred times as much, now in this time: houses, and brothers, and sisters, and mothers, and children, and land, with persecutions, and in the future age eternal life.

31 But many of the first shall be last, and the last shall be first."

32 Now they were on the way ascending to Jerusalem. And Jesus went ahead of them, and they were astonished. And those following him were afraid. And again, taking aside the twelve, he began to tell them what was about to happen to him.

33 "For behold, we are going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of man will be handed over to the leaders of the priests, and to the scribes, and the elders. And they will condemn him to death, and they will hand him over to the Gentiles.

34 And they will mock him, and spit on him, and scourge him, and put him to death. And on the third day, he will rise again."

35 And James and John, the sons of Zebedee, drew near to him, saying, "Teacher, we wish that whatever we will ask, you would do for us."

36 But he said to them, "What do you want me to do for you?"

37 And they said, "Grant to us that we may sit, one at your right and the other at your left, in your glory."

38 But Jesus said to them: "You do not know what you are asking. Are you able to drink from the chalice from which I drink, or to be baptized with the baptism with which I am to be baptized?"

39 But they said to him, "We can." Then Jesus said to them: "Indeed, you shall drink from the chalice, from which I drink; and you shall be baptized with the baptism, with which I am to be baptized.

40 But to sit at my right, or at my left, is not mine to give to you, but it is for those for whom it has been prepared."

41 And the ten, upon hearing this, began to be indignant toward James and John.

42 But Jesus, calling them, said to them: "You know that those who seem to be leaders among the Gentiles dominate them, and their leaders exercise authority over them.

43 But it is not to be this way among you. Instead, whoever would become greater shall be your minister;

44 and whoever will be first among you shall be the servant of all.

45 So, too, the Son of man has not come so that they would minister to him, but so that he would minister and would give his life as a redemption for many."

46 And they went to Jericho. And as he was setting out from Jericho with his disciples and a very numerous multitude, Bartimaeus, the son of Timaeus, a blind man, sat begging beside the way.

47 And when he had heard that it was Jesus of Nazareth, he began to cry out and to say, "Jesus, Son of David, take pity on me."

48 And many admonished him to be quiet. But he cried out all the more, "Son of David, take pity on me."

49 And Jesus, standing still, instructed him to be called. And they called the blind man, saying to him: "Be at peace. Arise. He is calling you."

50 And casting aside his garment, he leapt up and went to him.

51 And in response, Jesus said to him, "What do you want, that I should do for you?" And the blind man said to him, "Master, that I may see."

52 Then Jesus said to him, "Go, your faith has made you whole." And immediately he saw, and he followed him on the way.

Mark 11

1 And as they were approaching Jerusalem and Bethania, toward the mount of Olives, he sent two of his disciples,

2 and he said to them: "Go into the village that is opposite you, and immediately upon entering there, you will find a colt tied, on which no man has yet sat. Release him and bring him.

3 And if anyone will say to you: 'What are you doing?' Say that the Lord has need of him. And he will immediately send him here."

4 And going out, they found the colt tied before the outer gate, at the meeting of two ways. And they untied him.

5 And some of those who were standing there said to them, "What are you doing by releasing the colt?"

6 And they spoke to them just as Jesus had instructed them. And they permitted them.

7 And they led the colt to Jesus. And they placed their garments on it; and he sat upon it.

8 Then many spread their garments along the way; but others cut down leafy branches from trees and scattered them on the way.

9 And those who went ahead, and those who followed, cried out saying: "Hosanna! Blessed is he who has arrived in the name of the Lord.

10 Blessed is the advent of the kingdom of our father David. Hosanna in the highest!"

11 And he entered into Jerusalem, into the temple. And having looked around at everything, since it was now the evening hour, he went out to Bethania with the twelve.

12 And the next day, as they were departing from Bethania, he was hungry.

13 And when he had seen a fig tree with leaves in the distance, he went to it, in case he might find something on it. And when he had gone to it, he found nothing but leaves. For it was not the season for figs.

14 And in response, he said to it, "From now on and forever, may no one eat fruit from you again!" And his disciples heard this.

15 And they went to Jerusalem. And when he had entered into the temple, he began to cast out the sellers and the buyers in the temple. And he overturned the tables of the moneychangers and the chairs of the vendors of doves.

16 And he would not permit anyone to carry goods through the temple.

17 And he taught them, saying: "Is it not written: 'For my house shall be called the house of prayer for all nations?' But you have made it into a den of robbers."

18 And when the leaders of the priests, and the scribes, had heard this, they sought a means by which they might destroy him. For they feared him, because the entire multitude was in admiration over his doctrine.

19 And when evening had arrived, he departed from the city.

20 And when they passed by in the morning, they saw that the fig tree had dried up from the roots.

21 And Peter, remembering, said to him, "Master, behold, the fig tree that you cursed has withered."

22 And in response, Jesus said to them: "Have the faith of God.

23 Amen I say to you, that whoever will say to this mountain, 'Be taken up and cast into the sea,' and who will not have hesitated in his heart, but will have believed: then whatever he has said be done, it shall be done for him.

24 For this reason, I say to you, all things whatsoever that you ask for when praying: believe that you will receive them, and they will happen for you.

25 And when you stand to pray, if you hold anything against anyone, forgive them, so that your Father, who is in heaven, may also forgive you your sins.

26 But if you will not forgive, neither will your Father, who is in heaven, forgive you your sins."

27 And they went again to Jerusalem. And when he was walking in the temple, the leaders of the priests, and the scribes, and the elders approached him.

28 And they said to him: "By what authority do you do these things? And who has given you this authority, so that you would do these things?"

29 But in response, Jesus said to them: "I also will ask you one word, and if you answer me, I will tell you by what authority I do these things.

30 The baptism of John: was it from heaven or from men? Answer me."

31 But they discussed it among themselves, saying: "If we say, 'From heaven,' he will say, 'Then why did you not believe him?'

32 If we say, 'From men,' we fear the people. For they all hold that John was a true prophet."

33 And answering, they said to Jesus, "We do not know." And in response, Jesus said to them, "Neither will I tell you by what authority I do these things."

Mark 12

1 And he began to speak to them in parables: "A man dug a vineyard, and surrounded it with a hedge, and dug a pit, and built a tower, and he loaned it out to farmers, and he set out on a long journey.

2 And in time, he sent a servant to the farmers, in order to receive some of the fruit of the vineyard from the farmers.

3 But they, having apprehended him, beat him and sent him away empty.

4 And again, he sent another servant to them. And they wounded him on the head, and they treated him with contempt.

5 And again, he sent another, and him they killed, and many others: some they beat, but others they killed.

6 Therefore, having still one son, most dear to him, he sent him also to them, at the very end, saying, 'For they will reverence my son.'

7 But the settlers said one to another: 'This is the heir. Come, let us kill him. And then the inheritance will be ours.'

8 And apprehending him, they killed him. And they cast him out of the vineyard.

9 Therefore, what will the lord of the vineyard do?" "He will come and destroy the settlers. And he will give the vineyard to others."

10 "And so, have you not read this scripture?: 'The stone which the builders have rejected, the same has been made the head of the corner.

11 By the Lord has this been done, and it is wondrous in our eyes.' "

12 And they sought to take hold of him, but they feared the crowd. For they knew that he had spoken this parable about them. And leaving him behind, they went away.

13 And they sent some of the Pharisees and Herodians to him, so that they might trap him with words.

14 And these, arriving, said to him: "Teacher, we know that you are truthful and that you do not favor anyone; for you do not consider the appearance of men, but you teach the way of God in truth. Is it lawful to give the tribute to Caesar, or should we not give it?"

15 And knowing their skill in deception, he said to them: "Why do you test me? Bring me a denarius, so that I may see it."

16 And they brought it to him. And he said to them, "Whose image and inscription is this?" They said to him, "Caesar's."

17 So in response, Jesus said to them, "Then render to Caesar, the things that are of Caesar; and to God, the things that are of God." And they wondered over him.

18 And the Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection, approached him. And they questioned him, saying:

19 "Teacher, Moses wrote for us that if any man's brother will have died and left behind a wife, and not have left behind sons, his brother should take his wife to himself and should raise up offspring for his brother.

20 So then, there were seven brothers. And the first took a wife, and he died without leaving behind offspring.

21 And the second took her, and he died. And neither did he leave behind offspring. And the third acted similarly.

22 And in like manner, each of the seven received her and did not leave behind offspring. Last of all, the woman also died.

23 Therefore, in the resurrection, when they will rise again, to which of them will she be a wife? For each of the seven had her as wife."

24 And Jesus responded by saying to them: "But have you not gone astray, by knowing neither the scriptures, nor the power of God?

25 For when they will be resurrected from the dead, they shall neither marry, nor be given in marriage, but they are like the Angels in heaven.

26 But concerning the dead who rise again, have you not read in the book of Moses, how God spoke to him from the bush, saying: 'I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob?'

27 He is not the God of the dead, but of the living. Therefore, you have gone far astray."

28 And one of the scribes, who had heard them arguing, drew near to him. And seeing that he had answered them well, he questioned him as to which was the first commandment of all.

29 And Jesus answered him: "For the first commandment of all is this: 'Listen, O Israel. The Lord your God is one God.

30 And you shall love the Lord your God from your whole heart, and from your whole soul, and from your whole mind, and from your whole strength. This is the first commandment.'

31 But the second is similar to it: 'You shall love your neighbor as yourself.' There is no other commandment greater than these."

32 And the scribe said to him: Well said, Teacher. You have spoken the truth that there is one God, and there is no other beside him;

33 and that he should be loved from the whole heart, and from the whole understanding, and from the whole soul, and from the whole strength. And to love one's neighbor as one's self is greater than all holocausts and sacrifices."

34 And Jesus, seeing that he had responded wisely, said to him, "You are not far from the kingdom of God." And after that, no one dared to question him.

35 And while teaching in the temple, Jesus said in answer: "How is it that the scribes say that the Christ is the son of David?

36 For David himself said in the Holy Spirit: 'The Lord said to my Lord: Sit at my right hand, until I set your enemies as your footstool.'

37 Therefore, David himself calls him Lord, and so how can he be his son?" And a great multitude listened to him willingly.

38 And he said to them in his doctrine: "Beware of the scribes, who prefer to walk in long robes and to be greeted in the marketplace,

39 and to sit in the first chairs in the synagogues, and to have the first seats at feasts,

40 who devour the houses of widows under the pretense of long prayers. These shall receive the more extensive judgment."

41 And Jesus, sitting opposite the offertory box, considered the way in which the crowd cast coins into the offertory, and that many of the wealthy cast in a great deal.

42 But when one poor widow had arrived, she put in two small coins, which is a quarter.

43 And calling together his disciples, he said to them: "Amen I say to you, that this poor widow has put in more than all those who contributed to the offertory.

44 For they all gave from their abundance, yet truly, she gave from her scarcity, even all that she had, her entire living."

Mark 13

1 And as he was departing from the temple, one of his disciples said to him, "Teacher, observe these fine stones and fine structures."

2 And in response, Jesus said to him: "Do you see all these great buildings? There shall not be left stone upon stone, which is not torn down."

3 And as he sat at the Mount of Olives, opposite the temple, Peter, and James, and John, and Andrew questioned him privately.

4 "Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign when all these things will begin to be fulfilled?"

5 And Jesus, answering, began to say to them: "See to it that no one leads you astray.

6 For many will come in my name, saying, 'For I am he,' and they will lead many astray.

7 But when you will have heard of wars and rumors of wars, you should not be afraid. For these things must be, but the end is not so soon.

8 For nation will rise up against nation, and kingdom over kingdom, and there shall be earthquakes in various places, and famines. These are but the beginning of the sorrows.

9 But see to yourselves. For they will hand you over to councils, and in the synagogues you will be beaten, and you shall stand before governors and kings because of me, as a testimony for them.

10 And the Gospel must first be preached to all nations.

11 And when they have seized you and handed you over, do not consider in advance what to say. But whatever will be given you in that hour, say that. For you will not be speaking, but the Holy Spirit.

12 Then brother will betray brother to death, and the father, a son; and children will rise up against their parents and will bring about their death.

13 And you will be hated by all for the sake of my name. But whoever will have persevered unto the end, the same will be saved.

14 Then, when you have seen the abomination of desolation, standing where it ought not to be, let the reader understand: then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains.

15 And let whoever is on the rooftop not descend to the house, nor enter so as to take anything from the house.

16 And let whoever may be in the field not return to take his garment.

17 But woe to those who are pregnant or nursing in those days.

18 Truly, pray that these things may not happen in winter.

19 For those days shall have such tribulations as have not been since the beginning of the creation that God founded, even until now, and shall not be.

20 And unless the Lord had shortened the days, no flesh would be saved. But, for the sake of the elect, whom he has chosen, he has shortened the days.

21 And then, if anyone will have said to you: 'Behold, here is the Christ. Behold, in that place.' Do not believe it.

22 For false Christs and false prophets will rise up, and they will present signs and wonders, so as to lead astray, if it were possible, even the elect.

23 Therefore, you must take heed. Behold, I have foretold all to you.

24 But in those days, after that tribulation, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give her splendor.

25 And the stars of heaven will be falling down, and the powers that are in heaven will be moved.

26 And then they shall see the Son of man arriving on the clouds, with great power and glory.

27 And then he will send his Angels, and gather together his elect, from the four winds, from the limits of the earth, to the limits of heaven.

28 Now from the fig tree discern a parable. When its branch becomes tender and the foliage has been formed, you know that summer is very near.

29 So also, when you will have seen these things happen, know that it is very near, even at the doors.

30 Amen I say to you, that this lineage shall not pass away, until all these things have happened.

31 Heaven and earth shall pass away, but my word shall not pass away.

32 But concerning that day or hour, no one knows, neither the Angels in heaven, nor the Son, but only the Father.

33 Take heed, be vigilant, and pray. For you do not know when the time may be.

34 It is like a man who, setting out on a sojourn, left behind his house, and gave his servants authority over every work, and instructed the doorkeeper to stand watch.

35 Therefore, be vigilant, for you do not know when the lord of the house may arrive: in the evening, or in the middle of the night, or at first light, or in the morning.

36 Otherwise, when he will have arrived unexpectedly, he may find you sleeping.

37 But what I say to you, I say to all: Be vigilant."

Mark 14

1 Now the feast of Passover and of Unleavened Bread was two days away. And the leaders of the priests, and the scribes, were seeking a means by which they might deceitfully seize him and kill him.

2 But they said, "Not on the feast day, lest perhaps there may be a tumult among the people."

3 And when he was in Bethania, in the house of Simon the leper, and was reclining to eat, a woman arrived having an alabaster container of ointment, of precious spikenard. And breaking open the alabaster container, she poured it over his head.

4 But there were some who became indignant within themselves and who were saying: "What is the reason for this waste of the ointment?

5 For this ointment could have been sold for more than three hundred denarii and been given to the poor." And they murmured against her.

6 But Jesus said: "Permit her. What is the reason that you trouble her? She has done a good deed for me.

7 For the poor, you have with you always. And whenever you wish, you are able to do good to them. But you do not have me always.

8 But she has done what she could. She has arrived in advance to anoint my body for burial.

9 Amen I say to you, wherever this Gospel shall be preached throughout the entire world, the things she has done also shall be told, in memory of her."

10 And Judas Iscariot, one of the twelve, went away, to the leaders of the priests, in order to betray him to them.

11 And they, upon hearing it, were gladdened. And they promised him that they would give him money. And he sought an opportune means by which he might betray him.

12 And on the first day of Unleavened Bread, when they immolate the Passover, the disciples said to him, "Where do you want us to go and prepare for you to eat the Passover?"

13 And he sent two of his disciples, and he said to them: "Go into the city. And you will meet a man carrying a pitcher of water; follow him.

14 And wherever he will have entered, say to the owner of the house, 'The Teacher says: Where is my dining room, where I may eat the Passover with my disciples?'

15 And he will show you a large cenacle, fully furnished. And there, you shall prepare it for us."

16 And his disciples departed and went into the city. And they found it just as he had told them. And they prepared the Passover.

17 Then, when evening came, he arrived with the twelve.

18 And while reclining and eating with them at table, Jesus said, "Amen I say to you, that one of you, who eats with me, will betray me."

19 But they began to be sorrowful and to say to him, one at a time: "Is it I?"

20 And he said to them: "It is one of the twelve, who dips his hand with me in the dish.

21 And indeed, the Son of man goes, just as it has been written of him. But woe to that man by whom the Son of man will be betrayed. It would be better for that man if he had never been born."

22 And while eating with them, Jesus took bread. And blessing it, he broke it and gave it to them, and he said: "Take. This is my body."

23 And having taken the chalice, giving thanks, he gave it to them. And they all drank from it.

24 And he said to them: "This is my blood of the new covenant, which shall be shed for many.

25 Amen I say to you, that I will no longer drink from this fruit of the vine, until that day when I will drink it new in the kingdom of God."

26 And having sung a hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.

27 And Jesus said to them: "You will all fall away from me in this night. For it has been written: 'I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered.'

28 But after I have risen again, I will go before you to Galilee."

29 Then Peter said to him, "Even if all will have fallen away from you, yet I will not."

30 And Jesus said to him, "Amen I say to you, that this day, in this night, before the rooster has uttered its voice twice, you will deny me three times."

31 But he spoke further, "Even if I must die along with you, I will not deny you." And they all spoke similarly also.

32 And they went to a country estate, by the name of Gethsemani. And he said to his disciples, "Sit here, while I pray."

33 And he took Peter, and James, and John with him. And he began to be afraid and wearied.

34 And he said to them: "My soul is sorrowful, even unto death. Remain here and be vigilant."

35 And when he had proceeded on a little ways, he fell prostrate on the ground. And he prayed that, if it were possible, the hour might pass away from him.

36 And he said: "Abba, Father, all things are possible to you. Take this chalice from me. But let it be, not as I will, but as you will."

37 And he went and found them sleeping. And he said to Peter: "Simon, are you sleeping? Were you not able to be vigilant for one hour?

38 Watch and pray, so that you may not enter into temptation. The spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh is weak."

39 And going away again, he prayed, saying the same words.

40 And upon returning, he found them sleeping yet again, (for their eyes were heavy) and they did not know how to respond to him.

41 And he arrived for the third time, and he said to them: "Sleep now, and take rest. It is enough. The hour has arrived. Behold, the Son of man will be betrayed into the hands of sinners.

42 Rise up, let us go. Behold, he who will betray me is near."

43 And while he was still speaking, Judas Iscariot, one of the twelve, arrived, and with him was a large crowd with swords and clubs, sent from the leaders of the priests, and the scribes, and the elders.

44 Now his betrayer had given them a sign, saying: "He whom I shall kiss, it is he. Take hold of him, and lead him away cautiously."

45 And when he had arrived, immediately drawing near to him, he said: "Hail, Master!" And he kissed him.

46 But they laid hands on him and held him.

47 Then a certain one of those standing near, drawing a sword, struck a servant of the high priest and cut off his ear.

48 And in response, Jesus said to them: "Have you set out to apprehend me, just as if to a robber, with swords and clubs?

49 Daily, I was with you in the temple teaching, and you did not take hold of me. But in this way, the scriptures are fulfilled."

50 Then his disciples, leaving him behind, all fled away.

51 Now a certain young man followed him, having nothing but a fine linen cloth over himself. And they took hold of him.

52 But he, rejecting the fine linen cloth, escaped from them naked.

53 And they led Jesus to the high priest. And all the priests and the scribes and the elders came together.

54 But Peter followed him from a distance, even into the court of the high priest. And he sat with the servants at the fire and warmed himself.

55 Yet truly, the leaders of the priests and the entire council sought testimony against Jesus, so that they might deliver him to death, and they found none.

56 For many spoke false testimony against him, but their testimony did not agree.

57 And certain ones, rising up, bore false witness against him, saying:

58 "For we heard him say, 'I will destroy this temple, made with hands, and within three days I will build another, not made with hands.' "

59 And their testimony did not agree.

60 And the high priest, rising up in their midst, questioned Jesus, saying, "Do you have nothing to say in answer to the things that are brought against you by these ones?"

61 But he was silent and gave no answer. Again, the high priest questioned him, and he said to him, "Are you the Christ, the Son of the Blessed God?"

62 Then Jesus said to him: "I am. And you shall see the Son of man sitting at the right hand of the power of God and arriving with the clouds of heaven."

63 Then the high priest, rending his garments, said: "Why do we still require witnesses?

64 You have heard the blasphemy. How does it seem to you?" And they all condemned him, as guilty unto death.

65 And some began to spit on him, and to cover his face and to strike him with fists, and to say to him, "Prophesy." And the servants struck him with the palms their hands.

66 And while Peter was in the court below, one of the maidservants of the high priest arrived.

67 And when she had seen Peter warming himself, she stared at him, and she said: "You also were with Jesus of Nazareth."

68 But he denied it, saying, "I neither know nor understand what you saying." And he went outside, in front of the court; and a rooster crowed.

69 Then again, when a maidservant had seen him, she began to say to the bystanders, "For this is one of them."

70 But he denied it again. And after a little while, again those standing near said to Peter: "In truth, you are one of them. For you, too, are a Galilean."

71 Then he began to curse and to swear, saying, "For I do not know this man, about whom you are speaking."

72 And immediately the rooster crowed again. And Peter remembered the word that Jesus had said to him, "Before the rooster crows twice, you will deny me three times." And he began to weep.

Mark 15

1 And immediately in the morning, after the leaders of the priests had taken counsel with the elders and the scribes and the entire council, binding Jesus, they led him away and delivered him to Pilate.

2 And Pilate questioned him, "You are the king of the Jews?" But in response, he said to him, "You are saying it."

3 And the leaders of the priests accused him in many things.

4 Then Pilate again questioned him, saying: "Do you not have any response? See how greatly they accuse you."

5 But Jesus continued to give no response, so that Pilate wondered.

6 Now on the feast day, he was accustomed to release to them one of the prisoners, whomever they requested.

7 But there was one called Barabbas, who had committed murder in the sedition, who was confined with those of the sedition.

8 And when the crowd had ascended, they began to petition him to do as he always did for them.

9 But Pilate answered them and said, "Do you want me to release to you the king of the Jews?"

10 For he knew that it was out of envy that the leaders of the priests had betrayed him.

11 Then the chief priests incited the crowd, so that he would release Barabbas to them instead.

12 But Pilate, responding again, said to them: "Then what do you want me to do with the king of the Jews?"

13 But again they cried out, "Crucify him."

14 Yet truly, Pilate said to them: "Why? What evil has he done?" But they cried out all the more, "Crucify him."

15 Then Pilate, wishing to satisfy the people, released Barabbas to them, and he delivered Jesus, having severely scourged him, to be crucified.

16 Then the soldiers led him away to the court of the praetorium. And they called together the entire cohort.

17 And they clothed him with purple. And platting a crown of thorns, they placed it on him.

18 And they began to salute him: "Hail, king of the Jews."

19 And they struck his head with a reed, and they spit on him. And kneeling down, they reverenced him.

20 And after they had mocked him, they stripped him of the purple, and they clothed him in his own garments. And they led him away, so that they might crucify him.

21 And they compelled a certain passerby, Simon the Cyrenian, who was arriving from the countryside, the father of Alexander and Rufus, to take up his cross.

22 And they led him through to the place called Golgotha, which means, 'the Place of Calvary.'

23 And they gave him wine with myrrh to drink. But he did not accept it.

24 And while crucifying him, they divided his garments, casting lots over them, to see who would take what.

25 Now it was the third hour. And they crucified him.

26 And the title of his case was written as: THE KING OF THE JEWS.

27 And with him they crucified two robbers: one at his right, and the other at his left.

28 And the scripture was fulfilled, which says: "And with the iniquitous he was reputed."

29 And the passersby blasphemed him, shaking their heads and saying, "Ah, you who would destroy the temple of God, and in three days rebuild it,

30 save yourself by descending from the cross."

31 And similarly the leaders of the priests, mocking him with the scribes, said to one another: "He saved others. He is not able to save himself.

32 Let the Christ, the king of Israel, descend now from the cross, so that we may see and believe." Those who were crucified with him also insulted him.

33 And when the sixth hour arrived, a darkness occurred over the entire earth, until the ninth hour.

34 And at the ninth hour, Jesus cried out with a loud voice, saying, "Eloi, Eloi, lamma sabacthani?" which means, "My God, My God, why have you forsaken me?"

35 And some of those standing near, upon hearing this, said, "Behold, he is calling Elijah."

36 Then one of them, running and filling a sponge with vinegar, and placing it around a reed, gave it to him to drink, saying: "Wait. Let us see if Elijah will come to take him down."

37 Then Jesus, having emitted a loud cry, expired.

38 And the veil of the temple was torn in two, from the top to the bottom.

39 Then the centurion who stood opposite him, seeing that he had expired while crying out in this way, said: "Truly, this man was the Son of God."

40 Now there were also women watching from a distance, among whom were Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James the younger and of Joseph, and Salome,

41 (and while he was in Galilee, they followed him and ministered to him) and many other women, who had ascended along with him to Jerusalem.

42 And when evening had now arrived (because it was the Preparation Day, which is before the Sabbath)

43 there arrived Joseph of Arimathea, a noble council member, who himself was also awaiting the kingdom of God. And he boldly entered to Pilate and petitioned for the body of Jesus.

44 But Pilate wondered if he had already died. And summoning a centurion, he questioned him as to whether he was already dead.

45 And when he had been informed by the centurion, he gave the body to Joseph.

46 Then Joseph, having bought a fine linen cloth, and taking him down, wrapped him in the fine linen and laid him in a sepulcher, which was hewn from a rock. And he rolled a stone to the entrance of the tomb.

47 Now Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of Joseph observed where he was laid.

Mark 16

1 And when the Sabbath had passed, Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James, and Salome bought aromatic spices, so that when they arrived they could anoint Jesus.

2 And very early in the morning, on the first of the Sabbaths, they went to the tomb, the sun having now risen.

3 And they said to one another, "Who will roll back the stone for us, away from the entrance of the tomb?"

4 And looking, they saw that the stone was rolled back. For certainly it was very large.

5 And upon entering the tomb, they saw a young man sitting on the right side, covered with a white robe, and they were astonished.

6 And he said to them, "Do not become frightened. You are seeking Jesus of Nazareth, the Crucified One. He has risen. He is not here. Behold, the place where they laid him.

7 But go, tell his disciples and Peter that he is going before you into Galilee. There you shall see him, just as he told you."

8 But they, going out, fled from the tomb. For trembling and fear had overwhelmed them. And they said nothing to anyone. For they were afraid.

9 But he, rising early on the first Sabbath, appeared first to Mary Magdalene, from whom he had cast out seven demons.

10 She went and announced it to those who had been with him, while they were mourning and weeping.

11 And they, upon hearing that he was alive and that he had been seen by her, did not believe it.

12 But after these events, he was shown in another likeness to two of them walking, as they were going out to the countryside.

13 And they, returning, reported it to the others; neither did they believe them.

14 Finally, he appeared to the eleven, as they sat at table. And he rebuked them for their incredulity and hardness of heart, because they did not believe those who had seen that he had risen again.

15 And he said to them: "Go forth to the whole world and preach the Gospel to every creature.

16 Whoever will have believed and been baptized will be saved. Yet truly, whoever will not have believed will be condemned.

17 Now these signs will accompany those who believe. In my name, they shall cast out demons. They will speak in new languages.

18 They will take up serpents, and, if they drink anything deadly, it will not harm them. They shall lay their hands upon the sick, and they will be well."

19 And indeed, the Lord Jesus, after he had spoken to them, was taken up into heaven, and he sits at the right hand of God.

20 Then they, setting out, preached everywhere, with the Lord cooperating and confirming the word by the accompanying signs.

Luke 1

1 Since, indeed, many have attempted to set in order a narrative of the things that have been completed among us,

2 just as they have been handed on to those of us who from the beginning saw the same and were ministers of the word,

3 so it seemed good to me also, having diligently followed everything from the beginning, to write to you, in an orderly manner, most excellent Theophilus,

4 so that you might know the truthfulness of those words by which you have been instructed.

5 There was, in the days of Herod, king of Judea, a certain priest named Zechariah, of the section of Abijah, and his wife was of the daughters of Aaron, and her name was Elizabeth.

6 Now they were both just before God, progressing in all of the commandments and the justifications of the Lord without blame.

7 And they had no child, because Elizabeth was barren, and they both had become advanced in years.

8 Then it happened that, when he was exercising the priesthood before God, in the order of his section,

9 according to the custom of the priesthood, the lot fell so that he would offer incense, entering into the temple of the Lord.

10 And the entire multitude of the people was praying outside, at the hour of incense.

11 Then there appeared to him an Angel of the Lord, standing at the right of the altar of incense.

12 And upon seeing him, Zechariah was disturbed, and fear fell over him.

13 But the Angel said to him: "Do not be afraid, Zechariah, for your prayer has been heard, and your wife Elizabeth shall bear a son to you. And you shall call his name John.

14 And there will be joy and exultation for you, and many will rejoice in his nativity.

15 For he will be great in the sight of the Lord, and he will not drink wine or strong drink, and he will be filled with the Holy Spirit, even from his mother's womb.

16 And he will convert many of the sons of Israel to the Lord their God.

17 And he will go before him with the spirit and power of Elijah, so that he may turn the hearts of the fathers to the sons, and the incredulous to the prudence of the just, so as to prepare for the Lord a completed people."

18 And Zechariah said to the Angel: "How may I know this? For I am elderly, and my wife is advanced in years."

19 And in response, the Angel said to him: "I am Gabriel, who stands before God, and I have been sent to speak to you, and to proclaim these things to you.

20 And behold, you will be silent and unable to speak, until the day on which these things shall be, because you have not believed my words, which will be fulfilled in their time."

21 And the people were waiting for Zechariah. And they wondered why he was being delayed in the temple.

22 Then, when he came out, he was unable to speak to them. And they realized that he had seen a vision in the temple. And he was making signs to them, but he remained mute.

23 And it happened that, after the days of his office were completed, he went away to his house.

24 Then, after those days, his wife Elizabeth conceived, and she hid herself for five months, saying:

25 "For the Lord did this for me, at the time when he decided to take away my reproach among men."

26 Then, in the sixth month, the Angel Gabriel was sent by God, to a city of Galilee named Nazareth,

27 to a virgin betrothed to a man whose name was Joseph, of the house of David; and the name of the virgin was Mary.

28 And upon entering, the Angel said to her: "Hail, full of grace. The Lord is with you. Blessed are you among women."

29 And when she had heard this, she was disturbed by his words, and she considered what kind of greeting this might be.

30 And the Angel said to her: "Do not be afraid, Mary, for you have found grace with God.

31 Behold, you shall conceive in your womb, and you shall bear a son, and you shall call his name: JESUS.

32 He will be great, and he will be called the Son of the Most High, and the Lord God will give him the throne of David his father. And he will reign in the house of Jacob for eternity.

33 And his kingdom shall have no end."

34 Then Mary said to the Angel, "How shall this be done, since I do not know man?"

35 And in response, the Angel said to her: "The Holy Spirit will pass over you, and the power of the Most High will overshadow you. And because of this also, the Holy One who will be born of you shall be called the Son of God.

36 And behold, your cousin Elizabeth has herself also conceived a son, in her old age. And this is the sixth month for her who is called barren.

37 For no word will be impossible with God."

38 Then Mary said: "Behold, I am the handmaid of the Lord. Let it be done to me according to your word." And the Angel departed from her.

39 And in those days, Mary, rising up, traveled quickly into the hill country, to a city of Judah.

40 And she entered into the house of Zechariah, and she greeted Elizabeth.

41 And it happened that, as Elizabeth heard the greeting of Mary, the infant leaped in her womb, and Elizabeth was filled with the Holy Spirit.

42 And she cried out with a loud voice and said: "Blessed are you among women, and blessed is the fruit of your womb.

43 And how does this concern me, so that the mother of my Lord would come to me?

44 For behold, as the voice of your greeting came to my ears, the infant in my womb leaped for joy.

45 And blessed are you who believed, for the things that were spoken to you by the Lord shall be accomplished."

46 And Mary said: "My soul magnifies the Lord.

47 And my spirit leaps for joy in God my Saviour.

48 For he has looked with favor on the humility of his handmaid. For behold, from this time, all generations shall call me blessed.

49 For he who is great has done great things for me, and holy is his name.

50 And his mercy is from generation to generations for those who fear him.

51 He has accomplished powerful deeds with his arm. He has scattered the arrogant in the intentions of their heart.

52 He has deposed the powerful from their seat, and he has exalted the humble.

53 He has filled the hungry with good things, and the rich he has sent away empty.

54 He has taken up his servant Israel, mindful of his mercy,

55 just as he spoke to our fathers: to Abraham and to his offspring forever."

56 Then Mary stayed with her for about three months. And she returned to her own house.

57 Now the time for Elizabeth to give birth arrived, and she brought forth a son.

58 And her neighbors and relatives heard that the Lord had magnified his mercy with her, and so they congratulated her.

59 And it happened that, on the eighth day, they arrived to circumcise the boy, and they called him by his father's name, Zechariah.

60 And in response, his mother said: "Not so. Instead, he shall be called John."

61 And they said to her, "But there is no one among your relatives who is called by that name."

62 Then they made signs to his father, as to what he wanted him to be called.

63 And requesting a writing tablet, he wrote, saying: "His name is John." And they all wondered.

64 Then, at once, his mouth was opened, and his tongue loosened, and he spoke, blessing God.

65 And fear fell upon all of their neighbors. And all these words were made known throughout all the hill country of Judea.

66 And all those who heard it stored it up in their heart, saying: "What do you think this boy will be?" And indeed, the hand of the Lord was with him.

67 And his father Zechariah was filled with the Holy Spirit. And he prophesied, saying:

68 "Blessed is the Lord God of Israel. For he has visited and has wrought the redemption of his people.

69 And he has raised up a horn of salvation for us, in the house of David his servant,

70 just as he spoke by the mouth of his holy Prophets, who are from ages past:

71 salvation from our enemies, and from the hand of all those who hate us,

72 to accomplish mercy with our fathers, and to call to mind his holy testament,

73 the oath, which he swore to Abraham, our father, that he would grant to us,

74 so that, having been freed from the hand of our enemies, we may serve him without fear,

75 in holiness and in justice before him, throughout all our days.

76 And you, child, shall be called the prophet of the Most High. For you will go before the face of the Lord: to prepare his ways,

77 to give knowledge of salvation to his people for the remission of their sins,

78 through the heart of the mercy of our God, by which, descending from on high, he has visited us,

79 to illuminate those who sit in darkness and in the shadow of death, and to direct our feet in the way of peace."

80 And the child grew, and he was strengthened in spirit. And he was in the wilderness, until the day of his manifestation to Israel.

Luke 2

1 And it happened in those days that a decree went out from Caesar Augustus, so that the whole world would be enrolled.

2 This was the first enrollment; it was made by the ruler of Syria, Quirinius.

3 And all went to be declared, each one to his own city.

4 Then Joseph also ascended from Galilee, from the city of Nazareth, into Judea, to the city of David, which is called Bethlehem, because he was of the house and family of David,

5 in order to be declared, with Mary his espoused wife, who was with child.

6 Then it happened that, while they were there, the days were completed, so that she would give birth.

7 And she brought forth her firstborn son. And she wrapped him in swaddling clothes and laid him in a manger, because there was no room for them at the inn.

8 And there were shepherds in the same region, being vigilant and keeping watch in the night over their flock.

9 And behold, an Angel of the Lord stood near them, and the brightness of God shone around them, and they were struck with a great fear.

10 And the Angel said to them: "Do not be afraid. For, behold, I proclaim to you a great joy, which will be for all the people.

11 For today a Saviour has been born for you in the city of David: he is Christ the Lord.

12 And this will be a sign for you: you will find the infant wrapped in swaddling clothes and lying in a manger."

13 And suddenly there was with the Angel a multitude of the celestial army, praising God and saying,

14 "Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace to men of good will."

15 And it happened that, when the Angels had departed from them into heaven, the shepherds said to one another, "Let us cross over to Bethlehem and see this word, which has happened, which the Lord has revealed to us."

16 And they went quickly. And they found Mary and Joseph; and the infant was lying in a manger.

17 Then, upon seeing this, they understood the word that had been spoken to them about this boy.

18 And all who heard it were amazed by this, and by those things which were told to them by the shepherds.

19 But Mary kept all these words, pondering them in her heart.

20 And the shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God for all the things that they had heard and seen, just as it was told to them.

21 And after eight days were ended, so that the boy would be circumcised, his name was called JESUS, just as he was called by the Angel before he was conceived in the womb.

22 And after the days of her purification were fulfilled, according to the law of Moses, they brought him to Jerusalem, in order to present him to the Lord,

23 just as it is written in the law of the Lord, "For every male opening the womb shall be called holy to the Lord,"

24 and in order to offer a sacrifice, according to what is said in the law of the Lord, "a pair of turtledoves or two young pigeons."

25 And behold, there was a man in Jerusalem, whose name was Simeon, and this man was just and God-fearing, awaiting the consolation of Israel. And the Holy Spirit was with him.

26 And he had received an answer from the Holy Spirit: that he would not see his own death before he had seen the Christ of the Lord.

27 And he went with the Spirit to the temple. And when the child Jesus was brought in by his parents, in order to act on his behalf according to the custom of the law,

28 he also took him up, into his arms, and he blessed God and said:

29 "Now you may dismiss your servant in peace, O Lord, according to your word.

30 For my eyes have seen your salvation,

31 which you have prepared before the face of all peoples:

32 the light of revelation to the nations and the glory of your people Israel."

33 And his father and mother were wondering over these things, which were spoken about him.

34 And Simeon blessed them, and he said to his mother Mary: "Behold, this one has been set for the ruin and for the resurrection of many in Israel, and as a sign which will be contradicted.

35 And a sword will pass through your own soul, so that the thoughts of many hearts may be revealed."

36 And there was a prophetess, Anna, a daughter of Phanuel, from the tribe of Asher. She was very advanced in years, and she had lived with her husband for seven years from her virginity.

37 And then she was a widow, even to her eighty-fourth year. And without departing from the temple, she was a servant to fasting and prayer, night and day.

38 And entering at the same hour, she confessed to the Lord. And she spoke about him to all who were awaiting the redemption of Israel.

39 And after they had performed all things according to the law of the Lord, they returned to Galilee, to their city, Nazareth.

40 Now the child grew, and he was strengthened with the fullness of wisdom. And the grace of God was in him.

41 And his parents went every year to Jerusalem, at the time of the solemnity of Passover.

42 And when he had become twelve years old, they ascended to Jerusalem, according to the custom of the feast day.

43 And having completed the days, when they returned, the boy Jesus remained in Jerusalem. And his parents did not realize this.

44 But, supposing that he was in the company, they went a day's journey, seeking him among their relatives and acquaintances.

45 And not finding him, they returned to Jerusalem, seeking him.

46 And it happened that, after three days, they found him in the temple, sitting in the midst of the doctors, listening to them and questioning them.

47 But all who listened to him were astonished over his prudence and his responses.

48 And upon seeing him, they wondered. And his mother said to him: "Son, why have you acted this way toward us? Behold, your father and I were seeking you in sorrow."

49 And he said to them: "How is it that you were seeking me? For did you not know that it is necessary for me to be in these things which are of my Father?"

50 And they did not understand the word that he spoke to them.

51 And he descended with them and went to Nazareth. And he was subordinate to them. And his mother kept all these words in her heart.

52 And Jesus advanced in wisdom, and in age, and in grace, with God and men.

Luke 3

1 Then, in the fifteenth year of the reign of Tiberius Caesar, Pontius Pilate being procurator of Judea, and Herod tetrarch of Galilee, and his brother Philip tetrarch of Ituraea and of the region of Trachonitis, and Lysanias tetrarch of Abilene,

2 under the high priests Annas and Caiaphas: the word of the Lord came to John, the son of Zechariah, in the wilderness.

3 And he went into the entire region of the Jordan, preaching a baptism of repentance for the remission of sins,

4 just as it has been written in the book of the sermons of the prophet Isaiah: "The voice of one crying out in the wilderness: Prepare the way of the Lord. Make straight his paths.

5 Every valley shall be filled, and every mountain and hill shall be brought low. And what is crooked shall be made straight. And the rough paths shall be made into level ways.

6 And all flesh shall see the salvation of God."

7 Therefore, he said to the crowd that went out in order to be baptized by him: "You progeny of vipers! Who told you to flee from the approaching wrath?

8 So then, produce fruits worthy of repentance. And do not begin to say, 'We have Abraham as our father.' For I tell you that God has the power to raise up sons to Abraham from these stones.

9 For even now the axe has been placed at the root of the trees. Therefore, every tree that does not produce good fruit shall be cut down and cast into the fire."

10 And the crowed was questioning him, saying, "What then should we do?"

11 But in response, he said to them: "Whoever has two coats, let him give to those who do not have. And whoever has food, let him act similarly."

12 Now the tax collectors also came to be baptized, and they said to him, "Teacher, what should we do?"

13 But he said to them, "You should do nothing more than what has been appointed to you."

14 Then the soldiers also questioned him, saying, "And what should we do?" And he said to them: "You should strike no one, and you should not make false accusations. And be content with your pay."

15 Now all were thinking about John in their hearts, and the people were supposing that perhaps he might be the Christ.

16 John responded by saying to everyone: "Indeed, I baptize you with water. But there will arrive one stronger than me, the laces of whose shoes I am not worthy to loosen. He will baptize you in the Holy Spirit, and with fire.

17 His winnowing fan is in his hand. And he will purify his threshing floor. And he will gather the wheat into the barn. But the chaff he will burn with unquenchable fire."

18 Indeed, he also proclaimed many other things, exhorting the people.

19 But Herod the tetrarch, when he was corrected by him concerning Herodias, his brother's wife, and concerning all the evils that Herod had done,

20 added this also, above all else: that he confined John to prison.

21 Now it happened that, when all the people were being baptized, Jesus was baptized; and as he was praying, heaven was opened.

22 And the Holy Spirit, in a corporal appearance like a dove, descended upon him. And a voice came from heaven: "You are my beloved Son. In you, I am well pleased."

23 And Jesus himself was beginning to be about thirty years old, being (as it was supposed) the son of Joseph, who was of Heli, who was of Matthat,

24 who was of Levi, who was of Melchi, who was of Jannai, who was of Joseph,

25 who was of Mattathias, who was of Amos, who was of Nahum, who was of Esli, who was of Naggai,

26 who was of Maath, who was of Mattathias, who was of Semein, who was of Josech, who was of Joda,

27 who was of Joanan, who was of Rhesa, who was of Zerubbabel, who was of Shealtiel, who was of Neri,

28 who was of Melchi, who was of Addi, who was of Cosam, who was of Elmadam, who was of Er,

29 who was of Joshua, who was of Eliezer, who was of Jorim, who was of Matthat, who was of Levi,

30 who was of Simeon, who was of Judah, who was of Joseph, who was of Jonam, who was of Eliakim,

31 who was of Melea, who was of Menna, who was of Mattatha, who was of Nathan, who was of David,

32 who was of Jesse, who was of Obed, who was of Boaz, who was of Salmon, who was of Nahshon,

33 who was of Amminadab, who was of Aram, who was of Hezron, who was of Perez, who was of Judah,

34 who was of Jacob, who was of Isaac, who was of Abraham, who was of Terah, who was of Nahor,

35 who was of Serug, who was of Reu, who was of Peleg, who was of Eber, who was of Shelah,

36 who was of Cainan, who was of Arphaxad, who was of Shem, who was Of Noah, who was of Lamech,

37 who was of Methuselah, who was of Enoch, who was of Jared, who was of Mahalalel, who was of Cainan,

38 who was of Enos, who was of Seth, who was of Adam, who was of God.

Luke 4

1 And Jesus, filled with the Holy Spirit, returned from the Jordan. And he was urged by the Spirit into the wilderness

2 for forty days, and he was tested by the devil. And he ate nothing in those days. And when they were completed, he was hungry.

3 Then the devil said to him, "If you are the Son of God, speak to this stone, so that it may be made into bread."

4 And Jesus answered him, "It is written: 'Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word of God.' "

5 And the devil led him onto a high mountain, and he showed him all the kingdoms of the world in a moment of time,

6 and he said to him: "To you, I will give all this power, and its glory. For they have been handed over to me, and I give them to whomever I wish.

7 Therefore, if you will worship before me, all will be yours."

8 And in response, Jesus said to him: "It is written: 'You shall worship the Lord your God, and you shall serve him alone.' "

9 And he brought him to Jerusalem, and he set him on the parapet of the temple, and he said to him: "If you are the Son of God, cast yourself down from here.

10 For it is written that he has given his Angels charge over you, so that they may guard you,

11 and so that they may take you into their hands, lest perhaps you may hurt your foot against a stone."

12 And in response, Jesus said to him, "It is said: 'You shall not tempt the Lord your God.' "

13 And when all the temptation was completed, the devil withdrew from him, until a time.

14 And Jesus returned, in the power of the Spirit, into Galilee. And his fame spread throughout the entire region.

15 And he taught in their synagogues, and he was magnified by everyone.

16 And he went to Nazareth, where he had been raised. And he entered into the synagogue, according to his custom, on the Sabbath day. And he rose up to read.

17 And the book of the prophet Isaiah was handed to him. And as he unrolled the book, he found the place where it was written:

18 "The Spirit of the Lord is upon me; because of this, he has anointed me. He has sent me to evangelize the poor, to heal the contrite of heart,

19 to preach forgiveness to captives and sight to the blind, to release the broken into forgiveness, to preach the acceptable year of the Lord and the day of retribution."

20 And when he had rolled up the book, he returned it to the minister, and he sat down. And the eyes of everyone in the synagogue were fixed on him.

21 Then he began to say to them, "On this day, this scripture has been fulfilled in your hearing."

22 And everyone gave testimony to him. And they wondered at the words of grace that proceeded from his mouth. And they said, "Is this not the son of Joseph?"

23 And he said to them: "Certainly, you will recite to me this saying, 'Physician, heal yourself.' The many great things that we have heard were done in Capernaum, do here also in your own country."

24 Then he said: "Amen I say to you, that no prophet is accepted in his own country.

25 In truth, I say to you, there were many widows in the days of Elijah in Israel, when the heavens were closed for three years and six months, when a great famine had occurred throughout the entire land.

26 And to none of these was Elijah sent, except to Zarephath of Sidon, to a woman who was a widow.

27 And there were many lepers in Israel under the prophet Elisha. And none of these was cleansed, except Naaman the Syrian."

28 And all those in the synagogue, upon hearing these things, were filled with anger.

29 And they rose up and drove him beyond the city. And they brought him all the way to the edge of the mount, upon which their city had been built, so that they might thrown him down violently.

30 But passing through their midst, he went away.

31 And he descended to Capernaum, a city of Galilee. And there he taught them on the Sabbaths.

32 And they were astonished at his doctrine, for his word was spoken with authority.

33 And in the synagogue, there was a man who had an unclean demon, and he cried out with a loud voice,

34 saying: "Let us alone. What are we to you, Jesus of Nazareth? Have you come to destroy us? I know you who you are: the Holy One of God."

35 And Jesus rebuked him, saying, "Be silent and depart from him." And when the demon had thrown him into their midst, he departed from him, and he no longer harmed him.

36 And fear fell over them all. And they discussed this among themselves, saying: "What is this word? For with authority and power he commands the unclean spirits, and they depart."

37 And his fame spread to every place in the region.

38 Then Jesus, rising up from the synagogue, entered into the house of Simon. Now Simon's mother-in-law was in the grip of a severe fever. And they petitioned him on her behalf.

39 And standing over her, he commanded the fever, and it left her. And promptly rising up, she ministered to them.

40 Then, when the sun had set, all those who had anyone afflicted with various diseases brought them to him. Then, laying his hands on each one of them, he cured them.

41 Now demons departed from many of them, crying out and saying, "You are the son of God." And rebuking them, he would not permit them to speak. For they knew him to be the Christ.

42 Then, when it was daytime, going out, he went to a deserted place. And the crowds sought him, and they went all the way to him. And they detained him, so that he would not depart from them.

43 And he said to them, "I must also preach the kingdom of God to other cities, because it was for this reason that I was sent."

44 And he was preaching in the synagogues of Galilee.

Luke 5

1 Now it happened that, when the crowds pressed toward him, so that they might hear the word of God, he was standing beside the lake of Genesaret.

2 And he saw two boats standing beside the lake. But the fishermen had climbed down, and they were washing their nets.

3 And so, climbing into one of the boats, which belonged to Simon, he asked him to draw back a little from the land. And sitting down, he taught the crowds from the boat.

4 Then, when he had ceased speaking, he said to Simon, "Lead us into deep water, and release your nets for a catch."

5 And in response, Simon said to him: "Teacher, working throughout the night, we caught nothing. But on your word, I will release the net."

6 And when they had done this, they enclosed such a copious multitude of fish that their net was rupturing.

7 And they signaled to their associates, who were in the other boat, so that they would come and help them. And they came and filled both boats, so that they were nearly submerged.

8 But when Simon Peter had seen this, he fell down at the knees of Jesus, saying, "Depart from me, Lord, for I am a sinful man."

9 For astonishment had enveloped him, and all who were with him, at the catch of fish that they had taken.

10 Now the same was true of James and John, the sons of Zebedee, who were associates of Simon. And Jesus said to Simon: "Do not be afraid. From now on, you will be catching men."

11 And having led their boats to land, leaving behind everything, they followed him.

12 And it happened that, while he was in a certain city, behold, there was a man full of leprosy who, upon seeing Jesus and falling to his face, petitioned him, saying: "Lord, if you are willing, you are able to cleanse me."

13 And extending his hand, he touched him, saying: "I am willing. Be cleansed." And at once, the leprosy departed from him.

14 And he instructed him that he should tell no one, "But go, show yourself to the priest, and make the offering for your cleansing, just as Moses has commanded, as a testimony for them."

15 Yet word of him traveled around all the more. And great crowds came together, so that they might listen and be cured by him from their infirmities.

16 And he withdrew into the desert and prayed.

17 And it happened, on a certain day, that he again sat down, teaching. And there were Pharisees and doctors of the law sitting nearby, who had come from every town of Galilee and Judea and Jerusalem. And the power of the Lord was present, to heal them.

18 And behold, some men were carrying in the bed of a man who was paralyzed. And they sought a way to bring him in, and to place him before him.

19 And not finding a way by which they might bring him in, because of the crowd, they climbed up to the roof, and they let him down through the roof tiles with his bed, into their midst, in front of Jesus.

20 And when he saw his faith, he said, "Man, your sins are forgiven you."

21 And the scribes and Pharisees began to think, saying: "Who is this, who is speaking blasphemies? Who is able to forgive sins, except God alone?"

22 But when Jesus realized their thoughts, responding, he said to them: "What are you thinking in your hearts?

23 Which is easier to say: 'Your sins are forgiven you,' or to say, 'Rise up and walk?'

24 But so that you may know that the Son of man has authority on earth to forgive sins," he said to the paralytic, "I say to you to: Rise up, take up your bed, and go into your house."

25 And at once, rising up in their sight, he took up the bed on which he was lying, and he went away to his own house, magnifying God.

26 And astonishment took hold of everyone, and they were magnifying God. And they were filled with fear, saying: "For we have seen miracles today."

27 And after these things, he went out, and he saw a tax collector named Levi, sitting at the customs office. And he said to him, "Follow me."

28 And leaving behind everything, rising up, he followed him.

29 And Levi made a great feast for him in his own house. And there was a large crowd of tax collectors and others, who were sitting at table with them.

30 But the Pharisees and scribes were murmuring, saying to his disciples, "Why do you eat and drink with tax collectors and sinners?"

31 And responding, Jesus said to them: "It is not those who are well who need a doctor, but those who have maladies.

32 I have not come to call the just, but sinners to repentance."

33 But they said to him, "Why do the disciples of John fast frequently, and make supplications, and those of the Pharisees act similarly, while yours eat and drink?"

34 And he said to them: "How can you cause the sons of the groom to fast, while the groom is still with them?

35 But the days will come when the groom will be taken away from them, and then they will fast, in those days."

36 Then he also made a comparison for them: "For no one sews a patch from a new garment onto an old garment. Otherwise, he both disrupts the new one, and the patch from the new one does not join together with the old one.

37 And no one puts new wine into old wineskins. Otherwise, the new wine ruptures the wineskins, and it will be poured out, and the wineskins will be lost.

38 Instead, the new wine is put into new wineskins, and both are preserved.

39 And no one who is drinking the old, soon wishes for the new. For he says, 'The old is better.' "

Luke 6

1 Now it happened that, on the second first Sabbath, as he passed through the grain field, his disciples were separating the ears of grain and eating them, by rubbing them in their hands.

2 Then certain Pharisees said to them, "Why are you doing what is not lawful on the Sabbaths?"

3 And responding to them, Jesus said: "Have you not read this, what David did when he was hungry, and those who were with him?

4 How he entered into the house of God, and took the bread of the Presence, and ate it, and gave it to those who were with him, though it is not lawful for anyone to eat it, except the priests alone?"

5 And he said to them, "For the Son of man is Lord, even of the Sabbath."

6 And it happened that, on another Sabbath, he entered into the synagogue, and he taught. And there was a man there, and his right hand was withered.

7 And the scribes and Pharisees observed whether he would heal on the Sabbath, so that they might thereby find an accusation against him.

8 Yet truly, he knew their thoughts, and so he said to the man who had the withered hand, "Rise up and stand in the middle." And rising up, he stood still.

9 Then Jesus said to them: "I ask you if it is lawful on the Sabbaths to do good, or to do evil? To give health to a life, or to destroy it?"

10 And looking around at everyone, he said to the man, "Extend your hand." And he extended it. And his hand was restored.

11 Then they were filled with madness, and they discussed with one another, what, in particular, they might do about Jesus.

12 And it happened that, in those days, he went out to a mountain to pray. And he was in the prayer of God throughout the night.

13 And when daylight had arrived, he called his disciples. And he chose twelve out of them (whom he also named Apostles):

14 Simon, whom he surnamed Peter, and Andrew his brother, James and John, Philip and Bartholomew,

15 Matthew and Thomas, James of Alphaeus, and Simon who is called the Zealot,

16 and Jude of James, and Judas Iscariot, who was a traitor.

17 And descending with them, he stood in a level place with a multitude of his disciples, and a copious multitude of people from all of Judea and Jerusalem and the seacoast, and Tyre and Sidon,

18 who had come so that they might listen to him and be healed of their diseases. And those who were troubled by unclean spirits were cured.

19 And the entire crowd was trying to touch him, because power went out from him and healed all.

20 And lifting up his eyes to his disciples, he said: "Blessed are you poor, for yours is the kingdom of God.

21 Blessed are you who are hungry now, for you shall be satisfied. Blessed are you who are weeping now, for you shall laugh.

22 Blessed shall you be when men will have hated you, and when they will have separated you and reproached you, and thrown out your name as if evil, because of the Son of man.

23 Be glad in that day and exult. For behold, your reward is great in heaven. For these same things their fathers did to the prophets.

24 Yet truly, woe to you who are wealthy, for you have your consolation.

25 Woe to you who are satisfied, for you will be hungry. Woe to you who laugh now, for you will mourn and weep.

26 Woe to you when men will have blessed you. For these same things their fathers did to the false prophets.

27 But I say to you who are listening: Love your enemies. Do good to those who hate you.

28 Bless those who curse you, and pray for those who slander you.

29 And to him who strikes you on the cheek, offer the other also. And from him who takes away your coat, do not withhold even your tunic.

30 But distribute to all who ask of you. And do not ask again of him who takes away what is yours.

31 And exactly as you would want people to treat you, treat them also the same.

32 And if you love those who love you, what credit is due to you? For even sinners love those who love them.

33 And if you will do good to those who do good to you, what credit is due to you? Indeed, even sinners behave this way.

34 And if you will loan to those from whom you hope to receive, what credit is due to you? For even sinners lend to sinners, in order to receive the same in return.

35 So truly, love your enemies. Do good, and lend, hoping for nothing in return. And then your reward will be great, and you will be sons of the Most High, for he himself is kind to the ungrateful and to the wicked.

36 Therefore, be merciful, just as your Father is also merciful.

37 Do not judge, and you will not be judged. Do not condemn, and you will not be condemned. Forgive, and you will be forgiven.

38 Give, and it will be given to you: a good measure, pressed down and shaken together and overflowing, they will place upon your lap. Certainly, the same measure that you use to measure out, will be used to measure back to you again."

39 Now he told them another comparison: "How can the blind lead the blind? Would they not both fall into a pit?

40 The disciple is not above his teacher. But each one will be perfected, if he is like his teacher.

41 And why do you see the straw that is in your brother's eye, while the log that is in your own eye, you do not consider?

42 Or how can you say to your brother, 'Brother, allow me to remove the straw from your eye,' while you yourself do not see the log in your own eye? Hypocrite, first remove the log from your own eye, and then will you see clearly, so that you may lead out the straw from your brother's eye.

43 For there is no good tree which produces bad fruit, nor does an evil tree produce good fruit.

44 For each and every tree is known by its fruit. For they do not gather figs from thorns, nor do they gather the grape from the bramble bush.

45 A good man, from the good storehouse of his heart, offers what is good. And an evil man, from the evil storehouse, offers what is evil. For out of the abundance of the heart, the mouth speaks.

46 But why do you call me, 'Lord, Lord,' and not do what I say?

47 Anyone who comes to me, and listens to my words, and does them: I will reveal to you what he is like.

48 He is like a man building a house, who has dug deep and has laid the foundation upon the rock. Then, when the floodwaters came, the river was rushing against that house, and it was not able to move it. For it was founded upon the rock.

49 But whoever hears and does not do: he is like a man building his house upon the soil, without a foundation. The river rushed against it, and it soon fell down, and the ruin of that house was great."

Luke 7

1 And when he had completed all his words in the hearing of the people, he entered Capernaum.

2 Now the servant of a certain centurion was dying, due to an illness. And he was very dear to him.

3 And when he had heard about Jesus, he sent elders of the Jews to him, petitioning him, so that he would come and heal his servant.

4 And when they had come to Jesus, they petitioned him anxiously, saying to him: "He is worthy that you should provide this to him.

5 For he loves our nation, and he has built a synagogue for us."

6 Then Jesus went with them. And when he was now not far from the house, the centurion sent friends to him, saying: "Lord, do not trouble yourself. For I am not worthy that you should enter under my roof.

7 Because of this, I also did not consider myself worthy to come to you. But say the word, and my servant shall be healed.

8 For I also am a man placed under authority, having soldiers under me. And I say to one, 'Go,' and he goes; and to another, 'Come,' and he comes; and to my servant, 'Do this,' and he does it."

9 And upon hearing this, Jesus was amazed. And turning to the multitude following him, he said, "Amen I say to you, not even in Israel have I found such great faith."

10 And those who had been sent, upon returning to the house, found that the servant, who had been sick, was now healthy.

11 And it happened afterwards that he went to a city, which is called Nain. And his disciples, and an abundant crowd, went with him.

12 Then, when he had drawn near to the gate of the city, behold, a deceased person was being carried out, the only son of his mother, and she was a widow. And a large crowd from the city was with her.

13 And when the Lord had seen her, being moved by mercy over her, he said to her, "Do not weep."

14 And he drew near and touched the coffin. Then those who carried it stood still. And he said, "Young man, I say to you, arise."

15 And the dead youth sat up and began to speak. And he gave him to his mother.

16 Then fear fell over all of them. And they magnified God, saying: "For a great prophet has risen up among us," and, "For God has visited his people."

17 And this word about him went out to all of Judea and to the entire surrounding region.

18 And the disciples of John reported to him concerning all these things.

19 And John called two of his disciples, and he sent them to Jesus, saying, "Are you he who is to come, or should we wait for another?"

20 But when the men had come to him, they said: "John the Baptist has sent us to you, saying: 'Are you he who is to come, or should we wait for another?' "

21 Now in that same hour, he cured many of their diseases and wounds and evil spirits; and to many of the blind, he gave sight.

22 And responding, he said to them: "Go and report to John what you have heard and seen: that the blind see, the lame walk, the lepers are cleansed, the deaf hear, the dead rise again, the poor are evangelized.

23 And blessed is anyone who has not taken offense at me."

24 And when the messengers of John had withdrawn, he began to speak about John to the crowds. "What did you go out to the desert to see? A reed shaken by the wind?

25 Then what did you go out to see? A man clothed in soft garments? Behold, those who are in costly apparel and finery are in the houses of kings.

26 Then what did you go out to see? A prophet? Certainly, I tell you, and more than a prophet.

27 This is he of whom it is written: "Behold, I send my Angel before your face, who shall prepare your way before you."

28 For I say to you, among those born of women, no one is greater than the prophet John the Baptist. But he who is least in the kingdom of God is greater than he."

29 And upon hearing this, all the people and the tax collectors justified God, by being baptized with the baptism of John.

30 But the Pharisees and the experts in the law despised the counsel of God concerning themselves, by not being baptized by him.

31 Then the Lord said: "Therefore, to what shall I compare the men of this generation? And to what are they similar?

32 They are like children sitting in the marketplace, talking with one another, and saying: 'We sang to you, and you did not dance. We lamented, and you did not weep.'

33 For John the Baptist came, neither eating bread nor drinking wine, and you say, 'He has a demon.'

34 The Son of man came, eating and drinking, and you say, 'Behold, a voracious man and a drinker of wine, a friend of tax collectors and of sinners.'

35 But wisdom is justified by all her children."

36 Then certain Pharisees petitioned him, so that they might eat with him. And he went into the house of the Pharisee, and he reclined at table.

37 And behold, a woman who was in the city, a sinner, found out that he was reclining at table in the house of the Pharisee, so she brought an alabaster container of ointment.

38 And standing behind him, beside his feet, she began to wash his feet with tears, and she wiped them with the hair of her head, and she kissed his feet, and she anointed them with ointment.

39 Then the Pharisee, who had invited him, upon seeing this, spoke within himself, saying, "This man, if he were a prophet, would certainly know who and what kind of woman is this, who is touching him: that she is a sinner."

40 And in response, Jesus said to him, "Simon, I have something to say to you." So he said, "Speak, Teacher."

41 "A certain creditor had two debtors: one owed five hundred denarii, and the other fifty.

42 And since they did not have the ability to repay him, he forgave them both. So then, which of them loves him more?"

43 In response, Simon said, "I suppose that it is he to whom he forgave the most." And he said to him, "You have judged correctly."

44 And turning to the woman, he said to Simon: "Do you see this woman? I entered into your house. You gave me no water for my feet. But she has washed my feet with tears, and has wiped them with her hair.

45 You gave no kiss to me. But she, from the time that she entered, has not ceased to kiss my feet.

46 You did not anoint my head with oil. But she has anointed my feet with ointment.

47 Because of this, I tell you: many sins are forgiven her, because she has loved much. But he who is forgiven less, loves less."

48 Then he said to her, "Your sins are forgiven you."

49 And those who sat at table with him began to say within themselves, "Who is this, who even forgives sins?"

50 Then he said to the woman: "Your faith has brought you salvation. Go in peace."

Luke 8

1 And it happened afterwards that he was making a journey through the cities and towns, preaching and evangelizing the kingdom of God. And the twelve were with him,

2 along with certain women who had been healed of evil spirits and infirmities: Mary, who is called Magdalene, from whom seven demons had departed,

3 and Joanna, the wife of Chuza, Herod's steward, and Susanna, and many other women, who were ministering to him from their resources.

4 Then, when a very numerous crowd was gathering together and hurrying from the cities to him, he spoke using a comparison:

5 "The sower went out to sow his seed. And as he sowed, some fell beside the way; and it was trampled and the birds of the air devoured it.

6 And some fell upon rock; and having sprung up, it withered away, because it had no moisture.

7 And some fell among thorns; and the thorns, rising up with it, suffocated it.

8 And some fell upon good soil; and having sprung up, it produced fruit one hundredfold." As he said these things, he cried out, "Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear."

9 Then his disciples questioned him as to what this parable might mean.

10 And he said to them: "To you it has been given to know the mystery of the kingdom of God. But to the rest, it is in parables, so that: seeing, they may not perceive, and hearing, they may not understand.

11 Now the parable is this: The seed is the word of God.

12 And those beside the way are those who hear it, but then the devil comes and takes the word from their heart, lest by believing it they may be saved.

13 Now those upon rock are those who, when they hear it, accept the word with joy, but these have no roots. So they believe for a time, but in a time of testing, they fall away.

14 And those which fell among thorns are those who have heard it, but as they go along, they are suffocated by the concerns and riches and pleasures of this life, and so they do not yield fruit.

15 But those which were on good soil are those who, upon hearing the word with a good and noble heart, retain it, and they bring forth fruit in patience.

16 Now no one, lighting a candle, covers it with a container, or sets it under a bed. Instead, he places it on a lampstand, so that those who enter may see the light.

17 For there is nothing secret, which will not be made clear, nor is there anything hidden, which will not be known and be brought into plain sight.

18 Therefore, take care how you listen. For whoever has, it will be given to him; and whoever does not have, even what he thinks he has will be taken away from him."

19 Then his mother and brothers came to him; but they were not able to go to him because of the crowd.

20 And it was reported to him, "Your mother and your brothers are standing outside, wanting to see you."

21 And in response, he said to them, "My mother and my brothers are those who hear the word of God and do it."

22 Now it happened, on a certain day, that he climbed into a little boat with his disciples. And he said to them, "Let us make a crossing over the lake." And they embarked.

23 And as they were sailing, he slept. And a windstorm descended over the lake. And they were taking on water and were in danger.

24 Then, drawing near, they awakened him, saying, "Teacher, we are perishing." But as he rose up, he rebuked the wind and the raging water, and they ceased. And a tranquility occurred.

25 Then he said to them, "Where is your faith?" And they, being afraid, were amazed, saying to one another, "Who do you think this is, so that he commands both wind and sea, and they obey him?"

26 And they sailed to the region of the Gerasenes, which is opposite Galilee.

27 And when he had gone out to the land, a certain man met him, who had now had a demon for a long time. And he did not wear clothes, nor did he stay in a house, but among the sepulchers.

28 And when he saw Jesus, he fell down before him. And crying out in a loud voice, he said: "What is there between me and you, Jesus, Son of the Most High God? I beg you not to torture me."

29 For he was ordering the unclean spirit to depart from the man. For on many occasions, it would seize him, and he was bound with chains and held by fetters. But breaking the chains, he was driven by the demon into deserted places.

30 Then Jesus questioned him, saying, "What is your name?" And he said, "Legion," because many demons had entered into him.

31 And they petitioned him not to order them to go into the abyss.

32 And in that place, there was a herd of many swine, pasturing on the mountain. And they petitioned him to permit them to enter into them. And he permitted them.

33 Therefore, the demons departed from the man, and they entered into the swine. And the herd rushed violently down a precipice into the lake, and they were drowned.

34 And when those who were pasturing them had seen this, they fled and reported it in the city and the villages.

35 Then they went out to see what was happening, and they came to Jesus. And they found the man, from whom the demons had departed, sitting at his feet, clothed as well as in a sane mind, and they were afraid.

36 Then those who had seen this also reported to them how he had been healed from the legion.

37 And the entire multitude from the region of the Gerasenes pleaded with him to depart from them. For they were seized by a great fear. Then, climbing into the boat, he went back again.

38 And the man from whom the demons had departed pleaded with him, so that he might be with him. But Jesus sent him away, saying,

39 "Return to your house and explain to them what great things God has done for you." And he traveled through the entire city, preaching about the great things that Jesus had done for him.

40 Now it happened that, when Jesus had returned, the crowd received him. For they were all waiting for him.

41 And behold, a man came, whose name was Jairus, and he was a leader of the synagogue. And he fell down at the feet of Jesus, asking him to enter into his house.

42 For he had an only daughter, nearly twelve years old, and she was dying. And it happened that, as he was going there, he was hemmed in by the crowd.

43 And there was a certain woman, with a flow of blood for twelve years, who had paid out all her substance on physicians, and she was unable to be cured by any of them.

44 She approached him from behind, and she touched the hem of his garment. And at once the flow of her blood stopped.

45 And Jesus said, "Who is it that touched me?" But as everyone was denying it, Peter, and those who were with him, said: "Teacher, the crowd hems you in and presses upon you, and yet you say, 'Who touched me?' "

46 And Jesus said: "Someone has touched me. For I know that power has gone out from me."

47 Then the woman, upon seeing that she was not hidden, came forward, trembling, and she fell down before his feet. And she declared before all the people the reason that she had touched him, and how she had been immediately healed.

48 But he said to her: "Daughter, your faith has saved you. Go in peace."

49 While he was still speaking, someone came to the ruler of the synagogue, saying to him: "Your daughter is dead. Do not trouble him."

50 Then Jesus, upon hearing this word, replied to the father of the girl: "Do not be afraid. Only believe, and she will be saved."

51 And when he had arrived at the house, he would not permit anyone to enter with him, except Peter and James and John, and the father and mother of the girl.

52 Now all were weeping and mourning for her. But he said: "Do not weep. The girl is not dead, but only sleeping."

53 And they derided him, knowing that she had died.

54 But he, taking her by the hand, cried out, saying, "Little girl, arise."

55 And her spirit returned, and she immediately rose up. And he ordered them to give her something to eat.

56 And her parents were stupefied. And he instructed them not to tell anyone what had happened.

Luke 9

1 Then calling together the twelve Apostles, he gave them power and authority over all demons and to cure diseases.

2 And he sent them to preach the kingdom of God and to heal the infirm.

3 And he said to them: "You should take nothing for the journey, neither staff, nor traveling bag, nor bread, nor money; and you should not have two tunics.

4 And into whatever house you shall enter, lodge there, and do not move away from there.

5 And whoever will not have received you, upon departing from that city, shake off even the dust on your feet, as a testimony against them."

6 And going forth, they traveled around, through the towns, evangelizing and curing everywhere.

7 Now Herod the tetrarch heard about all the things that were being done by him, but he doubted, because it was said

8 by some, "For John has risen from the dead," yet truly, by others, "For Elijah has appeared," and by still others, "For one of the prophets from of old has risen again."

9 And Herod said: "I beheaded John. So then, who is this, about whom I hear such things?" And he sought to see him.

10 And when the Apostles returned, they explained to him all the things that they had done. And taking them with him, he withdrew to a deserted place apart, which belongs to Bethsaida.

11 But when the crowd had realized this, they followed him. And he received them and spoke to them about the kingdom of God. And those who were in need of cures, he healed.

12 Then the day began to decline. And drawing near, the twelve said to him: "Dismiss the crowds, so that, by going into the surrounding towns and villages, they may separate and find food. For we are here in a deserted place."

13 But he said to them, "You give them something to eat." And they said, "There is with us no more than five loaves and two fish, unless perhaps we are to go and buy food for this entire multitude."

14 Now there were about five thousand men. So he said to his disciples, "Have them recline to eat in groups of fifty."

15 And they did so. And they caused them all to recline to eat.

16 Then, taking the five loaves and the two fish, he gazed up to heaven, and he blessed and broke and distributed them to his disciples, in order to set them before the crowd.

17 And they all ate and were satisfied. And twelve baskets of fragments were taken up, which were left over from them.

18 And it happened that, when he was praying alone, his disciples also were with him, and he questioned them, saying: "Who do the multitudes say that I am?"

19 But they answered by saying: "John the Baptist. But some say Elijah. Yet truly, others say that one of the prophets from before has risen again."

20 Then he said to them, "But who do you say that I am?" In response, Simon Peter said, "The Christ of God."

21 But speaking sharply to them, he instructed them not to tell this to anyone,

22 saying, "For the Son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected by the elders and the leaders of the priests and the scribes, and be killed, and on the third day rise again."

23 Then he said to everyone: "If anyone is willing to come after me: let him deny himself, and take up his cross every day, and follow me.

24 For whoever will have saved his life, will lose it. Yet whoever will have lost his life for my sake, will save it.

25 For how does it benefit a man, if he were to gain the whole world, yet lose himself, or cause himself harm?

26 For whoever will be ashamed of me and of my words: of him the Son of man will be ashamed, when he will have arrived in his majesty and that of his Father and of the holy Angels.

27 And yet, I tell you a truth: There are some standing here who shall not taste death, until they see the kingdom of God."

28 And it happened that, about eight days after these words, he took Peter and James and John, and he ascended onto a mountain, so that he might pray.

29 And while he was praying, the appearance of his countenance was altered, and his vestment became white and shining.

30 And behold, two men were talking with him. And these were Moses and Elijah, appearing in majesty.

31 And they spoke of his departure, which he would accomplish at Jerusalem.

32 Yet truly, Peter and those who were with him were weighed down by sleep. And becoming alert, they saw his majesty and the two men who were standing with him.

33 And it happened that, as these were departing from him, Peter said to Jesus: "Teacher, it is good for us to be here. And so, let us make three tabernacles: one for you, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah." For he did not know what he was saying.

34 Then, as he was saying these things, a cloud came and overshadowed them. And as these were entering into the cloud, they were afraid.

35 And a voice came from the cloud, saying: "This is my beloved son. Listen to him."

36 And while the voice was being uttered, Jesus was found to be alone. And they were silent and told no one, in those days, any of these things, which they had seen.

37 But it happened on the following day that, as they were descending from the mountain, a great crowd met him.

38 And behold, a man from the crowd cried out, saying, "Teacher, I beg you, look kindly on my son, for he is my only son.

39 And behold, a spirit takes hold of him, and he suddenly cries out, and it throws him down and convulses him, so that he foams. And though it tears him apart, it leaves him only with difficulty.

40 And I asked your disciples to cast him out, and they were unable."

41 And in response, Jesus said: "O unfaithful and perverse generation! How long will I be with you and endure you? Bring your son here."

42 And as he was approaching him, the demon threw him down and convulsed him.

43 And Jesus rebuked the unclean spirit, and he healed the boy, and he restored him to his father.

44 And all were astonished at the greatness of God. And as everyone was wondering over all that he was doing, he said to his disciples: "You must set these words in your hearts. For it shall be that the Son of man will be delivered into the hands of men."

45 But they did not understood this word, and it was concealed from them, so that they did not perceive it. And they were afraid to question him about this word.

46 Now an idea entered into them, as to which of them was greater.

47 But Jesus, perceiving the thoughts of their hearts, took a child and stood him beside him.

48 And he said to them: "Whoever will receive this child in my name, receives me; and whoever receives me, receives him who sent me. For whoever is the lesser among you all, the same is greater."

49 And responding, John said: "Teacher, we saw a certain one casting out demons in your name. And we prohibited him, for he does not follow with us."

50 And Jesus said to him: "Do not prohibit him. For whoever is not against you, is for you."

51 Now it happened that, while the days of his dissipation were being completed, he steadfastly set his face to go to Jerusalem.

52 And he sent messengers before his face. And going on, they entered into a city of the Samaritans, to prepare for him.

53 And they would not receive him, because his face was going toward Jerusalem.

54 And when his disciples, James and John, had seen this, they said, "Lord, do you want us to call for fire to descend from heaven and consume them?"

55 And turning, he rebuked them, saying: "Do you not know of whose spirit you are?

56 The Son of man came, not to destroy lives, but to save them." And they went into another town.

57 And it happened that, as they were walking along the way, someone said to him, "I will follow you, wherever you will go."

58 Jesus said to him: "Foxes have dens, and the birds of the air have nests. But the Son of man has nowhere to lay his head."

59 Then he said to another, "Follow me." But he said, "Lord, permit me first to go and bury my father."

60 And Jesus said to him: "Let the dead bury their dead. But you go and announce the kingdom of God."

61 And another said: "I will follow you, Lord. But permit me first to explain this to those of my house."

62 Jesus said to him, "No one who puts his hand to the plow, and then looks back, is fit for the kingdom of God."

Luke 10

1 Then, after these things, the Lord also designated another seventy-two. And he sent them in pairs before his face, into every city and place where he was to arrive.

2 And he said to them: "Certainly the harvest is great, but the workers are few. Therefore, ask the Lord of the harvest to send workers into his harvest.

3 Go forth. Behold, I send you out like lambs among wolves.

4 Do not choose to carry a purse, nor provisions, nor shoes; and you shall greet no one along the way.

5 Into whatever house you will have entered, first say, 'Peace to this house.'

6 And if a son of peace is there, your peace will rest upon him. But if not, it will return to you.

7 And remain in the same house, eating and drinking the things that are with them. For the worker is worthy of his pay. Do not choose to pass from house to house.

8 And into whatever city you have entered and they have received you, eat what they set before you.

9 And cure the sick who are in that place, and proclaim to them, 'The kingdom of God has drawn near to you.'

10 But into whatever city you have entered and they have not received you, going out into its main streets, say:

11 'Even the dust which clings to us from your city, we wipe away against you. Yet know this: the kingdom of God has drawn near.'

12 I say to you, that in that day, Sodom will be forgiven more than that city will be.

13 Woe to you, Chorazin! Woe to you, Bethsaida! For if the miracles that have been wrought in you, had been wrought in Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago, sitting in haircloth and ashes.

14 Yet truly, Tyre and Sidon will be forgiven more in the judgment than you will be.

15 And as for you, Capernaum, who would be exalted even up to Heaven: you shall be submerged into Hell.

16 Whoever hears you, hears me. And whoever despises you, despises me. And whoever despises me, despises him who sent me."

17 Then the seventy-two returned with gladness, saying, "Lord, even the demons are subject to us, in your name."

18 And he said to them: "I was watching as Satan fell like lightning from heaven.

19 Behold, I have given you authority to tread upon serpents and scorpions, and upon all the powers of the enemy, and nothing shall hurt you.

20 Yet truly, do not choose to rejoice in this, that the spirits are subject to you; but rejoice that your names are written in heaven."

21 In the same hour, he exulted in the Holy Spirit, and he said: "I confess to you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because you have hidden these things from the wise and the prudent, and have revealed them to little ones. It is so, Father, because this way was pleasing before you.

22 All things have been delivered to me by my Father. And no one knows who the Son is, except the Father, and who the Father is, except the Son, and those to whom the Son has chosen to reveal him."

23 And turning to his disciples, he said: "Blessed are the eyes that see what you see.

24 For I say to you, that many prophets and kings wanted to see the things that you see, and they did not see them, and to hear the things that you hear, and they did not hear them."

25 And behold, a certain expert in the law rose up, testing him and saying, "Teacher, what must I do to possess eternal life?"

26 But he said to him: "What is written in the law? How do you read it?"

27 In response, he said: "You shall love the Lord your God from your whole heart, and from your whole soul, and from all your strength, and from all your mind, and your neighbor as yourself."

28 And he said to him: "You have answered correctly. Do this, and you will live."

29 But since he wanted to justify himself, he said to Jesus, "And who is my neighbor?"

30 Then Jesus, taking this up, said: "A certain man descended from Jerusalem to Jericho, and he happened upon robbers, who now also plundered him. And inflicting him with wounds, they went away, leaving him behind, half-alive.

31 And it happened that a certain priest was descending along the same way. And seeing him, he passed by.

32 And similarly a Levite, when he was near the place, also saw him, and he passed by.

33 But a certain Samaritan, being on a journey, came near him. And seeing him, he was moved by mercy.

34 And approaching him, he bound up his wounds, pouring oil and wine on them. And setting him on his pack animal, he brought him to an inn, and he took care of him.

35 And the next day, he took out two denarii, and he gave them to the proprietor, and he said: 'Take care of him. And whatever extra you will have spent, I will repay to you at my return.'

36 Which of these three, does it seem to you, was a neighbor to him who fell among the robbers?"

37 Then he said, "The one who acted with mercy toward him." And Jesus said to him, "Go, and act similarly."

38 Now it happened that, while they were traveling, he entered into a certain town. And a certain woman, named Martha, received him into her home.

39 And she had a sister, named Mary, who, while sitting beside the Lord's feet, was listening to his word.

40 Now Martha was continually busying herself with serving. And she stood still and said: "Lord, is it not a concern to you that my sister has left me to serve alone? Therefore, speak to her, so that she may help me."

41 And the Lord responded by saying to her: "Martha, Martha, you are anxious and troubled over many things.

42 And yet only one thing is necessary. Mary has chosen the best portion, and it shall not be taken away from her."

Luke 11

1 And it happened that, while he was in a certain place praying, when he ceased, one of his disciples said to him, "Lord, teach us to pray, as John also taught his disciples."

2 And he said to them: "When you are praying, say: Father, may your name be kept holy. May your kingdom come.

3 Give us this day our daily bread.

4 And forgive us our sins, since we also forgive all who are indebted to us. And lead us not into temptation."

5 And he said to them: "Which of you will have a friend and will go to him in the middle of the night, and will say to him: 'Friend, lend me three loaves,

6 because a friend of mine has arrived from a journey to me, and I do not have anything to set before him.'

7 And from within, he would answer by saying: 'Do not disturb me. The door is closed now, and my children and I are in bed. I cannot get up and give it to you.'

8 Yet if he will persevere in knocking, I tell you that, even though he would not get up and give it to him because he is a friend, yet due to his continued insistence, he will get up and give him whatever he needs.

9 And so I say to you: Ask, and it shall be given to you. Seek, and you shall find. Knock, and it shall be opened to you.

10 For everyone who asks, receives. And whoever seeks, finds. And whoever knocks, it shall be opened to him.

11 So then, who among you, if he asks his father for bread, he would give him a stone? Or if he asks for a fish, he would give him a serpent, instead of a fish?

12 Or if he will ask for an egg, he would offer to him a scorpion?

13 Therefore, if you, being evil, know how to give good things to your sons, how much more will your Father give, from heaven, a spirit of goodness to those who ask him?"

14 And he was casting out a demon, and the man was mute. But when he had cast out the demon, the mute man spoke, and so the crowds were amazed.

15 But some of them said, "It is by Beelzebub, the leader of demons, that he casts out demons."

16 And others, testing him, required a sign from heaven of him.

17 But when he perceived their thoughts, he said to them: "Every kingdom divided against itself will become desolate, and house will fall upon house.

18 So then, if Satan is also divided against himself, how will his kingdom stand? For you say that it is by Beelzebub that I cast out demons.

19 But if I cast out demons by Beelzebub, by whom do your own sons cast them out? Therefore, they shall be your judges.

20 Moreover, if it is by the finger of God that I cast out demons, then certainly the kingdom of God has overtaken you.

21 When a strong armed man guards his entrance, the things that he possesses are at peace.

22 But if a stronger one, overwhelming him, has defeated him, he will take away all his weapons, in which he trusted, and he will distribute his spoils.

23 Whoever is not with me, is against me. And whoever does not gather with me, scatters.

24 When an unclean spirit has departed from a man, he walks through waterless places, seeking rest. And not finding any, he says: 'I will return to my house, from which I departed.'

25 And when he has arrived, he finds it swept clean and decorated.

26 Then he goes, and he takes in seven other spirits with him, more wicked than himself, and they enter and live there. And so, the end of that man is made worse the beginning."

27 And it happened that, when he was saying these things, a certain woman from the crowd, lifting up her voice, said to him, "Blessed is the womb that bore you and the breasts that nursed you."

28 Then he said, "Yes, but moreover: blessed are those who hear the word of God and keep it."

29 Then, as the crowds were quickly gathering, he began to say: "This generation is a wicked generation: it seeks a sign. But no sign will be given to it, except the sign of the prophet Jonah.

30 For just as Jonah was a sign to the Ninevites, so also will the Son of man be to this generation.

31 The queen of the South will rise up, at the judgment, with the men of this generation, and she will condemn them. For she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon. And behold, more than Solomon is here.

32 The men of Nineveh will rise up, at the judgment, with this generation, and they will condemn it. For at the preaching of Jonah, they repented. And behold, more than Jonah is here.

33 No one lights a candle and places it in hiding, nor under a bushel basket, but upon a lampstand, so that those who enter may see the light.

34 Your eye is the light of your body. If your eye is wholesome, your entire body will be filled with light. But if it is wicked, then even your body will be darkened.

35 Therefore, take care, lest the light that is within you become darkness.

36 So then, if your entire body becomes filled with light, not having any part in darkness, then it will be entirely light, and, like a shining lamp, it will illuminate you."

37 And as he was speaking, a certain Pharisee asked him to eat with him. And going inside, he sat down to eat.

38 But the Pharisee began to say, thinking within himself: "Why might it be that he has not washed before eating?"

39 And the Lord said to him: "You Pharisees today clean what is outside the cup and the plate, but what is inside of you is full of plunder and iniquity.

40 Fools! Did not he who made what is outside, indeed also make what is inside?

41 Yet truly, give what is above as alms, and behold, all things are clean for you.

42 But woe to you, Pharisees! For you tithe mint and rue and every herb, but you ignore judgment and the charity of God. But these things you ought to have done, without omitting the others.

43 Woe to you, Pharisees! For you love the first seats in the synagogues, and greetings in the marketplace.

44 Woe to you! For you are like graves that are not noticeable, so that men walk over them without realizing it."

45 Then one of the experts in the law, in response, said to him, "Teacher, in saying these things, you bring an insult against us as well."

46 So he said: "And woe to you experts in the law! For you weigh men down with burdens which they are not able to bear, but you yourselves do not touch the weight with even one of your fingers.

47 Woe to you, who build the tombs of the prophets, while it is your fathers who killed them!

48 Clearly, you are testifying that you consent to the actions of your fathers, because even though they killed them, you build their sepulchers.

49 Because of this also, the wisdom of God said: I will send to them Prophets and Apostles, and some of these they will kill or persecute,

50 so that the blood of all the Prophets, which has been shed since the foundation of the world, may be charged against this generation:

51 from the blood of Abel, even to the blood of Zachariah, who perished between the altar and the sanctuary. So I say to you: it will be required of this generation!

52 Woe to you, experts in the law! For you have taken away the key of knowledge. You yourselves do not enter, and those who were entering, you would have prohibited."

53 Then, while he was saying these things to them, the Pharisees and the experts in the law began to insist strongly that he restrain his mouth about many things.

54 And waiting to ambush him, they sought something from his mouth that they might seize upon, in order to accuse him.

Luke 12

1 Then, as great crowds were standing so close that they were stepping on one another, he began to say to his disciples: "Beware of the leaven of the Pharisees, which is hypocrisy.

2 For there is nothing covered, which will not be revealed, nor anything hidden, which will not be known.

3 For the things that you have spoken in darkness will be declared in the light. And what you have said in the ear in bedrooms will be proclaimed from the housetops.

4 So I say to you, my friends: Do not be fearful of those who kill the body, and afterwards have no more that they can do.

5 But I will reveal to you whom you should fear. Fear him who, after he will have killed, has the power to cast into Hell. So I say to you: Fear him.

6 Are not five sparrows sold for two small coins? And yet not one of these is forgotten in the sight of God.

7 But even the very hairs of your head have all been numbered. Therefore, do not be afraid. You are worth more than many sparrows.

8 But I say to you: Everyone who will have confessed me before men, the Son of man will also confess him before the Angels of God.

9 But everyone who will have denied me before men, he will be denied before the Angels of God.

10 And everyone who speaks a word against the Son of man, it will be forgiven of him. But of him who will have blasphemed against the Holy Spirit, it will not be forgiven.

11 And when they will lead you to the synagogues, and to magistrates and authorities, do not choose to be worried about how or what you will answer, or about what you might say.

12 For the Holy Spirit will teach you, in the same hour, what you must say."

13 And someone from the crowd said to him, "Teacher, tell my brother to share the inheritance with me."

14 But he said to him, "Man, who has appointed me as judge or arbitrator over you?"

15 So he said to them: "Be cautious and wary of all avarice. For a person's life is not found in the abundance of the things that he possesses."

16 Then he spoke to them using a comparison, saying: "The fertile land of a certain wealthy man produced crops.

17 And he thought within himself, saying: 'What should I do? For I have nowhere to gather together my crops.'

18 And he said: 'This is what I will do. I will tear down my barns and build larger ones. And into these, I will gather all the things that have been grown for me, as well as my goods.

19 And I will say to my soul: Soul, you have many goods, stored up for many years. Relax, eat, drink, and be cheerful.'

20 But God said to him: 'Foolish one, this very night they require your soul of you. To whom, then, will those things belong, which you have prepared?'

21 So it is with him who stores up for himself, and is not wealthy with God."

22 And he said to his disciples: "And so I say to you: Do not choose to be anxious about your life, as to what you may eat, nor about your body, as to what you will wear.

23 Life is more than food, and the body is more than clothing.

24 Consider the ravens. For they neither sow nor reap; there is no storehouse or barn for them. And yet God pastures them. How much more are you, compared to them?

25 But which of you, by thinking, is able to add one cubit to his stature?

26 Therefore, if you are not capable, in what is so little, why be anxious about the rest?

27 Consider the lilies, how they grow. They neither work nor weave. But I say to you, not even Solomon, in all his glory, was clothed like one of these.

28 Therefore, if God so clothes the grass, which is in the field today and thrown into the furnace tomorrow, how much more you, O little in faith?

29 And so, do not choose to inquire as to what you will eat, or what you will drink. And do not choose to be lifted up on high.

30 For all these things are sought by the Gentiles of the world. And your Father knows that you have need of these things.

31 Yet truly, seek first the kingdom of God, and his justice, and all these things shall be added to you.

32 Do not be afraid, little flock; for it has pleased your Father to give you the kingdom.

33 Sell what you possess, and give alms. Make for yourselves purses that will not wear out, a treasure that will not fall short, in heaven, where no thief approaches, and no moth corrupts.

34 For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also.

35 Let your waists be girded, and let lamps be burning in your hands.

36 And let you yourselves be like men awaiting their lord, when he will return from the wedding; so that, when he arrives and knocks, they may open to him promptly.

37 Blessed are those servants whom the Lord, when he returns, will find being vigilant. Amen I say to you, that he will gird himself and have them sit down to eat, while he, continuing on, will minister to them.

38 And if he will return in the second watch, or if in the third watch, and if he will find them to be so: then blessed are those servants.

39 But know this: that if the father of the family knew at what hour the thief would arrive, he would certainly stand watch, and he would not permit his house to be broken into.

40 You also must be prepared. For the Son of man will return at an hour that you will not realize."

41 Then Peter said to him, "Lord, are you telling this parable to us, or also to everyone?"

42 So the Lord said: "Who do you think is the faithful and prudent steward, whom his Lord has appointed over his family, in order to give them their measure of wheat in due time?

43 Blessed is that servant if, when his Lord will return, he will find him acting in this manner.

44 Truly I say to you, that he will appoint him over all that he possesses.

45 But if that servant will have said in his heart, 'My Lord has made a delay in his return,' and if he has begun to strike the men and women servants, and to eat and drink, and to be inebriated,

46 then the Lord of that servant will return on a day which he hoped not, and at an hour which he knew not. And he will separate him, and he will place his portion with that of the unfaithful.

47 And that servant, who knew the will of his Lord, and who did not prepare and did not act according to his will, will be beaten many times over.

48 Yet he who did not know, and who acted in a way that deserves a beating, will be beaten fewer times. So then, of all to whom much has been given, much will be required. And of those to whom much has been entrusted, even more will be asked.

49 I have come to cast a fire upon the earth. And what should I desire, except that it may be kindled?

50 And I have a baptism, with which I am to be baptized. And how I am constrained, even until it may be accomplished!

51 Do you think that I have come to give peace to the earth? No, I tell you, but division.

52 For from this time on, there will be five in one house: divided as three against two, and as two against three.

53 A father will be divided against a son, and a son against his father; a mother against a daughter and a daughter against a mother; a mother-in-law against her daughter-in-law, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law."

54 And he also said to the crowds: "When you see a cloud rising from the setting of the sun, immediately you say, 'A rain cloud is coming.' And so it does.

55 And when a south wind is blowing, you say, 'It will be hot.' And so it is.

56 You hypocrites! You discern the face of the heavens, and of the earth, yet how is it that you do not discern this time?

57 And why do you not, even among yourselves, judge what is just?

58 So, when you are going with your adversary to the ruler, while you are on the way, make an effort to be freed from him, lest perhaps he may lead you to the judge, and the judge may deliver you to the officer, and the officer may cast you into prison.

59 I tell you, you will not depart from there, until you have paid the very last coin."

Luke 13

1 And there were present, at that very time, some who were reporting about the Galileans, whose blood Pilate mixed with their sacrifices.

2 And responding, he said to them: "Do you think that these Galileans must have sinned more than all other Galileans, because they suffered so much?

3 No, I tell you. But unless you repent, you will all perish similarly.

4 And those eighteen upon whom the tower of Siloam fell and killed them, do you think that they also were greater transgressors than all the men living in Jerusalem?

5 No, I tell you. But if you do not repent, you will all perish similarly."

6 And he also told this parable: "A certain man had a fig tree, which was planted in his vineyard. And he came seeking fruit on it, but found none.

7 Then he said to the cultivator of the vineyard: 'Behold, for these three years I came seeking fruit on this fig tree, and I have found none. Therefore, cut it down. For why should it even occupy the land?'

8 But in response, he said to him: 'Lord, let it be for this year also, during which time I will dig around it and add fertilizer.

9 And, indeed, it should bear fruit. But if not, in the future, you shall cut it down.' "

10 Now he was teaching in their synagogue on the Sabbaths.

11 And behold, there was a woman who had a spirit of infirmity for eighteen years. And she was bent over; and she was unable to look upwards at all.

12 And when Jesus saw her, he called her to himself, and he said to her, "Woman, you are released from your infirmity."

13 And he laid his hands upon her, and immediately she was straightened, and she glorified God.

14 Then, as a result, the ruler of the synagogue became angry that Jesus had cured on the Sabbath, and he said to the crowd: "There are six days on which you ought to work. Therefore, come and be cured on those, and not on the day of the Sabbath."

15 Then the Lord said to him in response: "You hypocrites! Does not each one of you, on the Sabbath, release his ox or donkey from the stall, and lead it to water?

16 So then, should not this daughter of Abraham, whom Satan has bound for lo these eighteen years, be released from this restraint on the day of the Sabbath?"

17 And as he was saying these things, all his adversaries were ashamed. And all the people rejoiced in everything that was being done gloriously by him.

18 And so he said: "To what is the kingdom of God similar, and to what figure shall I compare it?

19 It is like a grain of mustard seed, which a man took and cast into his garden. And it grew, and it became a great tree, and the birds of the air rested in its branches."

20 And again, he said: "To what figure shall I compare the kingdom of God?

21 It is like leaven, which a woman took and hid in three measures of fine wheat flour, until it was entirely leavened."

22 And he was traveling through the cities and towns, teaching and making his way to Jerusalem.

23 And someone said to him, "Lord, are they few who are saved?" But he said to them:

24 "Strive to enter through the narrow gate. For many, I tell you, will seek to enter and not be able.

25 Then, when the father of the family will have entered and shut the door, you will begin to stand outside and to knock at the door, saying, 'Lord, open to us.' And in response, he will say to you, 'I do not know where you are from.'

26 Then you will begin to say, 'We ate and drank in your presence, and you taught in our streets.'

27 And he will say to you: 'I do not know where you are from. Depart from me, all you workers of iniquity!'

28 In that place, there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth, when you see Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob, and all the prophets, in the kingdom of God, yet you yourselves are expelled outside.

29 And they will arrive from the East, and the West, and the North, and the South; and they will recline at table in the kingdom of God.

30 And behold, those who are last will be first, and those who are first will be last."

31 On the same day, some of the Pharisees approached, saying to him: "Depart, and go away from here. For Herod wishes to kill you."

32 And he said to them: "Go and tell that fox: 'Behold, I cast out demons and accomplish healings, today and tomorrow. And on the third day I reach the end.'

33 Yet truly, it is necessary for me to walk today and tomorrow and the following day. For it does not fall to a prophet to perish beyond Jerusalem.

34 Jerusalem, Jerusalem! You kill the prophets, and you stone those who are sent to you. Daily, I wanted to gather together your children, in the manner of a bird with her nest under her wings, but you were not willing!

35 Behold, your house will be left desolate for you. But I say to you, that you shall not see me, until it happens that you say: 'Blessed is he who has arrived in the name of the Lord.' "

Luke 14

1 And it happened that, when Jesus entered the house of a certain leader of the Pharisees on the Sabbath to eat bread, they were observing him.

2 And behold, a certain man before him was afflicted with edema.

3 And responding, Jesus spoke to the experts in the law and to the Pharisees, saying, "Is it lawful to cure on the Sabbath?"

4 But they kept silent. Yet truly, taking hold of him, he healed him and sent him away.

5 And responding to them, he said, "Which of you will have a donkey or an ox fall into a pit, and will not promptly pull him out, on the day of the Sabbath?"

6 And they were unable to respond to him about these things.

7 Then he also told a parable, to those who were invited, noticing how they chose the first seats at the table, saying to them:

8 "When you are invited to a wedding, do not sit down in the first place, lest perhaps someone more honored than yourself may have been invited by him.

9 And then he who called both you and him, approaching, may say to you, 'Give this place to him.' And then you would begin, with shame, to take the last place.

10 But when you are invited, go, sit down in the lowest place, so that, when he who invited you arrives, he may say to you, 'Friend, go up higher.' Then you will have glory in the sight of those who sit at table together with you.

11 For everyone who exalts himself shall be humbled, and whoever humbles himself shall be exalted."

12 Then he also said to the one who had invited him: "When you prepare a lunch or dinner, do not choose to call your friends, or your brothers, or your relatives, or your wealthy neighbors, lest perhaps they might then invite you in return and repayment would made to you.

13 But when you prepare a feast, call the poor, the disabled, the lame, and the blind.

14 And you will be blessed because they do not have a way to repay you. So then, your recompense will be in the resurrection of the just."

15 When someone sitting at table with him had heard these things, he said to him, "Blessed is he who will eat bread in the kingdom of God."

16 So he said to him: "A certain man prepared a great feast, and he invited many.

17 And he sent his servant, at the hour of the feast, to tell the invited to come; for now everything was ready.

18 And at once they all began to make excuses. The first said to him: 'I bought a farm, and I need to go out and see it. I ask you to excuse me.'

19 And another said: 'I bought five yoke of oxen, and I am going to examine them. I ask you to excuse me.'

20 And another said, 'I have taken a wife, and therefore I am not able to go.'

21 And returning, the servant reported these things to his lord. Then the father of the family, becoming angry, said to his servant: 'Go out quickly into the streets and neighborhoods of the city. And lead here the poor, and the disabled, and the blind, and the lame.'

22 And the servant said: 'It has been done, just as you ordered, lord, and there is still room.'

23 And the lord said to the servant: 'Go out to the highways and hedges, and compel them to enter, so that my house may be filled.

24 For I tell you, that none of those men who were invited will taste of my feast.' "

25 Now great crowds traveled with him. And turning around, he said to them:

26 "If anyone comes to me, and does not hate his father, and mother, and wife, and children, and brothers, and sisters, and yes, even his own life, he is not able to be my disciple.

27 And whoever does not bear his cross and come after me, is not able to be my disciple.

28 For who among you, wanting to build a tower, would not first sit down and determine the costs that are required, to see if he has the means to complete it?

29 Otherwise, after he will have laid the foundation and not been able to finish it, everyone who sees it may begin to mock him,

30 saying: 'This man began to build what he was not able to finish.'

31 Or, what king, advancing to engage in war against another king, would not first sit down and consider whether he may be able, with ten thousand, to meet one who comes against him with twenty thousand?

32 If not, then while the other is still far away, sending a delegation, he would ask him for terms of peace.

33 Therefore, everyone of you who does not renounce all that he possesses is not able to be my disciple.

34 Salt is good. But if the salt has lost its flavor, with what will it be seasoned?

35 It is useful neither in soil, nor in manure, so instead, it shall be thrown away. Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear."

Luke 15

1 Now tax collectors and sinners were drawing near to him, so that they might listen to him.

2 And the Pharisees and the scribes murmured, saying, "This one accepts sinners and eats with them."

3 And he told this parable to them, saying:

4 "What man among you, who has one hundred sheep, and if he will have lost one of them, would not leave the ninety-nine in the desert and go after the one whom he had lost, until he finds it?

5 And when he has found it, he places it on his shoulders, rejoicing.

6 And returning home, he calls together his friends and neighbors, saying to them: 'Congratulate me! For I have found my sheep, which had been lost.'

7 I say to you, that there will be so much more joy in heaven over one sinner repenting, than over the ninety-nine just, who do not need to repent.

8 Or what woman, having ten drachmas, if she will have lost one drachma, would not light a candle, and sweep the house, and diligently search until she finds it?

9 And when she has found it, she calls together her friends and neighbors, saying: 'Rejoice with me! For I have found the drachma, which I had lost.'

10 So I say to you, there will be joy before the Angels of God over even one sinner who is repentant."

11 And he said: "A certain man had two sons.

12 And the younger of them said to the father, 'Father, give me the portion of your estate which would go to me.' And he divided the estate between them.

13 And after not many days, the younger son, gathering it all together, set out on a long journey to a distant region. And there, he dissipated his substance, living in luxury.

14 And after he had consumed it all, a great famine occurred in that region, and he began to be in need.

15 And he went and attached himself to one of the citizens of that region. And he sent him to his farm, in order to feed the swine.

16 And he wanted to fill his belly with the scraps that the swine ate. But no one would give it to him.

17 And returning to his senses, he said: 'How many hired hands in my father's house have abundant bread, while I perish here in famine!

18 I shall rise up and go to my father, and I will say to him: Father, I have sinned against heaven and before you.

19 I am not worthy to be called your son. Make me one of your hired hands.'

20 And rising up, he went to his father. But while he was still at a distance, his father saw him, and he was moved with compassion, and running to him, he fell upon his neck and kissed him.

21 And the son said to him: 'Father, I have sinned against heaven and before you. Now I am not worthy to be called your son.'

22 But the father said to his servants: 'Quickly! Bring out the best robe, and clothe him with it. And put a ring on his hand and shoes on his feet.

23 And bring the fatted calf here, and kill it. And let us eat and hold a feast.

24 For this son of mine was dead, and has revived; he was lost, and is found.' And they began to feast.

25 But his elder son was in the field. And when he returned and drew near to the house, he heard music and dancing.

26 And he called one of the servants, and he questioned him as to what these things meant.

27 And he said to him: 'Your brother has returned, and your father has killed the fatted calf, because he has received him safely.'

28 Then he became indignant, and he was unwilling to enter. Therefore, his father, going out, began to plead with him.

29 And in response, he said to his father: 'Behold, I have been serving you for so many years. And I have never transgressed your commandment. And yet, you have never given me even a young goat, so that I might feast with my friends.

30 Yet after this son of yours returned, who has devoured his substance with loose women, you have killed the fatted calf for him.'

31 But he said to him: 'Son, you are with me always, and all that I have is yours.

32 But it was necessary to feast and to rejoice. For this brother of yours was dead, and has revived; he was lost, and is found.' "

Luke 16

1 And he also said to his disciples: "A certain man was wealthy, and he had a steward of his estate. And this man was accused to him of having dissipated his goods.

2 And he called him and said to him: 'What is this that I hear about you? Give an account of your stewardship. For you can no longer be my steward.'

3 And the steward said within himself: 'What shall I do? For my lord is taking the stewardship away from me. I am not strong enough to dig. I am too ashamed to beg.

4 I know what I will do so that, when I have been removed from the stewardship, they may receive me into their houses.'

5 And so, calling together each one of his lord's debtors, he said to the first, 'How much do you owe my lord?'

6 So he said, 'One hundred jars of oil.' And he said to him, 'Take your invoice, and quickly, sit down and write fifty.'

7 Next, he said to another, 'In truth, how much do you owe?' And he said, 'One hundred measures of wheat.' He said to him, 'Take your record books, and write eighty.'

8 And the lord praised the iniquitous steward, in that he had acted prudently. For the sons of this age are more prudent with their generation than are the sons of light.

9 And so I say to you, make friends for yourself using iniquitous mammon, so that, when you will have passed away, they may receive you into the eternal tabernacles.

10 Whoever is faithful in what is least, is also faithful in what is greater. And whoever is unjust in what is small, is also unjust in what is greater.

11 So then, if you have not been faithful with iniquitous mammon, who will trust you with what is true?

12 And if you have not been faithful with what belongs to another, who will give you what is yours?

13 No servant is able to serve two lords. For either he will hate the one and love the other, or he will cling to the one and despise the other. You cannot serve God and mammon."

14 But the Pharisees, who were greedy, were listening to all these things. And they ridiculed him.

15 And he said to them: "You are the ones who justify yourselves in the sight of men. But God knows your hearts. For what is lifted up by men is an abomination in the sight of God.

16 The law and the prophets were until John. Since then, the kingdom of God is being evangelized, and everyone acts with violence toward it.

17 But it is easier for heaven and earth to pass away, than for one dot of the law to fall away.

18 Everyone who divorces his wife and marries another commits adultery. And whoever marries her who has been divorced by her husband commits adultery.

19 A certain man was wealthy, and he was clothed in purple and in fine linen. And he feasted splendidly every day.

20 And there was a certain beggar, named Lazarus, who lay at his gate, covered with sores,

21 wanting to be filled with the crumbs which were falling from the wealthy man's table. But no one gave it to him. And even the dogs came and licked his sores.

22 Then it happened that the beggar died, and he was carried by the Angels into the bosom of Abraham. Now the wealthy man also died, and he was entombed in Hell.

23 Then lifting up his eyes, while he was in torments, he saw Abraham far away, and Lazarus in his bosom.

24 And crying out, he said: 'Father Abraham, take pity on me and send Lazarus, so that he may dip the tip of his finger in water to refresh my tongue. For I am tortured in this fire.'

25 And Abraham said to him: 'Son, recall that you received good things in your life, and in comparison, Lazarus received bad things. But now he is consoled, and truly you are tormented.

26 And besides all this, between us and you a great chaos has been established, so that those who might want to cross from here to you are not able, nor can someone cross from there to here.'

27 And he said: 'Then, father, I beg you to send him to my father's house, for I have five brothers,

28 so that he may testify to them, lest they also come into this place of torments.'

29 And Abraham said to him: 'They have Moses and the prophets. Let them listen to them.'

30 So he said: 'No, father Abraham. But if someone were to go to them from the dead, they would repent.'

31 But he said to him: 'If they will not listen to Moses and the prophets, neither will they believe even if someone has resurrected from the dead.' "

Luke 17

1 And he said to his disciples: "It is impossible for scandals not to occur. But woe to him through whom they come!

2 It would be better for him if a millstone were placed around his neck and he were thrown into the sea, than to lead astray one of these little ones.

3 Be attentive to yourselves. If your brother has sinned against you, correct him. And if he has repented, forgive him.

4 And if he has sinned against you seven times a day, and seven times a day has turned back to you, saying, 'I am sorry,' then forgive him."

5 And the Apostles said to the Lord, "Increase our faith."

6 But the Lord said: "If you have faith like a grain of mustard seed, you may say to this mulberry tree, 'Be uprooted, and be transplanted into the sea.' And it would obey you.

7 But which of you, having a servant plowing or feeding cattle, would say to him, as he was returning from the field, 'Come in immediately; sit down to eat,'

8 and would not say to him: 'Prepare my dinner; gird yourself and minister to me, while I eat and drink; and after these things, you shall eat and drink?'

9 Would he be grateful to that servant, for doing what he commanded him to do?

10 I think not. So too, when you have done all these things that have been taught to you, you should say: 'We are useless servants. We have done what we should have done.' "

11 And it happened that, while he was traveling to Jerusalem, he passed through the midst of Samaria and Galilee.

12 And as he was entering a certain town, ten leprous men met him, and they stood at a distance.

13 And they lifted up their voice, saying, "Jesus, Teacher, take pity on us."

14 And when he saw them, he said, "Go, show yourselves to the priests." And it happened that, as they were going, they were cleansed.

15 And one of them, when he saw that he was cleansed, returned, magnifying God with a loud voice.

16 And he fell face down before his feet, giving thanks. And this one was a Samaritan.

17 And in response, Jesus said: "Were not ten made clean? And so where are the nine?

18 Was no one found who would return and give glory to God, except this foreigner?"

19 And he said to him: "Rise up, go forth. For your faith has saved you."

20 Then he was questioned by the Pharisees: "When does the kingdom of God arrive?" And in response, he said to them: "The kingdom of God arrives unobserved.

21 And so, they will not say, 'Behold, it is here,' or 'Behold, it is there.' For behold, the kingdom of God is within you."

22 And he said to his disciples: "The time will come when you will desire to see one day of the Son of man, and you will not see it.

23 And they will say to you, 'Behold, he is here,' and 'Behold, he is there.' Do not choose to go out, and do not follow them.

24 For just as lightning flashes from under heaven and shines to whatever is under heaven, so also will the Son of man be in his day.

25 But first he must suffer many things and be rejected by this generation.

26 And just as it happened in the days of Noah, so also will it be in the days of the Son of man.

27 They were eating and drinking; they were taking wives and being given in marriage, even until the day that Noah entered the ark. And the flood came and destroyed them all.

28 It shall be similar to what happened in the days of Lot. They were eating and drinking; they were buying and selling; they were planting and building.

29 Then, on the day that Lot departed from Sodom, it rained fire and brimstone from heaven, and it destroyed them all.

30 According to these things, so shall it be in the day when the Son of man will be revealed.

31 In that hour, whoever will be on the rooftop, with his goods in the house, let him not descend to take them. And whoever will be in the field, similarly, let him not turn back.

32 Remember Lot's wife.

33 Whoever has sought to save his life, will lose it; and whoever has lost it, will bring it back to life.

34 I say to you, in that night, there will be two in one bed. One will be taken up, and the other will be left behind.

35 Two will be at the grindstone together. One will be taken up, and the other will be left behind. Two will be in the field. One will be taken up, and the other will be left behind."

36 Responding, they said to him, "Where, Lord?"

37 And he said to them, "Wherever the body will be, in that place also, the eagles shall be gathered together."

Luke 18

1 Now he also told them a parable, that we should continually pray and not cease,

2 saying: "There was a certain judge in a certain city, who did not fear God and did not respect man.

3 But there was a certain widow in that city, and she went to him, saying, 'Vindicate me from my adversary.'

4 And he refused to do so for a long time. But afterwards, he said within himself: 'Even though I do not fear God, nor respect man,

5 yet because this widow is pestering me, I will vindicate her, lest by returning, she may, in the end, wear me out.' "

6 Then the Lord said: "Listen to what the unjust judge said.

7 So then, will not God grant the vindication of his elect, who cry out to him day and night? Or will he continue to endure them?

8 I tell you that he will quickly bring vindication to them. Yet truly, when the Son of man returns, do you think that he will find faith on earth?"

9 Now about certain persons who consider themselves to be just, while disdaining others, he told also this parable:

10 "Two men ascended to the temple, in order to pray. One was a Pharisee, and the other was a tax collector.

11 Standing, the Pharisee prayed within himself in this way: 'O God, I give thanks to you that I am not like the rest of men: robbers, unjust, adulterers, even as this tax collector chooses to be.

12 I fast twice between Sabbaths. I give tithes from all that I possess.'

13 And the tax collector, standing at a distance, was not willing to even lift up his eyes to heaven. But he struck his chest, saying: 'O God, be merciful to me, a sinner.'

14 I say to you, this one descended to his house justified, but not the other. For everyone who exalts himself will be humbled; and whoever humbles himself will be exalted."

15 And they were bringing little children to him, so that he might touch them. And when the disciples saw this, they rebuked them.

16 But Jesus, calling them together, said: "Allow the children to come to me, and do not be an obstacle to them. For of such is the kingdom of God.

17 Amen, I say to you, whoever will not accept the kingdom of God like a child, will not enter into it."

18 And a certain leader questioned him, saying: "Good teacher, what should I do to possess eternal life?"

19 Then Jesus said to him: "Why do you call me good? No one is good except God alone.

20 You know the commandments: You shall not kill. You shall not commit adultery. You shall not steal. You shall not give false testimony. Honor your father and mother."

21 And he said, "I have kept all these things from my youth."

22 And when Jesus heard this, he said to him: "One thing is still lacking for you. Sell all the things that you have, and give to the poor. And then you will have treasure in heaven. And come, follow me."

23 When he heard this, he became very sorrowful. For he was very rich.

24 Then Jesus, seeing him brought to sorrow, said: "How difficult it is for those who have money to enter into the kingdom of God!

25 For it is easier for a camel to pass through the eye of a needle, than for a wealthy man to enter into the kingdom of God."

26 And those who were listening to this said, "Then who is able to be saved?"

27 He said to them, "Things that are impossible with men are possible with God."

28 And Peter said, "Behold, we have left everything, and we have followed you."

29 And he said to them: "Amen, I say to you, there is no one who has left behind home, or parents, or brothers, or a wife, or children, for the sake of the kingdom of God,

30 who will not receive much more in this time, and in the age to come eternal life."

31 Then Jesus took the twelve aside, and he said to them: "Behold, we are ascending to Jerusalem, and everything shall be completed which was written by the prophets about the Son of man.

32 For he will be handed over to the Gentiles, and he will be mocked and scourged and spit upon.

33 And after they have scourged him, they will kill him. And on the third day, he will rise again."

34 But they understood none of these things. For this word was concealed from them, and they did not understand the things that were said.

35 Now it happened that, as he was approaching Jericho, a certain blind man was sitting beside the way, begging.

36 And when he heard the multitude passing by, he asked what this was.

37 And they told him that Jesus of Nazareth was passing by.

38 And he cried out, saying, "Jesus, Son of David, take pity on me!"

39 And those who were passing by rebuked him, so that he would be silent. Yet truly, he cried out all the more, "Son of David, take pity on me!"

40 Then Jesus, standing still, ordered him to be brought to him. And when he had drawn near, he questioned him,

41 saying, "What do you want, that I might do for you?" So he said, "Lord, that I may see."

42 And Jesus said to him: "Look around. Your faith has saved you."

43 And immediately he saw. And he followed him, magnifying God. And all the people, when they saw this, gave praise to God.

Luke 19

1 And having entered, he walked through Jericho.

2 And behold, there was a man named Zacchaeus. And he was the leader of the tax collectors, and he was wealthy.

3 And he sought to see Jesus, to see who he was. But he was unable to do so, because of the crowd, for he was small in stature.

4 And running ahead, he climbed up a sycamore tree, so that he might see him. For he was to pass near there.

5 And when he had arrived at the place, Jesus looked up and saw him, and he said to him: "Zacchaeus, hurry down. For today, I should lodge in your house."

6 And hurrying, he came down, and he received him joyfully.

7 And when they all saw this, they murmured, saying that he had turned aside to a sinful man.

8 But Zacchaeus, standing still, said to the Lord: "Behold, Lord, one half of my goods I give to the poor. And if I have cheated anyone in any matter, I will repay him fourfold."

9 Jesus said to him: "Today, salvation has come to this house; because of this, he too is a son of Abraham.

10 For the Son of man has come to seek and to save what had been lost."

11 As they were listening to these things, continuing on, he spoke a parable, because he was nearing Jerusalem, and because they guessed that the kingdom of God might be manifested without delay.

12 Therefore, he said: "A certain man of nobility traveled to a far away region, to receive for himself a kingdom, and to return.

13 And calling his ten servants, he gave them ten pounds, and he said to them: 'Do business until I return.'

14 But his citizens hated him. And so they sent a delegation after him, saying, 'We do not want this one to reign over us.'

15 And it happened that he returned, having received the kingdom. And he ordered the servants, to whom he had given the money, to be called so that he would know how much each one had earned by doing business.

16 Now the first approached, saying: 'Lord, your one pound has earned ten pounds.'

17 And he said to him: 'Well done, good servant. Since you have been faithful in a small matter, you will hold authority over ten cities.'

18 And the second came, saying: 'Lord, your one pound has earned five pounds.'

19 And he said to him, 'And so, you shall be over five cities.'

20 And another approached, saying: 'Lord, behold your one pound, which I kept stored in a cloth.

21 For I feared you, because you are an austere man. You take up what you did not lay down, and you reap what you did not sow.'

22 He said to him: 'By your own mouth, do I judge you, O wicked servant. You knew that I am an austere man, taking up what I did not lay down, and reaping what I did not sow.

23 And so, why did you not give my money to the bank, so that, upon my return, I might have withdrawn it with interest?'

24 And he said to the bystanders, 'Take the pound away from him, and give it to him who has ten pounds.'

25 And they said to him, 'Lord, he has ten pounds.'

26 So then, I say to you, that to all who have, it shall be given, and he will have in abundance. And from him who does not have, even what he has will be taken from him.

27 'Yet truly, as for those enemies of mine, who did not want me to reign over them, bring them here, and put them to death before me.' "

28 And having said these things, he went ahead, ascending to Jerusalem.

29 And it happened that, when he had drawn near to Bethphage and Bethania, to the mount which is called Olivet, he sent two of his disciples,

30 saying: "Go into the town which is opposite you. Upon entering it, you will find the colt of a donkey, tied, on which no man has ever sat. Untie it, and lead it here.

31 And if anyone will ask you, 'Why are you untying it?' you shall say this to him: 'Because the Lord has requested its service.' "

32 And those who were sent went out, and they found the colt standing, just as he told them.

33 Then, as they were untying the colt, its owners said to them, "Why are you untying the colt?"

34 So they said, "Because the Lord has need of it."

35 And they led it to Jesus. And casting their garments on the colt, they helped Jesus onto it.

36 Then, as he was traveling, they were laying down their garments along the way.

37 And when he was now drawing near to the descent of Mount Olivet, the entire crowd of his disciples began to praise God joyfully, with a loud voice, over all the powerful works which they had seen,

38 saying: "Blessed is the king who has arrived in the name of the Lord! Peace in heaven and glory on high!"

39 And certain Pharisees within the crowd said to him, "Teacher, rebuke your disciples."

40 And he said to them, "I tell you, that if these will keep silent, the stones themselves will cry out."

41 And when he drew near, seeing the city, he wept over it, saying:

42 "If only you had known, indeed even in this your day, which things are for your peace. But now they are hidden from your eyes.

43 For the days will overtake you. And your enemies will encircle you with a valley. And they will surround you and hem you in on every side.

44 And they will knock you down to the ground, with your sons who are in you. And they will not leave stone upon stone within you, because you did not recognize the time of your visitation."

45 And entering into the temple, he began to cast out those who sold in it, and those who bought,

46 saying to them: "It is written: 'My house is a house of prayer.' But you have made it into a den of robbers."

47 And he was teaching in the temple daily. And the leaders of the priests, and the scribes, and the leaders of the people were seeking to destroy him.

48 But they could not find what to do to him. For all the people were listening to him attentively.

Luke 20

1 And it happened that, on one of the days when he was teaching the people in the temple and preaching the Gospel, the leaders of the priests, and the scribes, gathered together with the elders,

2 and they spoke to him, saying: "Tell us, by what authority do you do these things? Or, who is it that has given you this authority?"

3 And in response, Jesus said to them: "I will also question you about one word. Respond to me:

4 The baptism of John, was it from heaven, or of men?"

5 So they discussed it among themselves, saying: "If we say, 'From heaven,' he will say, 'Then why did you not believe him?'

6 But if we say, 'Of men,' the whole people will stone us. For they are certain that John was a prophet."

7 And so they responded that they did not know where it was from.

8 And Jesus said to them, "Neither will I tell you by what authority I do these things."

9 Then he began to tell the people this parable: "A man planted a vineyard, and he loaned it to settlers, and he was on a sojourn for a long time.

10 And in due time, he sent a servant to the farmers, so that they would give to him from the fruit of the vineyard. And they beat him and drove him away, empty-handed.

11 And he continued to send another servant. But beating him and treating him with contempt, they likewise sent him away, empty-handed.

12 And he continued to send a third. And wounding him also, they drove him away.

13 Then the lord of the vineyard said: 'What shall I do? I will send my beloved son. Perhaps when they have seen him, they will respect him.'

14 And when the settlers had seen him, they discussed it among themselves, saying: 'This one is the heir. Let us kill him, so that the inheritance will be ours.'

15 And forcing him outside of the vineyard, they killed him. What, then, will the lord of the vineyard do to them?"

16 "He will come and destroy those settlers, and he will give the vineyard to others." And upon hearing this, they said to him, "Let it not be."

17 Then, gazing at them, he said: "Then what does this mean, which is written: 'The stone which the builders have rejected, the same has become the head of the corner?'

18 Everyone who falls on that stone will be shattered. And anyone upon whom it falls will be crushed."

19 And the leaders of the priests, and the scribes, were seeking to lay hands on him in that same hour, but they feared the people. For they realized that he had spoken this parable about them.

20 And being attentive, they sent traitors, who would pretend that they were just, so that they might catch him in his words and then hand him over to the power and authority of the procurator.

21 And they questioned him, saying: "Teacher, we know that you speak and teach correctly, and that you do not consider anyone's status, but you teach the way of God in truth.

22 Is it lawful for us to pay the tribute to Caesar, or not?"

23 But realizing their deceitfulness, he said to them: "Why do you test me?

24 Show me a denarius. Whose image and inscription does it have?" In response, they said to him, "Caesar's."

25 And so, he said to them: "Then repay the things that are Caesar's, to Caesar, and the things that are God's, to God."

26 And they were not able to contradict his word before the people. And being amazed at his answer, they were silent.

27 Now some of the Sadducees, who deny that there is a resurrection, approached him. And they questioned him,

28 saying: "Teacher, Moses wrote for us: If any man's brother will have died, having a wife, and if he does not have any children, then his brother should take her as his wife, and he should raise up offspring for his brother.

29 And so there were seven brothers. And the first took a wife, and he died without sons.

30 And the next one married her, and he also died without a son.

31 And the third married her, and similarly all seven, and none of them left behind any offspring, and they each died.

32 Last of all, the woman also died.

33 In the resurrection, then, whose wife will she be? For certainly all seven had her as a wife."

34 And so, Jesus said to them: "The children of this age marry and are given in marriage.

35 Yet truly, those who shall be held worthy of that age, and of the resurrection from the dead, will neither be married, nor take wives.

36 For they can no longer die. For they are equal to the Angels, and they are children of God, since they are children of the resurrection.

37 For in truth, the dead do rise again, as Moses also showed beside the bush, when he called the Lord: 'The God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob.'

38 And so he is not the God of the dead, but of the living. For all are alive to him."

39 Then some of the scribes, in response, said to him, "Teacher, you have spoken well."

40 And they no longer dared to question him about anything.

41 But he said to them: "How can they say that the Christ is the son of David?

42 Even David himself says, in the book of Psalms: 'The Lord said to my Lord, sit at my right hand,

43 until I set your enemies as your footstool.'

44 Therefore, David calls him Lord. So how can he be his son?"

45 Now in the hearing of all the people, he said to his disciples:

46 "Be cautious of the scribes, who choose to walk in long robes, and who love greetings in the marketplace, and the first chairs in the synagogues, and the first places at table during feasts,

47 who devour the houses of widows, feigning long prayers. These will receive the greater damnation."

Luke 21

1 And looking around, he saw the wealthy putting their donations into the offertory.

2 Then he also saw a certain widow, a pauper, putting in two small brass coins.

3 And he said: "Truly, I say to you, that this poor widow has put in more than all the others.

4 For all these, out of their abundance, have added to the gifts for God. But she, out of what she needed, has put in all that she had to live on."

5 And when some of them were saying, about the temple, that it was adorned with excellent stones and gifts, he said,

6 "These things that you see, the days will arrive when there will not be left behind stone upon stone, which is not thrown down."

7 Then they questioned him, saying: "Teacher, when will these things be? And what will be the sign when these things will happen?"

8 And he said: "Be cautious, lest you be seduced. For many will come in my name, saying: 'For I am he,' and, 'The time has drawn near.' And so, do not choose to go after them.

9 And when you will have heard of battles and seditions, do not be terrified. These things must happen first. But the end is not so soon."

10 Then he said to them: "People will rise up against people, and kingdom against kingdom.

11 And there will be great earthquakes in various places, and pestilences, and famines, and terrors from heaven; and there will be great signs.

12 But before all these things, they will lay their hands on you and persecute you, handing you over to synagogues and into custody, dragging you before kings and governors, because of my name.

13 And this will be an opportunity for you to give testimony.

14 Therefore, set this in your hearts: that you should not consider in advance how you might respond.

15 For I will give to you a mouth and wisdom, which all your adversaries will not be able to resist or contradict.

16 And you will be handed over by your parents, and brothers, and relatives, and friends. And they will bring about the death of some of you.

17 And you will be hated by all because of my name.

18 And yet, not a hair of your head will perish.

19 By your patience, you shall possess your souls.

20 Then, when you will have seen Jerusalem encircled by an army, know then that its desolation has drawn near.

21 Then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains, and those who are in its midst withdraw, and those who are in the countryside not enter into it.

22 For these are the days of retribution, so that all things may be fulfilled, which have been written.

23 Then woe to those who are pregnant or nursing in those days. For there will be great distress upon the land and great wrath upon this people.

24 And they will fall by the edge of the sword. And they will be led away as captives into all nations. And Jerusalem will be trampled by the Gentiles, until the times of the nations are fulfilled.

25 And there will be signs in the sun and the moon and the stars. And there will be, on earth, distress among the Gentiles, out of confusion at the roaring of the sea and of the waves:

26 men withering away out of fear and out of apprehension over the things that will overwhelm the whole world. For the powers of the heavens will be moved.

27 And then they will see the Son of man coming on a cloud, with great power and majesty.

28 But when these things begin to happen, lift up your heads and look around you, because your redemption draws near."

29 And he told them a comparison: "Take notice of the fig tree and of all the trees.

30 When presently they produce fruit from themselves, you know that summer is near.

31 So you also, when you will have seen these things happen, know that the kingdom of God is near.

32 Amen I say to you, this lineage shall not pass away, until all these things happen.

33 Heaven and earth shall pass away. But my words shall not pass away.

34 But be attentive to yourselves, lest perhaps your hearts may be weighed down by self-indulgence and inebriation and the cares of this life. And then that day may overwhelm you suddenly.

35 For like a snare it will overwhelm all those who sit upon the face of the entire earth.

36 And so, be vigilant, praying at all times, so that you may be held worthy to escape from all these things, which are in the future, and to stand before the Son of man."

37 Now in the daytime, he was teaching in the temple. But truly, departing in the evening, he lodged on the mount that is called Olivet.

38 And all the people arrived in the morning to listen to him in the temple.

Luke 22

1 Now the days of the Feast of Unleavened Bread, which is called Passover, were approaching.

2 And the leaders of the priests, and the scribes, were seeking a way to execute Jesus. Yet truly, they were afraid of the people.

3 Then Satan entered into Judas, who was surnamed Iscariot, one of the twelve.

4 And he went out and was speaking with the leaders of the priests, and the magistrates, as to how he might hand him over to them.

5 And they were glad, and so they made an agreement to give him money.

6 And he made a promise. And he was seeking an opportunity to hand him over, apart from the crowds.

7 Then the day of Unleavened Bread arrived, on which it was necessary to kill the Pascal lamb.

8 And he sent Peter and John, saying, "Go out, and prepare the Passover for us, so that we may eat."

9 But they said, "Where do you want us to prepare it?"

10 And he said to them: "Behold, as you are entering into the city, a certain man will meet you, carrying a pitcher of water. Follow him to the house into which he enters.

11 And you shall say to the father of the household: 'The Teacher says to you: Where is the guestroom, where I may eat the Passover with my disciples?'

12 And he will show you a large cenacle, fully furnished. And so, prepare it there."

13 And going out, they found it to be just as he had told them. And they prepared the Passover.

14 And when the hour had arrived, he sat down at table, and the twelve Apostles with him.

15 And he said to them: "With longing have I desired to eat this Passover with you, before I suffer.

16 For I say to you, that from this time, I will not eat it, until it is fulfilled in the kingdom of God."

17 And having taken the chalice, he gave thanks, and he said: "Take this and share it among yourselves.

18 For I say to you, that I will not drink from the fruit of the vine, until the kingdom of God arrives."

19 And taking bread, he gave thanks and broke it and gave it to them, saying: "This is my body, which is given for you. Do this as a commemoration of me."

20 Similarly also, he took the chalice, after he had eaten the meal, saying: "This chalice is the new covenant in my blood, which will be shed for you.

21 But in truth, behold, the hand of my betrayer is with me at table.

22 And indeed, the Son of man goes according to what has been determined. And yet, woe to that man by whom he will be betrayed."

23 And they began to inquire among themselves, as to which of them might do this.

24 Now there was also a contention among them, as to which of them seemed to be the greater.

25 And he said to them: "The kings of the Gentiles dominate them; and those who hold authority over them are called beneficent.

26 But it must not be so with you. Instead, whoever is greater among you, let him become the lesser. And whoever is the leader, let him become the server.

27 For who is greater: he who sits at table, or he who serves? Is not he who sits at table? Yet I am in your midst as one who serves.

28 But you are those who have remained with me during my trials.

29 And I dispose to you, just as my Father has disposed to me, a kingdom,

30 so that you may eat and drink at my table in my kingdom, and so that you may sit upon thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel."

31 And the Lord said: "Simon, Simon! Behold, Satan has asked for you, so that he may sift you like wheat.

32 But I have prayed for you, so that your faith may not fail, and so that you, once converted, may confirm your brothers."

33 And he said to him, "Lord, I am prepared to go with you, even to prison and to death."

34 And he said, "I say to you, Peter, the rooster will not crow this day, until you have three times denied that you know me." And he said to them,

35 "When I sent you without money or provisions or shoes, did you lack anything?"

36 And they said, "Nothing." Then he said to them: "But now, let whoever has money take it, and likewise with provisions. And whoever does not have these, let him sell his coat and buy a sword.

37 For I say to you, that what has been written must still be fulfilled in me: 'And he was esteemed with the wicked.' Yet even these things about me have an end."

38 So they said, "Lord, behold, there are two swords here." But he said to them, "It is sufficient."

39 And departing, he went out, according to his custom, to the Mount of Olives. And his disciples also followed him.

40 And when he had arrived at the place, he said to them: "Pray, lest you enter into temptation."

41 And he was separated from them by about a stone's throw. And kneeling down, he prayed,

42 saying: "Father, if you are willing, take this chalice away from me. Yet truly, let not my will, but yours, be done."

43 Then an Angel appeared to him from heaven, strengthening him. And being in agony, he prayed more intensely;

44 and so his sweat became like drops of blood, running down to the ground.

45 And when he had risen up from prayer and had gone to his disciples, he found them sleeping out of sorrow.

46 And he said to them: "Why are you sleeping? Rise up, pray, lest you enter into temptation."

47 While he was still speaking, behold, a crowd arrived. And he who is called Judas, one of the twelve, went ahead of them and approached Jesus, in order to kiss him.

48 And Jesus said to him, "Judas, do you betray the Son of man with a kiss?"

49 Then those who were around him, realizing what was about to happen, said to him: "Lord, shall we strike with the sword?"

50 And one of them struck the servant of the high priest and cut off his right ear.

51 But in response, Jesus said, "Permit even this." And when he had touched his ear, he healed him.

52 Then Jesus said to the leaders of the priests, and the magistrates of the temple, and the elders, who had come to him: "Have you gone out, as if against a thief, with swords and clubs?

53 When I was with you each day in the temple, you did not extend your hands against me. But this is your hour and that of the power of darkness."

54 And apprehending him, they led him to the house of the high priest. Yet truly, Peter followed at a distance.

55 Now as they were sitting around a fire, which had been kindled in the middle of the atrium, Peter was in their midst.

56 And when a certain woman servant had seen him sitting in its light, and had looked at him intently, she said, "This one was also with him."

57 But he denied him by saying, "Woman, I do not know him."

58 And after a little while, another one, seeing him, said, "You also are one of them." Yet Peter said, "O man, I am not."

59 And after the interval of about one hour had passed, someone else affirmed it, saying: "Truly, this one also was with him. For he is also a Galilean."

60 And Peter said: "Man, I do not know what you are saying." And at once, while he was still speaking, the rooster crowed.

61 And the Lord turned around and looked at Peter. And Peter remembered the word of the Lord that he had said: "For before the rooster crows, you will deny me three times."

62 And going out, Peter wept bitterly.

63 And the men who were holding him ridiculed him and beat him.

64 And they blindfolded him and repeatedly struck his face. And they questioned him, saying: "Prophesy! Who is it that struck you?"

65 And blaspheming in many other ways, they spoke against him.

66 And when it was daytime, the elders of the people, and the leaders of the priests, and the scribes convened. And they led him into their council, saying, "If you are the Christ, tell us."

67 And he said to them: "If I tell you, you will not believe me.

68 And if I also question you, you will not answer me. Neither will you release me.

69 But from this time, the Son of man will be sitting at the right hand of the power of God."

70 Then they all said, "So you are the Son of God?" And he said. "You are saying that I am."

71 And they said: "Why do we still require testimony? For we have heard it ourselves, from his own mouth."

Luke 23

1 And the entire multitude of them, rising up, led him to Pilate.

2 Then they began to accuse him, saying, "We found this one subverting our nation, and prohibiting giving tribute to Caesar, and saying that he is Christ the king."

3 And Pilate questioned him, saying: "You are the king of the Jews?" But in response, he said: "You are saying it."

4 Then Pilate said to the leaders of the priests and to the crowds, "I find no case against this man."

5 But they continued more intensely, saying: "He has stirred up the people, teaching throughout all of Judea, beginning from Galilee, even to this place."

6 But Pilate, upon hearing Galilee, asked if the man were of Galilee.

7 And when he realized that he was under Herod's jurisdiction, he sent him away to Herod, who was himself also at Jerusalem in those days.

8 Then Herod, upon seeing Jesus, was very glad. For he had been wanting to see him for a long time, because he had heard so many things about him, and he was hoping to see some kind of sign wrought by him.

9 Then he questioned him with many words. But he gave him no response at all.

10 And the leaders of the priests, and the scribes, stood firm in persistently accusing him.

11 Then Herod, with his soldiers, scorned him. And he ridiculed him, clothing him in a white garment. And he sent him back to Pilate.

12 And Herod and Pilate became friends on that day. For previously they were enemies to one another.

13 And Pilate, calling together the leaders of the priests, and the magistrates, and the people,

14 said to them: "You have brought before me this man, as one who disturbs the people. And behold, having questioned him before you, I find no case against this man, in those things about which you accuse him.

15 And neither did Herod. For I sent you all to him, and behold, nothing deserving of death was recorded about him.

16 Therefore, I will chastise him and release him."

17 Now he was required to release one person for them on the feast day.

18 But the entire crowd exclaimed together, saying: "Take this one, and release to us Barabbas!"

19 Now he had been cast into prison because of a certain sedition that occurred in the city and for murder.

20 Then Pilate spoke to them again, wanting to release Jesus.

21 But they shouted in response, saying: "Crucify him! Crucify him!"

22 Then he said to them a third time: "Why? What evil has he done? I find no case against him for death. Therefore, I will chastise him and release him."

23 But they persisted, with loud voices, in demanding that he be crucified. And their voices increased in intensity.

24 And so Pilate issued a judgment granting their petition.

25 Then he released for them the one who had been cast into prison for murder and sedition, whom they were requesting. Yet truly, Jesus he handed over to their will.

26 And as they were leading him away, they apprehended a certain one, Simon of Cyrene, as he was returning from the countryside. And they imposed the cross on him to carry after Jesus.

27 Then a great crowd of people followed him, with women who were mourning and lamenting him.

28 But Jesus, turning to them, said: "Daughters of Jerusalem, do not weep over me. Instead, weep over yourselves and over your children.

29 For behold, the days will arrive in which they will say, 'Blessed are the barren, and the wombs that have not borne, and the breasts that have not nursed.'

30 Then they will begin to say to the mountains, 'Fall over us,' and to the hills, 'Cover us.'

31 For if they do these things with green wood, what will be done with the dry?"

32 Now they also led out two other criminals with him, in order to execute them.

33 And when they arrived at the place that is called Calvary, they crucified him there, with the robbers, one to the right and the other to the left.

34 Then Jesus said, "Father, forgive them. For they know not what they do." And truly, dividing his garments, they cast lots.

35 And people were standing near, watching. And the leaders among them derided him, saying: "He saved others. Let him save himself, if this one is the Christ, the elect of God."

36 And the soldiers also ridiculed him, approaching him and offering him vinegar,

37 and saying, "If you are the king of the Jews, save yourself."

38 Now there was also an inscription written over him in letters of Greek, and Latin, and Hebrew: THIS IS THE KING OF THE JEWS.

39 And one of those robbers who were hanging blasphemed him, saying, "If you are the Christ, save yourself and us."

40 But the other responded by rebuking him, saying: "Do you have no fear of God, since you are under the same condemnation?

41 And indeed, it is just for us. For we are receiving what our deeds deserve. But truly, this one has done nothing wrong."

42 And he said to Jesus, "Lord, remember me when you come into your kingdom."

43 And Jesus said to him, "Amen I say to you, this day you shall be with me in Paradise."

44 Now it was nearly the sixth hour, and a darkness occurred over the entire earth, until the ninth hour.

45 And the sun was obscured. And the veil of the temple was torn down the middle.

46 And Jesus, crying out with a loud voice, said: "Father, into your hands I commend my spirit." And upon saying this, he expired.

47 Now, the centurion, seeing what had happened, glorified God, saying, "Truly, this man was the Just One."

48 And the entire crowd of those who came together to see this spectacle also saw what had happened, and they returned, striking their breasts.

49 Now all those who knew him, and the women who had followed him from Galilee, were standing at a distance, watching these things.

50 And behold, there was a man named Joseph, who was a councilman, a good and just man,

51 (for he had not consented to their decision or their actions). He was from Arimathea, a city of Judea. And he was himself also anticipating the kingdom of God.

52 This man approached Pilate and petitioned for the body of Jesus.

53 And taking him down, he wrapped him in a fine linen cloth, and he placed him in a tomb hewn from rock, in which no one had ever been placed.

54 And it was the day of Preparation, and the Sabbath was drawing near.

55 Now the women who had come with him from Galilee, by following, saw the tomb and the manner in which his body was placed.

56 And upon returning, they prepared aromatic spices and ointments. But on the Sabbath, indeed, they rested, according to the commandment.

Luke 24

1 Then, on the first Sabbath, at very first light, they went to the tomb, carrying the aromatic spices that they had prepared.

2 And they found the stone rolled back from the tomb.

3 And upon entering, they did not find the body of the Lord Jesus.

4 And it happened that, while their minds were still confused about this, behold, two men stood beside them, in shining apparel.

5 Then, since they were afraid and were turning their faces toward the ground, these two said to them: "Why do you seek the living with the dead?

6 He is not here, for he has risen. Recall how he spoke to you, when he was still in Galilee,

7 saying: 'For the Son of man must be delivered into the hands of sinful men, and be crucified, and on the third day rise again.' "

8 And they called to mind his words.

9 And returning from the tomb, they reported all these things to the eleven, and to all the others.

10 Now it was Mary Magdalene, and Joanna, and Mary of James, and the other women who were with them, who told these things to the Apostles.

11 But these words seemed to them a delusion. And so they did not believe them.

12 But Peter, rising up, ran to the tomb. And stooping down, he saw the linen cloths positioned alone, and he went away wondering to himself about what had happened.

13 And behold, two of them went out, on the same day, to a town named Emmaus, which was the distance of sixty stadia from Jerusalem.

14 And they spoke to one another about all of these things that had occurred.

15 And it happened that, while they were speculating and questioning within themselves, Jesus himself, drawing near, traveled with them.

16 But their eyes were restrained, so that they would not recognize him.

17 And he said to them, "What are these words, which you are discussing with one another, as you walk and are sad?"

18 And one of them, whose name was Cleopas, responded by saying to him, "Are you the only one visiting Jerusalem who does not know the things that have happened there in these days?"

19 And he said to them, "What things?" And they said, "About Jesus of Nazareth, who was a noble prophet, powerful in works and in words, before God and all the people.

20 And how our high priests and leaders handed him over to be condemned to death. And they crucified him.

21 But we were hoping that he would be the Redeemer of Israel. And now, on top of all this, today is the third day since these things have happened.

22 Then, too, certain women from among us terrified us. For before daytime, they were at the tomb,

23 and, having not found his body, they returned, saying that they had even seen a vision of Angels, who said that he is alive.

24 And some of us went out to the tomb. And they found it just as the women had said. But truly, they did not find him."

25 And he said to them: "How foolish and reluctant in heart you are, to believe everything that has been spoken by the Prophets!

26 Was not the Christ required to suffer these things, and so enter into his glory?"

27 And beginning from Moses and all the Prophets, he interpreted for them, in all the Scriptures, the things that were about him.

28 And they drew near to the town where they were going. And he conducted himself so as to go on further.

29 But they were insistent with him, saying, "Remain with us, because it is toward evening and now daylight is declining." And so he entered with them.

30 And it happened that, while he was at table with them, he took bread, and he blessed and broke it, and he extended it to them.

31 And their eyes were opened, and they recognized him. And he vanished from their eyes.

32 And they said to one another, "Was not our heart burning within us, while he was speaking on the way, and when he opened the Scriptures to us?"

33 And rising up at that same hour, they returned to Jerusalem. And they found the eleven gathered together, and those who were with them,

34 saying: "In truth, the Lord has risen, and he has appeared to Simon."

35 And they explained the things that were done on the way, and how they had recognized him at the breaking of the bread.

36 Then, while they were talking about these things, Jesus stood in their midst, And he said to them: "Peace be with you. It is I. Do not be afraid."

37 Yet truly, they were very disturbed and terrified, supposing that they saw a spirit.

38 And he said to them: "Why are you disturbed, and why do these thoughts rise up in your hearts?

39 See my hands and feet, that it is I myself. Look and touch. For a spirit does not have flesh and bones, as you see that I have."

40 And when he had said this, he showed them his hands and feet.

41 Then, while they were still in disbelief and in wonder out of joy, he said, "Do you have anything here to eat?"

42 And they offered him a piece of roasted fish and a honeycomb.

43 And when he had eaten these in their sight, taking up what was left, he gave it to them.

44 And he said to them: "These are the words that I spoke to you when I was still with you, because all things must be fulfilled which are written in the law of Moses, and in the Prophets, and in the Psalms about me."

45 Then he opened their mind, so that they might understand the Scriptures.

46 And he said to them: "For so it is written, and so it was necessary, for the Christ to suffer and to rise up from the dead on the third day,

47 and, in his name, for repentance and the remission of sins to be preached, among all the nations, beginning at Jerusalem.

48 And you are witnesses of these things.

49 And I am sending the Promise of my Father upon you. But you must stay in the city, until such time as you are clothed with power from on high."

50 Then he led them out as far as Bethania. And lifting up his hands, he blessed them.

51 And it happened that, while he was blessing them, he withdrew from them, and he was carried up into heaven.

52 And worshiping, they returned to Jerusalem with great joy.

53 And they were always in the temple, praising and blessing God. Amen.

John 1

1 In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and God was the Word.

2 He was with God in the beginning.

3 All things were made through Him, and nothing that was made was made without Him.

4 Life was in Him, and Life was the light of men.

5 And the light shines in the darkness, and the darkness did not comprehend it.

6 There was a man sent by God, whose name was John.

7 He arrived as a witness to offer testimony about the Light, so that all would believe through him.

8 He was not the Light, but he was to offer testimony about the Light.

9 The true Light, which illuminates every man, was coming into this world.

10 He was in the world, and the world was made through him, and the world did not recognize him.

11 He went to his own, and his own did not accept him.

12 Yet whoever did accept him, those who believed in his name, he gave them the power to become the sons of God.

13 These are born, not of blood, nor of the will of flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God.

14 And the Word became flesh, and he lived among us, and we saw his glory, glory like that of an only-begotten son from the Father, full of grace and truth.

15 John offers testimony about him, and he cries out, saying: "This is the one about whom I said: 'He who is to come after me, has been placed ahead of me, because he existed before me.' "

16 And from his fullness, we all have received, even grace for grace.

17 For the law was given though Moses, but grace and truth came through Jesus Christ.

18 No one ever saw God; the only-begotten Son, who is in the bosom of the Father, he himself has described him.

19 And this is the testimony of John, when the Jews sent priests and Levites from Jerusalem to him, so that they might ask him, "Who are you?"

20 And he confessed it and did not deny it; and what he confessed was: "I am not the Christ."

21 And they questioned him: "Then what are you? Are you Elijah?" And he said, "I am not." "Are you the Prophet?" And he answered, "No."

22 Therefore, they said to him: "Who are you, so that we may give an answer to those who sent us? What do you say about yourself?"

23 He said, "I am a voice crying out in the desert, 'Make straight the way of the Lord,' just as the prophet Isaiah said."

24 And some of those who had been sent were from among the Pharisees.

25 And they questioned him and said to him, "Then why do you baptize, if you are not the Christ, and not Elijah, and not the Prophet?"

26 John answered them by saying: "I baptize with water. But in your midst stands one, whom you do not know.

27 The same is he who is to come after me, who has been placed ahead of me, the laces of whose shoes I am not worthy to loosen."

28 These things happened in Bethania, across the Jordan, where John was baptizing.

29 On the next day, John saw Jesus coming toward him, and so he said: "Behold, the Lamb of God. Behold, he who takes away the sin of the world.

30 This is the one about whom I said, 'After me arrives a man, who has been placed ahead of me, because he existed before me.'

31 And I did not know him. Yet it is for this reason that I come baptizing with water: so that he may be made manifest in Israel."

32 And John offered testimony, saying: "For I saw the Spirit descending from heaven like a dove; and he remained upon him.

33 And I did not know him. But he who sent me to baptize with water said to me: 'He over whom you will see the Spirit descending and remaining upon him, this is the one who baptizes with the Holy Spirit.'

34 And I saw, and I gave testimony: that this one is the Son of God."

35 The next day again, John was standing with two of his disciples.

36 And catching sight of Jesus walking, he said, "Behold, the Lamb of God."

37 And two disciples were listening to him speaking. And they followed Jesus.

38 Then Jesus, turning around and seeing them following him, said to them, "What are you seeking?" And they said to him, "Rabbi (which means in translation, Teacher), where do you live?"

39 He said to them, "Come and see." They went and saw where he was staying, and they stayed with him that day. Now it was about the tenth hour.

40 And Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, was one of the two who had heard about him from John and had followed him.

41 First, he found his brother Simon, and he said to him, "We have found the Messiah," (which is translated as the Christ).

42 And he led him to Jesus. And Jesus, gazing at him, said: "You are Simon, son of Jonah. You shall be called Cephas," (which is translated as Peter).

43 On the next day, he wanted to go into Galilee, and he found Philip. And Jesus said to him, "Follow me."

44 Now Philip was from Bethsaida, the city of Andrew and Peter.

45 Philip found Nathanael, and he said to him, "We have found the one about whom Moses wrote in the Law and the Prophets: Jesus, the son of Joseph, from Nazareth."

46 And Nathanael said to him, "Can anything good be from Nazareth?" Philip said to him, "Come and see."

47 Jesus saw Nathanael coming toward him, and he said about him, "Behold, an Israelite in whom truly there is no deceit."

48 Nathanael said to him, "From where do you know me?" Jesus responded and said to him, "Before Philip called you, when you were under the fig tree, I saw you."

49 Nathanael answered him and said: "Rabbi, you are the Son of God. You are the King of Israel."

50 Jesus responded and said to him: "Because I told you that I saw you under the fig tree, you believe. Greater things than these, you will see."

51 And he said to him, "Amen, amen, I say to you, you will see heaven opened, and the Angels of God ascending and descending over the Son of man."

John 2

1 And on the third day, a wedding was held in Cana of Galilee, and the mother of Jesus was there.

2 Now Jesus was also invited to the wedding, with his disciples.

3 And when the wine was failing, the mother of Jesus said to him, "They have no wine."

4 And Jesus said to her: "What is that to me and to you, woman? My hour has not yet arrived."

5 His mother said to the servants, "Do whatever he tells you."

6 Now in that place, there were six stone water jars, for the purification ritual of the Jews, containing two or three measures each.

7 Jesus said to them, "Fill the water jars with water." And they filled them to the very top.

8 And Jesus said to them, "Now draw from it, and carry it to the chief steward of the feast." And they took it to him.

9 Then, when the chief steward had tasted the water made into wine, since he did not know where it was from, for only the servants who had drawn the water knew, the chief steward called the groom,

10 and he said to him: "Every man offers the good wine first, and then, when they have become inebriated, he offers what is worse. But you have kept the good wine until now."

11 This was the beginning of the signs that Jesus accomplished in Cana of Galilee, and it manifested his glory, and his disciples believed in him.

12 After this, he descended to Capernaum, with his mother and his brothers and his disciples, but they did not remain there for many days.

13 And the Passover of the Jews was near, and so Jesus ascended to Jerusalem.

14 And he found, sitting in the temple, sellers of oxen and sheep and doves, and the moneychangers.

15 And when he had made something like a whip out of little cords, he drove them all out of the temple, including the sheep and the oxen. And he poured out the brass coins of the moneychangers, and he overturned their tables.

16 And to those who were selling doves, he said: "Take these things out of here, and do not make my Father's house into a house of commerce."

17 And truly, his disciples were reminded that it is written: "Zeal for your house consumes me."

18 Then the Jews responded and said to him, "What sign can you show to us, that you may do these things?"

19 Jesus responded and said to them, "Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up."

20 Then the Jews said, "This temple has been built up over forty-six years, and you will raise it up in three days?"

21 Yet he was speaking about the Temple of his body.

22 Therefore, when he had resurrected from the dead, his disciples were reminded that he had said this, and they believed in the Scriptures and in the word that Jesus had spoken.

23 Now while he was at Jerusalem during the Passover, on the day of the feast, many trusted in his name, seeing his signs that he was accomplishing.

24 But Jesus did not trust himself to them, because he himself had knowledge of all persons,

25 and because he had no need of anyone to offer testimony about a man. For he knew what was within a man.

John 3

1 Now there was a man among the Pharisees, named Nicodemus, a leader of the Jews.

2 He went to Jesus at night, and he said to him: "Rabbi, we know that you have arrived as a teacher from God. For no one would be able to accomplish these signs, which you accomplish, unless God were with him."

3 Jesus responded and said to him, "Amen, amen, I say to you, unless one has been reborn anew, he is not able to see the kingdom of God."

4 Nicodemus said to him: "How could a man be born when he is old? Surely, he cannot enter a second time into his mother's womb to be reborn?"

5 Jesus responded: "Amen, amen, I say to you, unless one has been reborn by water and the Holy Spirit, he is not able to enter into the kingdom of God.

6 What is born of the flesh is flesh, and what is born of the Spirit is spirit.

7 You should not be amazed that I said to you: You must be born anew.

8 The Spirit inspires where he wills. And you hear his voice, but you do not know where he comes from, or where he is going. So it is with all who are born of the Spirit."

9 Nicodemus responded and said to him, "How are these things able to be accomplished?"

10 Jesus responded and said to him: "You are a teacher in Israel, and you are ignorant of these things?

11 Amen, amen, I say to you, that we speak about what we know, and we testify about what we have seen. But you do not accept our testimony.

12 If I have spoken to you about earthly things, and you have not believed, then how will you believe, if I will speak to you about heavenly things?

13 And no one has ascended to heaven, except the one who descended from heaven: the Son of man who is in heaven.

14 And just as Moses lifted up the serpent in the desert, so also must the Son of man be lifted up,

15 so that whoever believes in him may not perish, but may have eternal life.

16 For God so loved the world that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that all who believe in him may not perish, but may have eternal life.

17 For God did not send his Son into the world, in order to judge the world, but in order that the world may be saved through him.

18 Whoever believes in him is not judged. But whoever does not believe is already judged, because he does not believe in the name of the only-begotten Son of God.

19 And this is the judgment: that the Light has come into the world, and men loved darkness more than light. For their works were evil.

20 For everyone who does evil hates the Light and does not go toward the Light, so that his works may not be corrected.

21 But whoever acts in truth goes toward the Light, so that his works may be manifested, because they have been accomplished in God."

22 After these things, Jesus and his disciples went into the land of Judea. And he was living there with them and baptizing.

23 Now John was also baptizing, at Aenon near Salim, because there was much water in that place. And they were arriving and being baptized.

24 For John had not yet been cast into prison.

25 Then a dispute occurred between the disciples of John and the Jews, about purification.

26 And they went to John and said to him: "Rabbi, the one who was with you across the Jordan, about whom you offered testimony: behold, he is baptizing and everyone is going to him."

27 John responded and said: "A man is not able to receive anything, unless it has been given to him from heaven.

28 You yourselves offer testimony for me that I said, 'I am not the Christ,' but that I have been sent before him.

29 He who holds the bride is the groom. But the friend of the groom, who stands and listens to Him, rejoices joyfully at the voice of the groom. And so, this, my joy, has been fulfilled.

30 He must increase, while I must decrease.

31 He who comes from above, is above everything. He who is from below, is of the earth, and he speaks about the earth. He who comes from heaven is above everything.

32 And what he has seen and heard, about this he testifies. And no one accepts his testimony.

33 Whoever has accepted his testimony has certified that God is truthful.

34 For he whom God has sent speaks the words of God. For God does not give the Spirit by measure.

35 The Father loves the Son, and he has given everything into his hand.

36 Whoever believes in the Son has eternal life. But whoever is unbelieving toward the Son shall not see life; instead the wrath of God remains upon him."

John 4

1 And so, when Jesus realized that the Pharisees had heard that Jesus made more disciples and baptized more than John,

2 (though Jesus himself was not baptizing, but only his disciples)

3 he left behind Judea, and he traveled again to Galilee.

4 Now he needed to cross through Samaria.

5 Therefore, he went into a city of Samaria which is called Sychar, near the estate which Jacob gave to his son Joseph.

6 And Jacob's well was there. And so Jesus, being tired from the journey, was sitting in a certain way on the well. It was about the sixth hour.

7 A woman of Samaria arrived to draw water. Jesus said to her, "Give me to drink."

8 For his disciples had gone into the city in order to buy food.

9 And so, that Samaritan woman said to him, "How is it that you, being a Jew, are requesting a drink from me, though I am a Samaritan woman?" For the Jews do not associate with the Samaritans.

10 Jesus responded and said to her: "If you knew the gift of God, and who it is who is saying to you, 'Give me to drink,' perhaps you would have made a request of him, and he would have given you living water."

11 The woman said to him: "Lord, you do not have anything with which to draw water, and the well is deep. From where, then, do you have living water?

12 Surely, you are not greater than our father Jacob, who gave us the well and who drank from it, with his sons and his cattle?"

13 Jesus responded and said to her: "All who drink from this water will thirst again. But whoever shall drink from the water that I will give to him will not thirst for eternity.

14 Instead, the water that I will give to him will become in him a fountain of water, springing up into eternal life."

15 The woman said to him, "Lord, give me this water, so that I may not thirst and may not come here to draw water."

16 Jesus said to her, "Go, call your husband, and return here."

17 The woman responded and said, "I have no husband." Jesus said to her: "You have spoken well, in saying, 'I have no husband.'

18 For you have had five husbands, but he whom you have now is not your husband. You have spoken this in truth."

19 The woman said to him: "Lord, I see that you are a Prophet.

20 Our fathers worshipped on this mountain, but you say that Jerusalem is the place where one ought to worship."

21 Jesus said to her: "Woman, believe me, the hour is coming when you shall worship the Father, neither on this mountain, nor in Jerusalem.

22 You worship what you do not know; we worship what we do know. For salvation is from the Jews.

23 But the hour is coming, and it is now, when true worshippers shall worship the Father in spirit and in truth. For the Father also seeks such persons who may worship him.

24 God is Spirit. And so, those who worship him must worship in spirit and in truth."

25 The woman said to him: "I know that the Messiah is coming (who is called the Christ). And then, when he will have arrived, he will announce everything to us."

26 Jesus said to her: "I am he, the one who is speaking with you."

27 And then his disciples arrived. And they wondered that he was speaking with the woman. Yet no one said: "What are you seeking?" or, "Why are you talking with her?"

28 And so the woman left behind her water jar and went into the city. And she said to the men there:

29 "Come and see a man who has told me all the things that I have done. Is he not the Christ?"

30 Therefore, they went out of the city and came to him.

31 Meanwhile, the disciples petitioned him, saying, "Rabbi, eat."

32 But he said to them, "I have food to eat which you do not know."

33 Therefore, the disciples said to one another, "Could someone have brought him something to eat?"

34 Jesus said to them: "My food is to do the will of the One who sent me, so that I may perfect his work.

35 Do you not say, 'There are still four months, and then the harvest arrives?' Behold, I say to you: Lift up your eyes and look at the countryside; for it is already ripe for the harvest.

36 For he who reaps, receives wages and gathers fruit unto eternal life, so that both he who sows and he who reaps may rejoice together.

37 For in this the word is true: that it is one who sows, and it is another who reaps.

38 I have sent you to reap that for which you did not labor. Others have labored, and you have entered into their labors."

39 Now many of the Samaritans from that city believed in him, because of the word of the woman who was offering testimony: "For he told me all the things that I have done."

40 Therefore, when the Samaritans had come to him, they petitioned him to lodge there. And he lodged there for two days.

41 And many more believed in him, because of his own word.

42 And they said to the woman: "Now we believe, not because of your speech, but because we ourselves have heard him, and so we know that he is truly the Savior of the world."

43 Then, after two days, he departed from there, and he traveled into Galilee.

44 For Jesus himself offered testimony that a Prophet has no honor in his own country.

45 And so, when he had arrived in Galilee, the Galileans received him, because they had seen all that he had done at Jerusalem, in the day of the feast. For they also went to the feast day.

46 Then he went again into Cana of Galilee, where he made water into wine. And there was a certain ruler, whose son was sick at Capernaum.

47 Since he had heard that Jesus came to Galilee from Judea, he sent to him and begged him to come down and heal his son. For he was beginning to die.

48 Therefore, Jesus said to him, "Unless you have seen signs and wonders, you do not believe."

49 The ruler said to him, "Lord, come down before my son dies."

50 Jesus said to him, "Go, your son lives." The man believed the word that Jesus spoke to him, and so he went away.

51 Then, as he was going down, his servants met him. And they reported to him, saying that his son was alive.

52 Therefore, he asked them at which hour he had become better. And they said to him, "Yesterday, at the seventh hour, the fever left him."

53 Then the father realized that it was at the same hour that Jesus said to him, "Your son lives." And both he and his entire household believed.

54 This next sign was the second that Jesus accomplished, after he had arrived in Galilee from Judea.

John 5

1 After these things, there was a feast day of the Jews, and so Jesus ascended to Jerusalem.

2 Now at Jerusalem is the Pool of Evidence, which in Hebrew is known as the Place of Mercy; it has five porticos.

3 Along these lay a great multitude of the sick, the blind, the lame, and the withered, waiting for the movement of the water.

4 Now at times an Angel of the Lord would descend into the pool, and so the water was moved. And whoever descended first into the pool, after the motion of the water, he was healed of whatever infirmity held him.

5 And there was a certain man in that place, having been in his infirmity for thirty-eight years.

6 Then, when Jesus had seen him reclining, and when he realized that he had been afflicted for a long time, he said to him, "Do you want to be healed?"

7 The invalid answered him: "Lord, I do not have any man to put me in the pool, when the water has been stirred. For as I am going, another descends ahead of me."

8 Jesus said to him, "Rise, take up your stretcher, and walk."

9 And immediately the man was healed. And he took up his stretcher and walked. Now this day was the Sabbath.

10 Therefore, the Jews said to the one who had been healed: "It is the Sabbath. It is not lawful for you to take up your stretcher."

11 He answered them, "The one who healed me, he said to me, 'Take up your stretcher and walk.' "

12 Therefore, they questioned him, "Who is that man, who said to you, 'Take up your bed and walk?' "

13 But the one who had been given health did not know who it was. For Jesus had turned aside from the crowd gathered in that place.

14 Afterwards, Jesus found him in the temple, and he said to him: "Behold, you have been healed. Do not choose to sin further, otherwise something worse may happen to you."

15 This man went away, and he reported to the Jews that it was Jesus who had given him health.

16 Because of this, the Jews were persecuting Jesus, for he was doing these things on the Sabbath.

17 But Jesus answered them, "Even now, my Father is working, and I am working."

18 And so, because of this, the Jews were seeking to kill him even more so. For not only did he break the Sabbath, but he even said that God was his Father, making himself equal to God.

19 Then Jesus responded and said to them: "Amen, amen, I say to you, the Son is not able to do anything of himself, but only what he has seen the Father doing. For whatever he does, even this does the Son do, similarly.

20 For the Father loves the Son, and he shows him all that he himself does. And greater works than these will he show him, so much so that you shall wonder.

21 For just as the Father raises the dead and gives life, so also does the Son give life to whomever he wills.

22 For the Father does not judge anyone. But he has given all judgment to the Son,

23 so that all may honor the Son, just as they honor the Father. Whoever does not honor the Son, does not honor the Father who sent him.

24 Amen, amen, I say to you, that whoever hears my word, and believes in him who sent me, has eternal life, and he does not go into judgment, but instead he crosses from death into life.

25 Amen, amen, I say to you, that the hour is coming, and it is now, when the dead shall hear the voice of the Son of God; and those who hear it shall live.

26 For just as the Father has life in himself, so also has he granted to the Son to have life in himself.

27 And he has given him the authority to accomplish judgment. For he is the Son of man.

28 Do not be amazed at this. For the hour is coming in which all who are in the grave shall hear the voice of the Son of God.

29 And those who have done good shall go forth to the resurrection of life. Yet truly, those who have done evil shall go to the resurrection of judgment.

30 I am not able to do anything of myself. As I hear, so do I judge. And my judgment is just. For I do not seek my own will, but the will of him who sent me.

31 If I offer testimony about myself, my testimony is not true.

32 There is another who offers testimony about me, and I know that the testimony which he offers about me is true.

33 You sent to John, and he offered testimony to the truth.

34 But I do not accept testimony from man. Instead, I say these things, so that you may be saved.

35 He was a burning and shining light. So you were willing, at the time, to exult in his light.

36 But I hold a greater testimony than that of John. For the works which the Father has given to me, so that I may complete them, these works themselves that I do, offer testimony about me: that the Father has sent me.

37 And the Father who has sent me has himself offered testimony about me. And you have never heard his voice, nor have you beheld his appearance.

38 And you do not have his word abiding in you. For the one whom he sent, the same you would not believe.

39 Study the Scriptures. For you think that in them you have eternal life. And yet they also offer testimony about me.

40 And you are not willing to come to me, so that you may have life.

41 I do not accept glory from men.

42 But I know you, that you do not have the love of God within you.

43 I have come in the name of my Father, and you do not accept me. If another will arrive in his own name, him you will accept.

44 How are you able to believe, you who accept glory from one another and yet do not seek the glory that is from God alone?

45 Do not consider that I might accuse you with the Father. There is one who accuses you, Moses, in whom you hope.

46 For if you were believing in Moses, perhaps you would believe in me also. For he wrote about me.

47 But if you do not believe by his writings, how will you believe by my words?"

John 6

1 After these things, Jesus traveled across the sea of Galilee, which is the Sea of Tiberias.

2 And a great multitude was following him, for they saw the signs that he was accomplishing toward those who were infirm.

3 Therefore, Jesus went onto a mountain, and he sat down there with his disciples.

4 Now the Passover, the feast day of the Jews, was near.

5 And so, when Jesus had lifted up his eyes and had seen that a very great multitude came to him, he said to Philip, "From where should we buy bread, so that these may eat?"

6 But he said this to test him. For he himself knew what he would do.

7 Philip answered him, "Two hundred denarii of bread would not be sufficient for each of them to receive even a little."

8 One of his disciples, Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, said to him:

9 "There is a certain boy here, who has five barley loaves and two fish. But what are these among so many?"

10 Then Jesus said, "Have the men sit down to eat." Now, there was much grass in that place. And so the men, in number about five thousand, sat down to eat.

11 Therefore, Jesus took the bread, and when he had given thanks, he distributed it to those who were sitting down to eat; similarly also, from the fish, as much as they wanted.

12 Then, when they were filled, he said to his disciples, "Gather the fragments that are left over, lest they be lost."

13 And so they gathered, and they filled twelve baskets with the fragments of the five barley loaves, which were left over from those who had eaten.

14 Therefore, those men, when they had seen that Jesus had accomplished a sign, they said, "Truly, this one is the Prophet who is to come into the world."

15 And so, when he realized that they were going to come and take him away and make him king, Jesus fled back to the mountain, by himself alone.

16 Then, when evening arrived, his disciples descended to the sea.

17 And when they had climbed into a boat, they went across the sea to Capernaum. And darkness had now arrived, and Jesus had not returned to them.

18 Then the sea was stirred up by a great wind that was blowing.

19 And so, when they had rowed about twenty-five or thirty stadia, they saw Jesus walking on the sea, and drawing near to the boat, and they were afraid.

20 But he said to them: "It is I. Do not be afraid."

21 Therefore, they were willing to receive him into the boat. But immediately the boat was at the land to which they were going.

22 On the next day, the crowd which was standing across the sea saw that there were no other small boats in that place, except one, and that Jesus had not entered into the boat with his disciples, but that his disciples had departed alone.

23 Yet truly, other boats came over from Tiberias, next to the place where they had eaten the bread after the Lord gave thanks.

24 Therefore, when the crowd had seen that Jesus was not there, nor his disciples, they climbed into the small boats, and they went to Capernaum, seeking Jesus.

25 And when they had found him across the sea, they said to him, "Rabbi, when did you come here?"

26 Jesus answered them and said: "Amen, amen, I say to you, you seek me, not because you have seen signs, but because you have eaten from the bread and were satisfied.

27 Do not work for food that perishes, but for that which endures to eternal life, which the Son of man will give to you. For God the Father has sealed him."

28 Therefore, they said to him, "What should we do, so that we may labor in the works of God?"

29 Jesus responded and said to them, "This is the work of God, that you believe in him whom he sent."

30 And so they said to him: "Then what sign will you do, so that we may see it and believe in you? What will you work?

31 Our fathers ate manna in the desert, just as it has been written, 'He gave them bread from heaven to eat.' "

32 Therefore, Jesus said to them: "Amen, amen, I say to you, Moses did not give you bread from heaven, but my Father gives you the true bread from heaven.

33 For the bread of God is he who descends from heaven and gives life to the world."

34 And so they said to him, "Lord, give us this bread always."

35 Then Jesus said to them: "I am the bread of life. Whoever comes to me shall not hunger, and whoever believes in me shall never thirst.

36 But I say to you, that even though you have seen me, you do not believe.

37 All that the Father gives to me shall come to me. And whoever comes to me, I will not cast out.

38 For I descended from heaven, not to do my own will, but the will of him who sent me.

39 Yet this is the will of the Father who sent me: that I should lose nothing out of all that he has given to me, but that I should raise them up on the last day.

40 So then, this is the will of my Father who sent me: that everyone who sees the Son and believes in him may have eternal life, and I will raise him up on the last day."

41 Therefore, the Jews murmured about him, because he had said: "I am the living bread, who descended from heaven."

42 And they said: "Is this not Jesus, the son of Joseph, whose father and mother we know? Then how can he say: 'For I descended from heaven?' "

43 And so Jesus responded and said to them: "Do not choose to murmur among yourselves.

44 No one is able to come to me, unless the Father, who has sent me, has drawn him. And I will raise him up on the last day.

45 It has been written in the Prophets: 'And they shall all be taught by God.' Everyone who has listened and learned from the Father comes to me.

46 Not that anyone has seen the Father, except he who is from God; this one has seen the Father.

47 Amen, amen, I say to you, whoever believes in me has eternal life.

48 I am the bread of life.

49 Your fathers ate manna in the desert, and they died.

50 This is the bread which descends from heaven, so that if anyone will eat from it, he may not die.

51 I am the living bread, who descended from heaven.

52 If anyone eats from this bread, he shall live in eternity. And the bread that I will give is my flesh, for the life of the world."

53 Therefore, the Jews debated among themselves, saying, "How can this man give us his flesh to eat?"

54 And so, Jesus said to them: "Amen, amen, I say to you, unless you eat the flesh of the Son of man and drink his blood, you will not have life in you.

55 Whoever eats my flesh and drinks my blood has eternal life, and I will raise him up on the last day.

56 For my flesh is true food, and my blood is true drink.

57 Whoever eats my flesh and drinks my blood abides in me, and I in him.

58 Just as the living Father has sent me and I live because of the Father, so also whoever eats me, the same shall live because of me.

59 This is the bread that descends from heaven. It is not like the manna that your fathers ate, for they died. Whoever eats this bread shall live forever."

60 He said these things when he was teaching in the synagogue at Capernaum.

61 Therefore, many of his disciples, upon hearing this, said: "This saying is difficult," and, "Who is able to listen to it?"

62 But Jesus, knowing within himself that his disciples were murmuring about this, said to them: "Does this offend you?

63 Then what if you were to see the Son of man ascending to where he was before?

64 It is the Spirit who gives life. The flesh does not offer anything of benefit. The words that I have spoken to you are spirit and life.

65 But there are some among you who do not believe." For Jesus knew from the beginning who were unbelieving and which one would betray him.

66 And so he said, "For this reason, I said to you that no one is able to come to me, unless it has been given to him by my Father."

67 After this, many of his disciples went back, and they no longer walked with him.

68 Therefore, Jesus said to the twelve, "Do you also want to go away?"

69 Then Simon Peter answered him: "Lord, to whom would we go? You have the words of eternal life.

70 And we have believed, and we recognize that you are the Christ, the Son of God."

71 Jesus answered them: "Have I not chosen you twelve? And yet one among you is a devil."

72 Now he was speaking about Judas Iscariot, the son of Simon. For this one, even though he was one of the twelve, was about to betray him.

John 7

1 Then, after these things, Jesus was walking in Galilee. For he was not willing to walk in Judea, because the Jews were seeking to kill him.

2 Now the feast day of the Jews, the Feast of Tabernacles, was near.

3 And his brothers said to him: "Move away from here and go into Judea, so that your disciples there may also see your works that you do.

4 Of course, no one does anything in secret, but he himself seeks to be in the public view. Since you do these things, manifest yourself to the world."

5 For neither did his brothers believe in him.

6 Therefore, Jesus said to them: "My time has not yet come; but your time is always at hand.

7 The world cannot hate you. But it hates me, because I offer testimony about it, that its works are evil.

8 You may go up to this feast day. But I am not going up to this feast day, because my time has not yet been fulfilled."

9 When he had said these things, he himself remained in Galilee.

10 But after his brothers went up, then he also went up to the feast day, not openly, but as if in secret.

11 Therefore, the Jews were seeking him on the feast day, and they were saying, "Where is he?"

12 And there was much murmuring in the crowd concerning him. For certain ones were saying, "He is good." But others were saying, "No, for he seduces the crowds."

13 Yet no one was speaking openly about him, out of fear of the Jews.

14 Then, about the middle of the feast, Jesus ascended into the temple, and he was teaching.

15 And the Jews wondered, saying: "How does this one know letters, though he has not been taught?"

16 Jesus responded to them and said: "My doctrine is not of me, but of him who sent me.

17 If anyone has chosen to do his will, then he will realize, about the doctrine, whether it is from God, or whether I am speaking from myself.

18 Whoever speaks from himself seeks his own glory. But whoever seeks the glory of him who sent him, this one is true, and injustice is not in him.

19 Did not Moses give you the law? And yet not one among you keeps the law!

20 Why are you seeking to kill me?" The crowd responded and said: "You must have a demon. Who is seeking to kill you?"

21 Jesus responded and said to them: "One work have I done, and you all wonder.

22 For Moses gave you circumcision, (not that it is of Moses, but of the fathers) and on the Sabbath you circumcise a man.

23 If a man can receive circumcision on the Sabbath, so that the law of Moses may not be broken, why are you indignant toward me, because I have made a man whole on the Sabbath?

24 Do not judge according to appearances, but instead judge a just judgment."

25 Therefore, some of those from Jerusalem said: "Is he not the one whom they are seeking to kill?

26 And behold, he is speaking openly, and they say nothing to him. Could the leaders have decided that it is true this one is the Christ?

27 But we know him and where he is from. And when the Christ has arrived, no one will know where he is from."

28 Therefore, Jesus cried out in the temple, teaching and saying: "You know me, and you also know where I am from. And I have not arrived of myself, but he who sent me is true, and him you do not know.

29 I know him. For I am from him, and he has sent me."

30 Therefore, they were seeking to apprehend him, and yet no one laid hands on him, because his hour had not yet come.

31 But many among the crowd believed in him, and they were saying, "When the Christ arrives, will he perform more signs than this man does?"

32 The Pharisees heard the crowd murmuring these things about him. And the leaders and the Pharisees sent attendants to apprehend him.

33 Therefore, Jesus said to them: "For a brief time, I am still with you, and then I am going to him who sent me.

34 You shall seek me, and you will not find me. And where I am, you are not able to go."

35 And so the Jews said among themselves: "Where is this place to which he will go, such that we will not find him? Will he go to those dispersed among the Gentiles and teach the Gentiles?

36 What is this word that he spoke, 'You will seek me and you will not find me; and where I am, you are not able to go?' "

37 Then, on the last great day of the feast, Jesus was standing and crying out, saying: "If anyone thirsts, let him come to me and drink:

38 whoever believes in me, just as Scripture says, 'From his chest shall flow rivers of living water.' "

39 Now he said this about the Spirit, which those who believe in him would soon be receiving. For the Spirit had not yet been given, because Jesus had not yet been glorified.

40 Therefore, some from that crowd, when they had heard these words of his, were saying, "This one truly is the Prophet."

41 Others were saying, "He is the Christ." Yet certain ones were saying: "Does the Christ come from Galilee?

42 Does Scripture not say that the Christ comes from the offspring of David and from Bethlehem, the town where David was?"

43 And so there arose a dissension among the multitude because of him.

44 Now certain ones among them wanted to apprehended him, but no one laid hands upon him.

45 Therefore, the attendants went to the high priests and the Pharisees. And they said to them, "Why have you not brought him?"

46 The attendants responded, "Never has a man spoken like this man."

47 And so the Pharisees answered them: "Have you also been seduced?

48 Have any of the leaders believed in him, or any of the Pharisees?

49 But this crowd, which does not know the law, they are accursed."

50 Nicodemus, the one who came to him by night and who was one of them, said to them,

51 "Does our law judge a man, unless it has first heard him and has known what he has done?"

52 They responded and said to him: "Are you also a Galilean? Study the Scriptures, and see that a prophet does not arise from Galilee."

53 And each one returned to his own house.

John 8

1 But Jesus continued on to the Mount of Olives.

2 And early in the morning, he went again to the temple; and all the people came to him. And sitting down, he taught them.

3 Now the scribes and Pharisees brought forward a woman caught in adultery, and they stood her in front of them.

4 And they said to him: "Teacher, this woman was just now caught in adultery.

5 And in the law, Moses commanded us to stone such a one. Therefore, what do you say?"

6 But they were saying this to test him, so that they might be able to accuse him. Then Jesus bent down and wrote with his finger on the earth.

7 And then, when they persevered in questioning him, he stood upright and said to them, "Let whoever is without sin among you be the first to cast a stone at her."

8 And bending down again, he wrote on the earth.

9 But upon hearing this, they went away, one by one, beginning with the eldest. And Jesus alone remained, with the woman standing in front of him.

10 Then Jesus, raising himself up, said to her: "Woman, where are those who accused you? Has no one condemned you?"

11 And she said, "No one, Lord." Then Jesus said: "Neither will I condemn you. Go, and now do not choose to sin anymore."

12 Then Jesus spoke to them again, saying: "I am the light of the world. Whoever follows me does not walk in darkness, but shall have the light of life."

13 And so the Pharisees said to him, "You offer testimony about yourself; your testimony is not true."

14 Jesus responded and said to them: "Even though I offer testimony about myself, my testimony is true, for I know where I came from and where I am going.

15 You judge according to the flesh. I do not judge anyone.

16 And when I do judge, my judgment is true. For I am not alone, but it is I and he who sent me: the Father.

17 And it is written in your law that the testimony of two men is true.

18 I am one who offers testimony about myself, and the Father who sent me offers testimony about me."

19 Therefore, they said to him, "Where is your Father?" Jesus answered: "You know neither me, nor my Father. If you did know me, perhaps you would know my Father also."

20 Jesus spoke these words at the treasury, while teaching in the temple. And no one apprehended him, because his hour had not yet come.

21 Therefore, Jesus again spoke to them: "I am going, and you shall seek me. And you will die in your sin. Where I am going, you are not able to go."

22 And so the Jews said, "Is he going to kill himself, for he said: 'Where I am going, you are not able to go?' "

23 And he said to them: "You are from below. I am from above. You are of this world. I am not of this world.

24 Therefore, I said to you, that you will die in your sins. For if you will not believe that I am, you will die in your sin."

25 And so they said to him, "Who are you?" Jesus said to them: "The Beginning, who is also speaking to you.

26 I have much to say about you and to judge. But he who sent me is true. And what I have heard from him, this I speak within the world."

27 And they did not realize that he was calling God his Father.

28 And so Jesus said to them: "When you will have lifted up the Son of man, then you shall realize that I am, and that I do nothing of myself, but just as the Father has taught me, so do I speak.

29 And he who sent me is with me, and he has not abandoned me alone. For I always do what is pleasing to him."

30 As he was speaking these things, many believed in him.

31 Therefore, Jesus said to those Jews who believed in him: "If you will abide in my word, you will truly be my disciples.

32 And you shall know the truth, and the truth shall set you free."

33 They answered him: "We are the offspring of Abraham, and we have never been a slave to anyone. How can you say, 'You shall be set free?' "

34 Jesus answered them: "Amen, amen, I say to you, that everyone who commits sin is a slave of sin.

35 Now the slave does not abide in the house for eternity. Yet the Son does abide in eternity.

36 Therefore, if the Son has set you free, then you will truly be free.

37 I know that you are sons of Abraham. But you are seeking to kill me, because my word has not taken hold in you.

38 I speak what I have seen with my Father. And you do what you have seen with your father."

39 They responded and said to him, "Abraham is our father." Jesus said to them: "If you are the sons of Abraham, then do the works of Abraham.

40 But now you are seeking to kill me, a man who has spoken the truth to you, which I have heard from God. This is not what Abraham did.

41 You do the works of your father." Therefore, they said to him: "We were not born out of fornication. We have one father: God."

42 Then Jesus said to them: "If God were your father, certainly you would love me. For I proceeded and came from God. For I did not come from myself, but he sent me.

43 Why do you not recognize my speech? It is because you are not able to hear my word.

44 You are of your father, the devil. And you will carry out the desires of your father. He was a murderer from the beginning. And he did not stand in the truth, because the truth is not in him. When he speaks a lie, he speaks it from his own self. For he is a liar, and the father of lies.

45 But if I speak the truth, you do not believe me.

46 Which of you can convict me of sin? If I speak the truth to you, why do you not believe me?

47 Whoever is of God, hears the words of God. For this reason, you do not hear them: because you are not of God."

48 Therefore, the Jews responded and said to him, "Are we not correct in saying that you are a Samaritan, and that you have a demon?"

49 Jesus responded: "I do not have a demon. But I honor my Father, and you have dishonored me.

50 But I am not seeking my own glory. There is One who seeks and judges.

51 Amen, amen, I say to you, if anyone will have kept my word, he will not see death for eternity."

52 Therefore, the Jews said: "Now we know that you have a demon. Abraham is dead, and the Prophets; and yet you say, 'If anyone will have kept my word, he shall not taste death for eternity.'

53 Are you greater than our father Abraham, who is dead? And the prophets are dead. So who do you make yourself to be?"

54 Jesus responded: "If I glorify myself, my glory is nothing. It is my Father who glorifies me. And you say about him that he is your God.

55 And yet you have not known him. But I know him. And if I were to say that I do not know him, then I would be like you, a liar. But I know him, and I keep his word.

56 Abraham, your father, rejoiced that he might see my day; he saw it and was glad."

57 And so the Jews said to him, "You have not yet reached fifty years, and you have seen Abraham?"

58 Jesus said to them, "Amen, amen, I say to you, before Abraham was made, I am."

59 Therefore, they took up stones to cast at him. But Jesus hid himself, and he departed from the temple.

John 9

1 And Jesus, while passing by, saw a man blind from birth.

2 And his disciples asked him, "Rabbi, who sinned, this man or his parents, that he would be born blind?"

3 Jesus responded: "Neither this man nor his parents sinned, but it was so that the works of God would be made manifest in him.

4 I must work the works of him who sent me, while it is day: the night is coming, when no one is able to work.

5 As long as I am in the world, I am the light of the world."

6 When he had said these things, he spat on the ground, and he made clay from the spittle, and he smeared the clay over his eyes.

7 And he said to him: "Go, wash in the pool of Siloam" (which is translated as: one who has been sent). Therefore, he went away and washed, and he returned, seeing.

8 And so the bystanders and those who had seen him before, when he was a beggar, said, "Is this not the one who was sitting and begging?" Some said, "This is he."

9 But others said, "Certainly not, but he is similar to him." Yet truly, he himself said, "I am he."

10 Therefore, they said to him, "How were your eyes opened?"

11 He responded: "That man who is called Jesus made clay, and he anointed my eyes and said to me, 'Go to the pool of Siloam and wash.' And I went, and I washed, and I see."

12 And they said to him, "Where is he?" He said, "I do not know."

13 They brought the one who had been blind to the Pharisees.

14 Now it was the Sabbath, when Jesus made the clay and opened his eyes.

15 Therefore, again the Pharisees questioned him as to how he had seen. And he said to them, "He placed clay over my eyes, and I washed, and I see."

16 And so certain Pharisees said: "This man, who does not keep the Sabbath, is not from God." But others said, "How could a sinful man accomplish these signs?" And there was a schism among them.

17 Therefore, they spoke again to the blind man, "What do you say about him who opened your eyes?" Then he said, "He is a Prophet."

18 Therefore, the Jews did not believe, about him, that he had been blind and had seen, until they called the parents of him who had seen.

19 And they questioned them, saying: "Is this your son, whom you say was born blind? Then how is it that he now sees?"

20 His parents responded to them and said: "We know that this is our son and that he was born blind.

21 But how it is that he now sees, we do not know. And who opened his eyes, we do not know. Ask him. He is old enough. Let him speak for himself."

22 His parents said these things because they were afraid of the Jews. For the Jews had already conspired, so that if anyone were to confess him to be the Christ, he would be expelled from the synagogue.

23 It was for this reason that his parents said: "He is old enough. Ask him."

24 Therefore, they again called the man who had been blind, and they said to him: "Give glory to God. We know that this man is a sinner."

25 And so he said to them: "If he is a sinner, I do not know it. One thing I do know, that although I was blind, now I see."

26 Then they said to him: "What did he do to you? How did he open your eyes?"

27 He answered them: "I have already told you, and you heard it. Why do you want to hear it again? Do you also want to become his disciples?"

28 Therefore, they cursed him and said: "You be his disciple. But we are disciples of Moses.

29 We know that God spoke to Moses. But this man, we do not know where he is from."

30 The man responded and said to them: "Now in this is a wonder: that you do not know where he is from, and yet he has opened my eyes.

31 And we know that God does not hear sinners. But if anyone is a worshipper of God and does his will, then he heeds him.

32 From ancient times, it has not been heard that anyone has opened the eyes of someone born blind.

33 Unless this man were of God, he would not be able to do any such thing."

34 They responded and said to him, "You were born entirely in sins, and you would teach us?" And they cast him out.

35 Jesus heard that they had cast him out. And when he had found him, he said to him, "Do you believe in the Son of God?"

36 He responded and said, "Who is he, Lord, so that I may believe in him?"

37 And Jesus said to him, "You have both seen him, and he is the one who is speaking with you."

38 And he said, "I believe, Lord." And falling prostrate, he worshipped him.

39 And Jesus said, "I came into this world in judgment, so that those who do not see, may see; and so that those who see, may become blind."

40 And certain Pharisees, who were with him, heard this, and they said to him, "Are we also blind?"

41 Jesus said to them: "If you were blind, you would not have sin. Yet now you say, 'We see.' So your sin persists."

John 10

1 "Amen, amen, I say to you, he who does not enter through the door into the fold of the sheep, but climbs up by another way, he is a thief and a robber.

2 But he who enters through the door is the shepherd of the sheep.

3 To him the doorkeeper opens, and the sheep hear his voice, and he calls his own sheep by name, and he leads them out.

4 And when he has sent out his sheep, he goes before them, and the sheep follow him, because they know his voice.

5 But they do not follow a stranger; instead they flee from him, because they do not know the voice of strangers."

6 Jesus spoke this proverb to them. But they did not understand what he was saying to them.

7 Therefore, Jesus spoke to them again: "Amen, amen, I say to you, that I am the door of the sheep.

8 All others, as many as have come, are thieves and robbers, and the sheep did not listen to them.

9 I am the door. If anyone has entered through me, he will be saved. And he shall go in and go out, and he shall find pastures.

10 The thief does not come, except so that he may steal and slaughter and destroy. I have come so that they may have life, and have it more abundantly.

11 I am the good Shepherd. The good Shepherd gives his life for his sheep.

12 But the hired hand, and whoever is not a shepherd, to whom the sheep do not belong, he sees the wolf approaching, and he departs from the sheep and flees. And the wolf ravages and scatters the sheep.

13 And the hired hand flees, because he is a hired hand and there is no concern for the sheep within him.

14 I am the good Shepherd, and I know my own, and my own know me,

15 just as the Father knows me, and I know the Father. And I lay down my life for my sheep.

16 And I have other sheep that are not of this fold, and I must lead them. They shall hear my voice, and there shall be one sheepfold and one shepherd.

17 For this reason, the Father loves me: because I lay down my life, so that I may take it up again.

18 No one takes it away from me. Instead, I lay it down of my own accord. And I have the power to lay it down. And I have the power to take it up again. This is the commandment that I have received from my Father."

19 A dissension occurred again among the Jews because of these words.

20 Then many of them were saying: "He has a demon or he is insane. Why do you listen him?"

21 Others were saying: "These are not the words of someone who has a demon. How would a demon be able to open the eyes of the blind?"

22 Now it was the Feast of the Dedication at Jerusalem, and it was winter.

23 And Jesus was walking in the temple, in the portico of Solomon.

24 And so the Jews surrounded him and said to him: "How long will you hold our souls in suspense? If you are the Christ, tell us plainly."

25 Jesus answered them: "I speak to you, and you do not believe. The works that I do in the name of my Father, these offer testimony about me.

26 But you do not believe, because you are not of my sheep.

27 My sheep hear my voice. And I know them, and they follow me.

28 And I give them eternal life, and they shall not perish, for eternity. And no one shall seize them from my hand.

29 What my Father gave to me is greater than all, and no one is able to seize from the hand of my Father.

30 I and the Father are one."

31 Therefore, the Jews took up stones, in order to stone him.

32 Jesus answered them: "I have shown you many good works from my Father. For which of those works do you stone me?"

33 The Jews answered him: "We do not stone you for a good work, but for blasphemy and because, though you are a man, you make yourself God."

34 Jesus responded to them: "Is it not written in your law, 'I said: you are gods?'

35 If he called those to whom the word of God was given gods, and Scripture cannot be broken,

36 why do you say, about him whom the Father has sanctified and sent into the world, 'You have blasphemed,' because I said, 'I am the Son of God?'

37 If I do not do the works of my Father, do not believe in me.

38 But if I do them, even if you are not willing to believe in me, believe the works, so that you may know and believe that the Father is in me, and I am in the Father."

39 Therefore, they sought to apprehend him, but he escaped from their hands.

40 And he went again across the Jordan, to that place where John first was baptizing. And he lodged there.

41 And many went out to him. And they were saying: "Indeed, John accomplished no signs.

42 But all things whatsoever that John said about this man were true." And many believed in him.

John 11

1 Now there was a certain sick man, Lazarus of Bethania, from the town of Mary and her sister Martha.

2 And Mary was the one who anointed the Lord with ointment and wiped his feet with her hair; her brother Lazarus was sick.

3 Therefore, his sisters sent to him, saying: "Lord, behold, he whom you love is sick."

4 Then, upon hearing this, Jesus said to them: "This sickness is not unto death, but for the glory of God, so that the Son of God may be glorified by it."

5 Now Jesus loved Martha, and her sister Mary, and Lazarus.

6 Even so, after he heard that he was sick, he then still remained in the same place for two days.

7 Then, after these things, he said to his disciples, "Let us go into Judea again."

8 The disciples said to him: "Rabbi, the Jews are even now seeking to stone you. And would you go there again?"

9 Jesus responded: "Are there not twelve hours in the day? If anyone walks in the daylight, he does not stumble, because he sees the light of this world.

10 But if he walks in the nighttime, he stumbles, because the light is not in him."

11 He said these things, and after this, he said to them: "Lazarus our friend is sleeping. But I am going, so that I may awaken him from sleep."

12 And so his disciples said, "Lord, if he is sleeping, he shall be healthy."

13 But Jesus had spoken about his death. Yet they thought that he spoke about the repose of sleep.

14 Therefore, Jesus then said to them plainly, "Lazarus has died.

15 And I am glad for your sake that I was not there, so that you may believe. But let us go to him."

16 And then Thomas, who is called the Twin, said to his fellow disciples, "Let us go, too, so that we may die with him."

17 And so Jesus went. And he found that he had already been in the tomb for four days.

18 (Now Bethania was near Jerusalem, about fifteen stadia.)

19 And many of the Jews had come to Martha and Mary, so as to console them over their brother.

20 Therefore, Martha, when she heard that Jesus was arriving, went out to meet him. But Mary was sitting at home.

21 And then Martha said to Jesus: "Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died.

22 But even now, I know that whatever you will request from God, God will give to you."

23 Jesus said to her, "Your brother shall rise again."

24 Martha said to him, "I know that he shall rise again, at the resurrection on the last day."

25 Jesus said to her: "I am the Resurrection and the Life. Whoever believes in me, even though he has died, he shall live.

26 And everyone who lives and believes in me shall not die for eternity. Do you believe this?"

27 She said to him: "Certainly, Lord. I have believed that you are the Christ, the Son of the living God, who has come into this world."

28 And when she had said these things, she went and called her sister Mary quietly, saying, "The Teacher is here, and he is calling you."

29 When she heard this, she rose up quickly and went to him.

30 For Jesus had not yet arrived in the town. But he was still at that place where Martha had met him.

31 Therefore, the Jews who were with her in the house and who were consoling her, when they had seen that Mary rose up quickly and went out, they followed her, saying, "She is going to the tomb, so that she may weep there."

32 Therefore, when Mary had arrived to where Jesus was, seeing him, she fell down at his feet, and she said to him. "Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died."

33 And then, when Jesus saw her weeping, and the Jews who had arrived with her weeping, he groaned in spirit and became troubled.

34 And he said, "Where have you laid him?" They said to him, "Lord, come and see."

35 And Jesus wept.

36 Therefore, the Jews said, "See how much he loved him!"

37 But some of them said, "Would not he who opened the eyes of one born blind have been able to cause this man not to die?"

38 Therefore, Jesus, again groaning from within himself, went to the tomb. Now it was a cave, and a stone had been placed over it.

39 Jesus said, "Take away the stone." Martha, the sister of him who had died, said to him, "Lord, by now it will smell, for this is the fourth day."

40 Jesus said to her, "Did I not say to you that if you believe, you shall see the glory of God?"

41 Therefore, they took away the stone. Then, lifting up his eyes, Jesus said: "Father, I give thanks to you because you have heard me.

42 And I know that you always hear me, but I have said this for the sake of the people who are standing nearby, so that they may believe that you have sent me."

43 When he had said these things, he cried in a loud voice, "Lazarus, come out."

44 And immediately, he who had been dead went forth, bound at the feet and hands with winding bands. And his face was bound with a separate cloth. Jesus said to them, "Release him and let him go."

45 Therefore, many of the Jews, who had come to Mary and Martha, and who had seen the things that Jesus did, believed in him.

46 But certain ones among them went to the Pharisees and told them the things that Jesus had done.

47 And so, the high priests and the Pharisees gathered a council, and they were saying: "What can we do? For this man accomplishes many signs.

48 If we leave him alone, in this way all will believe in him. And then the Romans will come and take away our place and our nation."

49 Then one of them, named Caiaphas, since he was the high priest that year, said to them: "You do not understand anything.

50 Nor do you realize that it is expedient for you that one man should die for the people, and that the entire nation should not perish."

51 Yet he did not say this from himself, but since he was the high priest that year, he prophesied that Jesus would die for the nation.

52 And not only for the nation, but in order to gather together as one the children of God who have been dispersed.

53 Therefore, from that day, they planned to put him to death.

54 And so, Jesus no longer walked in public with the Jews. But he went into a region near the desert, to a city which is called Ephraim. And he lodged there with his disciples.

55 Now the Passover of the Jews was near. And many from the countryside ascended to Jerusalem before the Passover, so that they might sanctify themselves.

56 Therefore, they were seeking Jesus. And they conferred with one another, while standing in the temple: "What do you think? Will he come to the feast day?"

57 And the high priests and Pharisees had given an order, so that if anyone would know where he may be, he should reveal it, so that they might apprehend him.

John 12

1 Then six days before the Passover, Jesus went to Bethania, where Lazarus had died, whom Jesus raised up.

2 And they made a dinner for him there. And Martha was ministering. And truly, Lazarus was one of those who were sitting at table with him.

3 And then Mary took twelve ounces of pure spikenard ointment, very precious, and she anointed the feet of Jesus, and she wiped his feet with her hair. And the house was filled with the fragrance of the ointment.

4 Then one of his disciples, Judas Iscariot, who was soon to betray him, said,

5 "Why was this ointment not sold for three hundred denarii and given to the needy?"

6 Now he said this, not out of concern for the needy, but because he was a thief and, since he held the purse, he used to carry what was put into it.

7 But Jesus said: "Permit her, so that she may keep it against the day of my burial.

8 For the poor, you have with you always. But me, you do always not have."

9 Now a great multitude of the Jews knew that he was in that place, and so they came, not so much because of Jesus, but so that they might see Lazarus, whom he had raised from the dead.

10 And the leaders of the priests planned to put Lazarus to death also.

11 For many of the Jews, because of him, were going away and were believing in Jesus.

12 Then, on the next day, the great crowd that had come to the feast day, when they had heard that Jesus was coming to Jerusalem,

13 took branches of palm trees, and they went ahead to meet him. And they were crying out: "Hosanna! Blessed is he who arrives in the name of the Lord, the king of Israel!"

14 And Jesus found a small donkey, and he sat upon it, just as it is written:

15 "Do not be afraid, daughter of Zion. Behold, your king arrives, sitting on the colt of a donkey."

16 At first, his disciples did not realize these things. But when Jesus was glorified, then they remembered that these things were written about him, and that these things happened to him.

17 And so the crowd that had been with him, when he called Lazarus from the tomb and raised him from the dead, offered testimony.

18 Because of this, too, the crowd went out to meet him. For they heard that he had accomplished this sign.

19 Therefore, the Pharisees said among themselves: "Do you see that we are accomplishing nothing? Behold, the entire world has gone after him."

20 Now there were certain Gentiles among those who went up so that they might worship on the feast day.

21 Therefore, these approached Philip, who was from Bethsaida of Galilee, and they petitioned him, saying: "Sir, we want to see Jesus."

22 Philip went and told Andrew. Next, Andrew and Philip told Jesus.

23 But Jesus answered them by saying: "The hour arrives when the Son of man shall be glorified.

24 Amen, amen, I say to you, unless the grain of wheat falls to the ground and dies,

25 it remains alone. But if it dies, it yields much fruit. Whoever loves his life, will lose it. And whoever hates his life in this world, preserves it unto eternal life.

26 If anyone serves me, let him follow me. And where I am, there too my minister shall be. If anyone has served me, my Father will honor him.

27 Now my soul is troubled. And what should I say? Father, save me from this hour? But it is for this reason that I came to this hour.

28 Father, glorify your name!" And then a voice came from heaven, "I have glorified it, and I will glorify it again."

29 Therefore, the crowd, which was standing near and had heard it, said that it was like thunder. Others were saying, "An Angel was speaking with him."

30 Jesus responded and said: "This voice came, not for my sake, but for your sakes.

31 Now is the judgment of the world. Now will the prince of this world be cast out.

32 And when I have been lifted up from the earth, I will draw all things to myself."

33 (Now he said this, signifying what kind of death he would die.)

34 The crowd answered him: "We have heard, from the law, that the Christ remains forever. And so how can you say, 'The Son of man must be lifted up?' Who is this Son of man?"

35 Therefore, Jesus said to them: "For a brief time, the Light is among you. Walk while you have the Light, so that the darkness may not overtake you. But whoever walks in darkness does not know where is he going.

36 While you have the Light, believe in the Light, so that you may be sons of the Light." Jesus spoke these things, and then he went away and hid himself from them.

37 And although he had done such great signs in their presence, they did not believe in him,

38 so that the word of the prophet Isaiah might be fulfilled, which says: "Lord, who has believed in our hearing? And to whom has the arm of the Lord been revealed?"

39 Because of this, they were not able to believe, for Isaiah said again:

40 "He has blinded their eyes, and hardened their heart, so that they may not see with their eyes, and understand with their heart, and be converted: and then I would heal them."

41 These things Isaiah said, when he saw his glory and was speaking about him.

42 Yet truly, many of the leaders also believed in him. But because of the Pharisees, they did not confess him, so that they would not be cast out of the synagogue.

43 For they loved the glory of men more than the glory of God.

44 But Jesus cried out and said: "Whoever believes in me, does not believe in me, but in him who sent me.

45 And whoever sees me, sees him who sent me.

46 I have arrived as a light to the world, so that all who believe in me might not remain in darkness.

47 And if anyone has heard my words and not kept them, I do not judge him. For I did not come so that I may judge the world, but so that I may save the world.

48 Whoever despises me and does not accept my words has one who judges him. The word that I have spoken, the same shall judge him on the last day.

49 For I am not speaking from myself, but from the Father who sent me. He gave a commandment to me as to what I should say and how I should speak.

50 And I know that his commandment is eternal life. Therefore, the things that I speak, just as the Father has said to me, so also do I speak."

John 13

1 Before the feast day of the Passover, Jesus knew that the hour was approaching when he would pass from this world to the Father. And since he had always loved his own who were in the world, he loved them unto the end.

2 And when the meal had taken place, when the devil had now put it into the heart of Judas Iscariot, the son of Simon, to betray him,

3 knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands and that he came from God and was going to God,

4 he rose up from the meal, and he set aside his vestments, and when he had received a towel, he wrapped it around himself.

5 Next he put water into a shallow bowl, and he began to wash the feet of the disciples and to wipe them with the towel with which he was wrapped.

6 And then he came to Simon Peter. And Peter said to him, "Lord, would you wash my feet?"

7 Jesus responded and said to him: "What I am doing, you do not now understand. But you shall understand it afterward."

8 Peter said to him, "You shall never wash my feet!" Jesus answered him, "If I do not wash you, you will have no place with me."

9 Simon Peter said to him, "Then Lord, not only my feet, but also my hands and my head!"

10 Jesus said to him: "He who is washed need only wash his feet, and then he will be entirely clean. And you are clean, but not all."

11 For he knew which one would betray him. For this reason, he said, "You are not all clean."

12 And so, after he washed their feet and received his vestments, when he had sat down at table again, he said to them: "Do you know what I have done for you?

13 You call me Teacher and Lord, and you speak well: for so I am.

14 Therefore, if I, your Lord and Teacher, have washed your feet, you also ought to wash the feet of one another.

15 For I have given you an example, so that just as I have done for you, so also should you do.

16 Amen, amen, I say to you, the servant is not greater than his Lord, and the apostle is not greater than he who sent him.

17 If you understand this, you shall be blessed if you will do it.

18 I am not speaking about all of you. I know those whom I have chosen. But this is so that the Scripture may be fulfilled, 'He who eats bread with me shall lift up his heel against me.'

19 And I tell you this now, before it happens, so that when it has happened, you may believe that I am.

20 Amen, amen, I say to you, whoever receives anyone whom I send, receives me. And whoever receives me, receives him who sent me."

21 When Jesus had said these things, he was troubled in spirit. And he bore witness by saying: "Amen, amen, I say to you, that one among you shall betray me."

22 Therefore, the disciples looked around at one another, uncertain about whom he spoke.

23 And leaning against the bosom of Jesus was one of his disciples, the one whom Jesus loved.

24 Therefore, Simon Peter motioned to this one and said to him, "Who is it that he is speaking about?"

25 And so, leaning against the chest of Jesus, he said to him, "Lord, who is it?"

26 Jesus responded, "It is he to whom I shall extend the dipped bread." And when he had dipped the bread, he gave it to Judas Iscariot, son of Simon.

27 And after the morsel, Satan entered into him. And Jesus said to him, "What you are going to do, do quickly."

28 Now none of those sitting at table knew why he had said this to him.

29 For some were thinking that, because Judas held the purse, that Jesus had told him, "Buy those things which are needed by us for the feast day," or that he might give something to the needy.

30 Therefore, having accepted the morsel, he went out immediately. And it was night.

31 Then, when he had gone out, Jesus said: "Now the Son of man has been glorified, and God has been glorified in him.

32 If God has been glorified in him, then God will also glorify him in himself, and he will glorify him without delay.

33 Little sons, for a brief while, I am with you. You shall seek me, and just as I said to the Jews, 'Where I am going, you are not able to go,' so also I say to you now.

34 I give you a new commandment: Love one another. Just as I have loved you, so also must you love one another.

35 By this, all shall recognize that you are my disciples: if you will have love for one another."

36 Simon Peter said to him, "Lord, where are you going?" Jesus responded: "Where I am going, you are not able to follow me now. But you shall follow afterward."

37 Peter said to him: "Why am I unable to follow you now? I will lay down my life for you!"

38 Jesus answered him: "You will lay down your life for me? Amen, amen, I say to you, the rooster will not crow, until you deny me three times."

John 14

1 "Do not let your heart be troubled. You believe in God. Believe in me also.

2 In my Father's house, there are many dwelling places. If there were not, I would have told you. For I go to prepare a place for you.

3 And if I go and prepare a place for you, I will return again, and then I will take you to myself, so that where I am, you also may be.

4 And you know where I am going. And you know the way."

5 Thomas said to him, "Lord, we do not know where you are going, so how can we know the way?"

6 Jesus said to him: "I am the Way, and the Truth, and the Life. No one comes to the Father, except through me.

7 If you had known me, certainly you would also have known my Father. And from now on, you shall know him, and you have seen him."

8 Philip said to him, "Lord, reveal the Father to us, and it is enough for us."

9 Jesus said to him: "Have I been with you for so long, and you have not known me? Philip, whoever sees me, also sees the Father. How can you say, 'Reveal the Father to us?'

10 Do you not believe that I am in the Father and the Father is in me? The words that I am speaking to you, I do not speak from myself. But the Father abiding in me, he does these works.

11 Do you not believe that I am in the Father and the Father is in me?

12 Or else, believe because of these same works. Amen, amen, I say to you, whoever believes in me shall also do the works that I do. And greater things than these shall he do, for I go to the Father.

13 And whatever you shall ask the Father in my name, that I will do, so that the Father may be glorified in the Son.

14 If you shall ask anything of me in my name, that I will do.

15 If you love me, keep my commandments.

16 And I will ask the Father, and he will give another Advocate to you, so that he may abide with you for eternity:

17 the Spirit of Truth, whom the world is not able to accept, because it neither perceives him nor knows him. But you shall know him. For he will remain with you, and he will be in you.

18 I will not leave you orphans. I will return to you.

19 Yet a little while and the world will not see me any longer. But you will see me. For I live, and you shall live.

20 In that day, you shall know that I am in my Father, and you are in me, and I am in you.

21 Whoever holds to my commandments and keeps them: it is he who loves me. And whoever loves me shall be loved by my Father. And I will love him, and I will manifest myself to him."

22 Judas, not the Iscariot, said to him: "Lord, how does it happen that you will manifest yourself to us and not to the world?"

23 Jesus responded and said to him: "If anyone loves me, he shall keep my word. And my Father will love him, and we will come to him, and we will make our dwelling place with him.

24 Whoever does not love me, does not keep my words. And the word that you have heard is not of me, but it is of the Father who sent me.

25 These things I have spoken to you, while abiding with you.

26 But the Advocate, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, will teach you all things and will suggest to you everything whatsoever that I have said to you.

27 Peace I leave for you; my Peace I give to you. Not in the way that the world gives, do I give to you. Do not let your heart be troubled, and let it not fear.

28 You have heard that I said to you: I am going away, and I am returning to you. If you loved me, certainly you would be gladdened, because I am going to the Father. For the Father is greater than I.

29 And now I have told you this, before it happens, so that, when it will happen, you may believe.

30 I will not now speak at length with you. For the prince of this world is coming, but he does not have anything in me.

31 Yet this is so that the world may know that I love the Father, and that I am acting according to the commandment that the Father has given to me. Rise up, let us go from here."

John 15

1 "I am the true vine, and my Father is the vinedresser.

2 Every branch in me that does not bear fruit, he will take away. And each one that does bear fruit, he will cleanse, so that it may bring forth more fruit.

3 You are clean now, because of the word that I have spoken to you.

4 Abide in me, and I in you. Just as the branch is not able to bear fruit of itself, unless it abides in the vine, so also are you unable, unless you abide in me.

5 I am the vine; you are the branches. Whoever abides in me, and I in him, bears much fruit. For without me, you are able to do nothing.

6 If anyone does not abide in me, he will be cast away, like a branch, and he will wither, and they will gather him and cast him into the fire, and he burns.

7 If you abide in me, and my words abide in you, then you may ask for whatever you will, and it shall be done for you.

8 In this, my Father is glorified: that you should bring forth very much fruit and become my disciples.

9 As the Father has loved me, so I have loved you. Abide in my love.

10 If you keep my precepts, you shall abide in my love, just as I also have kept my Father's precepts and I abide in his love.

11 These things I have spoken to you, so that my joy may be in you, and your joy may be fulfilled.

12 This is my precept: that you love one another, just as I have loved you.

13 No one has a greater love than this: that he lay down his life for his friends.

14 You are my friends, if you do what I instruct you.

15 I will no longer call you servants, for the servant does not know what his Lord is doing. But I have called you friends, because everything whatsoever that I have heard from my Father, I have made known to you.

16 You have not chosen me, but I have chosen you. And I have appointed you, so that you may go forth and bear fruit, and so that your fruit may last. Then whatever you have asked of the Father in my name, he shall give to you.

17 This I command you: that you love one another.

18 If the world hates you, know that it has hated me before you.

19 If you had been of the world, the world would love what is its own. Yet truly, you are not of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world; because of this, the world hates you.

20 Remember my saying that I told you: The servant is not greater than his Lord. If they have persecuted me, they will persecute you also. If they have kept my word, they will keep yours also.

21 But all these things they will do to you because of my name, for they do not know him who sent me.

22 If I had not come and had not spoken to them, they would not have sin. But now they have no excuse for their sin.

23 Whoever hates me, hates my Father also.

24 If I had not accomplished among them works that no other person has accomplished, they would not have sin. But now they have both seen me, and they have hated me and my Father.

25 But this is so that the word may be fulfilled which was written in their law: 'For they hated me without cause.'

26 But when the Advocate has arrived, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth who proceeds from the Father, he will offer testimony about me.

27 And you shall offer testimony, because you are with me from the beginning."

John 16

1 "These things I have spoken to you, so that you would not stumble.

2 They will put you out of the synagogues. But the hour is coming when everyone who puts you to death will consider that he is offering an excellent service to God.

3 And they will do these things to you because they have not known the Father, nor me.

4 But these things I have spoken to you, so that, when the hour for these things will have arrived, you may remember that I told you.

5 But I did not tell you these things from the beginning, because I was with you. And now I am going to him who sent me. And no one among you has asked me, 'Where are you going?'

6 But because I have spoken these things to you, sorrow has filled your heart.

7 But I tell you the truth: it is expedient for you that I am going. For if I do not go, the Advocate will not come to you. But when I will have gone away, I will send him to you.

8 And when he has arrived, he will argue against the world, about sin and about justice and about judgment:

9 about sin, indeed, because they have not believed in me;

10 about justice, truly, because I am going to the Father, and you will not see me any longer;

11 about judgment, then, because the prince of this world has already been judged.

12 I still have many things to say to you, but you are not able to bear them now.

13 But when the Spirit of truth has arrived, he will teach the whole truth to you. For he will not be speaking from himself. Instead, whatever he will hear, he will speak. And he will announce to you the things that are to come.

14 He shall glorify me. For he will receive from what is mine, and he will announce it to you.

15 All things whatsoever that the Father has are mine. For this reason, I said that he will receive from what is mine and that he will announce it to you.

16 A little while, and then you will not see me. And again a little while, and you will see me. For I am going to the Father."

17 Then some of his disciples said to one another: "What is this, that he is saying to us: 'A little while, and you will not see me,' and 'Again a little while, and you will see me,' and, 'For I am going to the Father?' "

18 And they said: "What is this, that he is saying, 'A little while?' We do not understand what he is saying."

19 But Jesus realized that they wanted to question him, and so he said to them: "Are you inquiring among yourselves about this, that I said: 'A little while, and you will not see me, and again a little while, and you will see me?'

20 Amen, amen, I say to you, that you shall mourn and weep, but the world will rejoice. And you shall be greatly saddened, yet your sorrow shall be turned into joy.

21 A woman, when she is giving birth, has sorrow, because her hour has arrived. But when she has given birth to the child, then she no longer remembers the difficulties, because of the joy: for a man has been born into the world.

22 Therefore, you also, indeed, have sorrow now. But I will see you again, and your heart shall rejoice. And no one will take away your joy from you.

23 And, in that day, you will not petition me for anything. Amen, amen, I say to you, if you ask the Father for anything in my name, he will give it to you.

24 Until now, you have not requested anything in my name. Ask, and you shall receive, so that your joy may be full.

25 I have spoken these things to you in proverbs. The hour is coming when I will no longer speak to you in proverbs; instead, I will announce to you plainly from the Father.

26 In that day, you shall ask in my name, and I do not say to you that I will ask the Father for you.

27 For the Father himself loves you, because you have loved me, and because you have believed that I went forth from God.

28 I went forth from the Father, and I have come into the world. Next I am leaving the world, and I am going to the Father."

29 His disciples said to him: "Behold, now you are speaking plainly and not reciting a proverb.

30 Now we know that you know all things, and that you have no need for anyone to question you. By this, we believe that you went forth from God."

31 Jesus answered them: "Do you believe now?

32 Behold, the hour is coming, and it has now arrived, when you will be scattered, each one on his own, and you will leave me behind, alone. And yet I am not alone, for the Father is with me.

33 These things I have spoken to you, so that you may have peace in me. In the world, you will have difficulties. But have confidence: I have overcome the world."

John 17

1 Jesus said these things, and then, lifting up his eyes toward heaven, he said: "Father, the hour has arrived: glorify your Son, so that your Son may glorify you,

2 just as you have given authority over all flesh to him, so that he may give eternal life to all those whom you have given to him.

3 And this is eternal life: that they may know you, the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom you have sent.

4 I have glorified you on earth. I have completed the work that you gave me to accomplish.

5 And now Father, glorify me within yourself, with the glory that I had with you before the world ever was.

6 I have manifested your name to the men whom you have given to me from the world. They were yours, and you gave them to me. And they have kept your word.

7 Now they realize that all the things that you have given me are from you.

8 For I have given them the words that you gave to me. And they have accepted these words, and they have truly understood that I went forth from you, and they have believed that you sent me.

9 I pray for them. I do not pray for the world, but for those whom you have given to me. For they are yours.

10 And all that is mine is yours, and all that is yours is mine, and I am glorified in this.

11 And though I am not in the world, these are in the world, and I am coming to you. Father most holy, preserve them in your name, those whom you have given to me, so that they may be one, even as we are one.

12 While I was with them, I preserved them in your name. I have guarded those whom you have given to me, and not one of them is lost, except the son of perdition, so that the Scripture may be fulfilled.

13 And now I am coming to you. But I am speaking these things in the world, so that they may have the fullness of my joy within themselves.

14 I have given them your word, and the world has hated them. For they are not of the world, just as I, too, am not of the world.

15 I am not praying that you would take them out of the world, but that you would preserve them from evil.

16 They are not of the world, just as I also am not of the world.

17 Sanctify them in truth. Your word is truth.

18 Just as you have sent me into the world, I also have sent them into the world.

19 And it is for them that I sanctify myself, so that they, too, may be sanctified in truth.

20 But I am not praying for them only, but also for those who through their word shall believe in me.

21 So may they all be one. Just as you, Father, are in me, and I am in you, so also may they be one in us: so that the world may believe that you have sent me.

22 And the glory that you have given to me, I have given to them, so that they may be one, just as we also are one.

23 I am in them, and you are in me. So may they be perfected as one. And may the world know that you have sent me and that you have loved them, just as you have also loved me.

24 Father, I will that where I am, those whom you have given to me may also be with me, so that they may see my glory which you have given to me. For you loved me before the founding of the world.

25 Father most just, the world has not known you. But I have known you. And these have known that you sent me.

26 And I have made known your name to them, and I will make it known, so that the love in which you have loved me may be in them, and so that I may be in them."

John 18

1 When Jesus had said these things, he departed with his disciples across the Torrent of Kidron, where there was a garden, into which he entered with his disciples.

2 But Judas, who betrayed him, also knew the place, for Jesus had frequently met with his disciples there.

3 Then Judas, when he had received a cohort from both the high priests and the attendants of the Pharisees, approached the place with lanterns and torches and weapons.

4 And so Jesus, knowing all that was about to happen to him, advanced and said to them, "Who are you seeking?"

5 They answered him, "Jesus the Nazarene." Jesus said to them, "I am he." Now Judas, who betrayed him, was also standing with them.

6 Then, when he said to them, "I am he," they moved back and fell to the ground.

7 Then again he questioned them: "Who are you seeking?" And they said, "Jesus the Nazarene."

8 Jesus responded: "I told you that I am he. Therefore, if you are seeking me, permit these others to go away."

9 This was so that the word might be fulfilled, which he said, "Of those whom you have given to me, I have not lost any of them."

10 Then Simon Peter, having a sword, drew it, and he struck the servant of the high priest, and he cut off his right ear. Now the name of the servant was Malchus.

11 Therefore, Jesus said to Peter: "Set your sword into the scabbard. Should I not drink the chalice which my Father has given to me?"

12 Then the cohort, and the tribune, and the attendants of the Jews apprehended Jesus and bound him.

13 And they led him away, first to Annas, for he was the father-in-law of Caiaphas, who was the high priest that year.

14 Now Caiaphas was the one who had given counsel to the Jews that it was expedient for one man to die for the people.

15 And Simon Peter was following Jesus with another disciple. And that disciple was known to the high priest, and so he entered with Jesus into the court of the high priest.

16 But Peter was standing outside at the entrance. Therefore, the other disciple, who was known to the high priest, went out and spoke to the woman who was the doorkeeper, and he led in Peter.

17 Therefore, the woman servant keeping the door said to Peter, "Are you not also among the disciples of this man?" He said, "I am not."

18 Now the servants and attendants were standing before burning coals, for it was cold, and they were warming themselves. And Peter was standing with them also, warming himself.

19 Then the high priest questioned Jesus about his disciples and about his doctrine.

20 Jesus responded to him: "I have spoken openly to the world. I have always taught in the synagogue and in the temple, where all the Jews meet. And I have said nothing in secret.

21 Why do you question me? Question those who heard what I said to them. Behold, they know these things that I have said."

22 Then, when he had said this, one the attendants standing nearby struck Jesus, saying: "Is this the way you answer the high priest?"

23 Jesus answered him: "If I have spoken wrongly, offer testimony about the wrong. But if I have spoken correctly, then why do you strike me?"

24 And Annas sent him bound to Caiaphas, the high priest.

25 Now Simon Peter was standing and warming himself. Then they said to him, "Are you not also one of his disciples?" He denied it and said, "I am not."

26 One of the servants of the high priest (a relative of him whose ear Peter had cut off) said to him, "Did I not see you in the garden with him?"

27 Therefore, again, Peter denied it. And immediately the rooster crowed.

28 Then they led Jesus from Caiaphas into the praetorium. Now it was morning, and so they did not enter into the praetorium, so that they would not be defiled, but might eat the Passover.

29 Therefore, Pilate went outside to them, and he said, "What accusation are you bringing against this man?"

30 They responded and said to him, "If he were not an evil-doer, we would not have handed him over you."

31 Therefore, Pilate said to them, "Take him yourselves and judge him according to your own law." Then the Jews said to him, "It is not lawful for us to execute anyone."

32 This was so that the word of Jesus would be fulfilled, which he spoke signifying what kind of death he would die.

33 Then Pilate entered the praetorium again, and he called Jesus and said to him, "You are the king of the Jews?"

34 Jesus responded, "Are you saying this of yourself, or have others spoken to you about me?"

35 Pilate responded: "Am I a Jew? Your own nation and the high priests have handed you over to me. What have you done?"

36 Jesus responded: "My kingdom is not of this world. If my kingdom were of this world, my ministers would certainly strive so that I would not be handed over to the Jews. But my kingdom is not now from here."

37 And so Pilate said to him, "You are a king, then?" Jesus answered, "You are saying that I am a king. For this I was born, and for this I came into the world: so that I may offer testimony to the truth. Everyone who is of the truth hears my voice."

38 Pilate said to him, "What is truth?" And when he had said this, he went out again to the Jews, and he said to them, "I find no case against him.

39 But you have a custom, that I should release someone to you at the Passover. Therefore, do you want me to release to you the king of the Jews?"

40 Then they all cried out repeatedly, saying: "Not this one, but Barabbas." Now Barabbas was a robber.

John 19

1 Therefore, Pilate then took Jesus into custody and scourged him.

2 And the soldiers, plaiting a crown of thorns, imposed it on his head. And they put a purple garment around him.

3 And they were approaching him and saying, "Hail, king of the Jews!" And they struck him repeatedly.

4 Then Pilate went outside again, and he said to them: "Behold, I am bringing him out to you, so that you may realize that I find no case against him."

5 (Then Jesus went out, bearing the crown of thorns and the purple garment.) And he said to them, "Behold the man."

6 Therefore, when the high priests and the attendants had seen him, they cried out, saying: "Crucify him! Crucify him!" Pilate said to them: "Take him yourselves and crucify him. For I find no case against him."

7 The Jews answered him, "We have a law, and according to the law, he ought to die, for he has made himself the Son of God."

8 Therefore, when Pilate had heard this word, he was more fearful.

9 And he entered into the praetorium again. And he said to Jesus. "Where are you from?" But Jesus gave him no response.

10 Therefore, Pilate said to him: "Will you not speak to me? Do you not know that I have authority to crucify you, and I have authority to release you?"

11 Jesus responded, "You would not have any authority over me, unless it were given to you from above. For this reason, he who has handed me over to you has the greater sin."

12 And from then on, Pilate was seeking to release him. But the Jews were crying out, saying: "If you release this man, you are no friend of Caesar. For anyone who makes himself a king contradicts Caesar."

13 Now when Pilate had heard these words, he brought Jesus outside, and he sat down in the seat of judgment, in a place which is called the Pavement, but in Hebrew, it is called the Elevation.

14 Now it was the preparation day of the Passover, about the sixth hour. And he said to the Jews, "Behold your king."

15 But they were crying out: "Take him away! Take him away! Crucify him!" Pilate said to them, "Shall I crucify your king?" The high priests responded, "We have no king except Caesar."

16 Therefore, he then handed him over to them to be crucified. And they took Jesus and led him away.

17 And carrying his own cross, he went forth to the place which is called Calvary, but in Hebrew it is called the Place of the Skull.

18 There they crucified him, and with him two others, one on each side, with Jesus in the middle.

19 Then Pilate also wrote a title, and he set it above the cross. And it was written: JESUS THE NAZARENE, KING OF THE JEWS.

20 Therefore, many of the Jews read this title, for the place where Jesus was crucified was close to the city. And it was written in Hebrew, in Greek, and in Latin.

21 Then the high priests of the Jews said to Pilate: Do not write, 'King of the Jews,' but that he said, 'I am King of the Jews.'

22 Pilate responded, "What I have written, I have written."

23 Then the soldiers, when they had crucified him, took his garments, and they made four parts, one part to each soldier, and the tunic. But the tunic was seamless, woven from above throughout the whole.

24 Then they said to one another, "Let us not cut it, but instead let us cast lots over it, to see whose it will be." This was so that the Scripture would be fulfilled, saying: "They have distributed my garments among themselves, and for my vesture they have cast lots." And indeed, the soldiers did these things.

25 And standing beside the cross of Jesus were his mother, and his mother's sister, and Mary of Cleophas, and Mary Magdalene.

26 Therefore, when Jesus had seen his mother and the disciple whom he loved standing near, he said to his mother, "Woman, behold your son."

27 Next, he said to the disciple, "Behold your mother." And from that hour, the disciple accepted her as his own.

28 After this, Jesus knew that all had been accomplished, so in order that the Scripture might be completed, he said, "I thirst."

29 And there was a container placed there, full of vinegar. Then, placing a sponge full of vinegar around hyssop, they brought it to his mouth.

30 Then Jesus, when he had received the vinegar, said: "It is consummated." And bowing down his head, he surrendered his spirit.

31 Then the Jews, because it was the preparation day, so that the bodies would not remain upon the cross on the Sabbath (for that Sabbath was a great day), they petitioned Pilate in order that their legs might be broken, and they might be taken away.

32 Therefore, the soldiers approached, and, indeed, they broke the legs of the first one, and of the other who was crucified with him.

33 But after they had approached Jesus, when they saw that he was already dead, they did not break his legs.

34 Instead, one of the soldiers opened his side with a lance, and immediately there went out blood and water.

35 And he who saw this has offered testimony, and his testimony is true. And he knows that he speaks the truth, so that you also may believe.

36 For these things happened so that the Scripture would be fulfilled: "You shall not break a bone of him."

37 And again, another Scripture says: "They shall look upon him, whom they have pierced."

38 Then, after these things, Joseph from Arimathea, (because he was a disciple of Jesus, but a secret one for fear of the Jews) petitioned Pilate so that he might take away the body of Jesus. And Pilate gave permission. Therefore, he went and took away the body of Jesus.

39 Now Nicodemus also arrived, (who had gone to Jesus at first by night) bringing a mixture of myrrh and aloe, weighing about seventy pounds.

40 Therefore, they took the body of Jesus, and they bound it with linen cloths and the aromatic spices, just as it is the manner of the Jews to bury.

41 Now in the place where he was crucified there was a garden, and in the garden there was a new tomb, in which no one had yet been laid.

42 Therefore, because of the preparation day of the Jews, since the tomb was nearby, they placed Jesus there.

John 20

1 Then on the first Sabbath, Mary Magdalene went to the tomb early, while it was still dark, and she saw that the stone had been rolled away from the tomb.

2 Therefore, she ran and went to Simon Peter, and to the other disciple, whom Jesus loved, and she said to them, "They have taken the Lord away from the tomb, and we do not know where they have laid him."

3 Therefore, Peter departed with the other disciple, and they went to the tomb.

4 Now they both ran together, but the other disciple ran more quickly, ahead of Peter, and so he arrived at the tomb first.

5 And when he bowed down, he saw the linen cloths lying there, but he did not yet enter.

6 Then Simon Peter arrived, following him, and he entered the tomb, and he saw the linen cloths lying there,

7 and the separate cloth which had been over his head, not placed with the linen cloths, but in a separate place, wrapped up by itself.

8 Then the other disciple, who had arrived first at the tomb, also entered. And he saw and believed.

9 For as yet they did not understand the Scripture, that it was necessary for him to rise again from the dead.

10 Then the disciples went away again, each by himself.

11 But Mary was standing outside the tomb, weeping. Then, while she was weeping, she bowed down and gazed into the tomb.

12 And she saw two Angels in white, sitting where the body of Jesus had been placed, one at the head, and one at the feet.

13 They say to her, "Woman, why are you weeping?" She said to them, "Because they have taken away my Lord, and I do not know where they have placed him."

14 When she had said this, she turned around and saw Jesus standing there, but she did not know that it was Jesus.

15 Jesus said to her: "Woman, why are you weeping? Who are you seeking?" Considering that it was the gardener, she said to him, "Sir, if you have moved him, tell me where you have placed him, and I will take him away."

16 Jesus said to her, "Mary!" And turning, she said to him, "Rabboni!" (which means, Teacher).

17 Jesus said to her: "Do not touch me. For I have not yet ascended to my Father. But go to my brothers and tell them: 'I am ascending to my Father and to your Father, to my God and to your God.' "

18 Mary Magdalene went, announcing to the disciples, "I have seen the Lord, and these are the things that he said to me."

19 Then, when it was late on the same day, on the first of the Sabbaths, and the doors were closed where the disciples were gathered, for fear of the Jews, Jesus came and stood in their midst, and he said to them: "Peace to you."

20 And when he had said this, he showed them his hands and side. And the disciples were gladdened when they saw the Lord.

21 Therefore, he said to them again: "Peace to you. As the Father has sent me, so I send you."

22 When he had said this, he breathed on them. And he said to them: "Receive the Holy Spirit.

23 Those whose sins you shall forgive, they are forgiven them, and those whose sins you shall retain, they are retained."

24 Now Thomas, one of the twelve, who is called the Twin, was not with them when Jesus arrived.

25 Therefore, the other disciples said to him, "We have seen the Lord." But he said to them, "Unless I will see in his hands the mark of the nails and place my finger into the place of the nails, and place my hand into his side, I will not believe."

26 And after eight days, again his disciples were within, and Thomas was with them. Jesus arrived, though the doors had been closed, and he stood in their midst and said, "Peace to you."

27 Next, he said to Thomas: "Look at my hands, and place your finger here; and bring your hand close, and place it at my side. And do not choose to be unbelieving, but faithful."

28 Thomas responded and said to him, "My Lord and my God."

29 Jesus said to him: "You have seen me, Thomas, so you have believed. Blessed are those who have not seen and yet have believed."

30 Jesus also accomplished many other signs in the sight of his disciples. These have not been written in this book.

31 But these things have been written, so that you may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God, and so that, in believing, you may have life in his name.

John 21

1 After this, Jesus manifested himself again to the disciples at the Sea of Tiberias. And he manifested himself in this way.

2 These were together: Simon Peter and Thomas, who is called the Twin, and Nathanael, who was from Cana of Galilee, and the sons of Zebedee, and two others of his disciples.

3 Simon Peter said to them, "I am going fishing." They said to him, "And we are going with you." And they went and climbed into the ship. And in that night, they caught nothing.

4 But when morning arrived, Jesus stood on the shore. Yet the disciples did not realize that it was Jesus.

5 Then Jesus said to them, "Children, do you have any food?" They answered him, "No."

6 He said to them, "Cast the net to the right side of the ship, and you will find some." Therefore, they cast it out, and then they were not able to draw it in, because of the multitude of fish.

7 Therefore, the disciple whom Jesus loved said to Peter, "It is the Lord." Simon Peter, when he had heard that it was the Lord, wrapped his tunic around himself, (for he was naked) and he cast himself into the sea.

8 Then the other disciples arrived in a boat, (for they were not far from the land, only about two hundred cubits) dragging the net with the fish.

9 Then, when they climbed down to the land they saw burning coals prepared, and fish already placed above them, and bread.

10 Jesus said to them, "Bring some of the fish that you have just now caught."

11 Simon Peter climbed up and drew in the net to land: full of large fish, one hundred and fifty-three of them. And although there were so many, the net was not torn.

12 Jesus said to them, "Approach and dine." And not one of them sitting down to eat dared to ask him, "Who are you?" For they knew that it was the Lord.

13 And Jesus approached, and he took bread, and he gave it to them, and similarly with the fish.

14 This was now the third time that Jesus was manifested to his disciples, after he had resurrected from the dead.

15 Then, when they had dined, Jesus said to Simon Peter, "Simon, son of John, do you love me more than these?" He said to him, "Yes, Lord, you know that I love you." He said to him, "Feed my lambs."

16 He said to him again: "Simon, son of John, do you love me?" He said to him, "Yes, Lord, you know that I love you." He said to him, "Feed my lambs."

17 He said to him a third time, "Simon, son of John, do you love me?" Peter was very grieved that he had asked him a third time, "Do you love me?" And so he said to him: "Lord, you know all things. You know that I love you." He said to him, "Feed my sheep.

18 Amen, amen, I say to you, when you were younger, you girded yourself and walked wherever you wanted. But when you are older, you will extend your hands, and another shall gird you and lead you where you do not want to go."

19 Now he said this to signify by what kind of death he would glorify God. And when he had said this, he said to him, "Follow me."

20 Peter, turning around, saw the disciple whom Jesus loved following, the one who also had leaned on his chest at supper and said, "Lord, who is it who shall betray you?"

21 Therefore, when Peter had seen him, he said to Jesus, "Lord, but what about this one?"

22 Jesus said to him: "If I want him to remain until I return, what is that to you? You follow me."

23 Therefore, the saying went out among the brothers that this disciple would not die. But Jesus did not say to him that he would not die, but only, "If I want him to remain until I return, what is that to you?"

24 This is the same disciple who offers testimony about these things, and who has written these things. And we know that his testimony is true.

25 Now there are also many other things that Jesus did, which, if each of these were written down, the world itself, I suppose, would not be able to contain the books that would be written.

Acts 1

1 Certainly, O Theophilus, I composed the first discourse about everything that Jesus began to do and to teach,

2 instructing the Apostles, whom he had chosen through the Holy Spirit, even until the day on which he was taken up.

3 He also presented himself alive to them, after his Passion, appearing to them throughout forty days and speaking about the kingdom of God with many elucidations.

4 And dining with them, he instructed them that they should not depart from Jerusalem, but that they should wait for the Promise of the Father, "about which you have heard," he said, "from my own mouth.

5 For John, indeed, baptized with water, but you shall be baptized with the Holy Spirit, not many days from now."

6 Therefore, those who had assembled together questioned him, saying, "Lord, is this the time when you will restore the kingdom of Israel?"

7 But he said to them: "It is not yours to know the times or the moments, which the Father has set by his own authority.

8 But you shall receive the power of the Holy Spirit, passing over you, and you shall be witnesses for me in Jerusalem, and in all Judea and Samaria, and even to the ends of the earth."

9 And when he had said these things, while they were watching, he was lifted up, and a cloud took him from their sight.

10 And while they were watching him going up to heaven, behold, two men stood near them in white vestments.

11 And they said: "Men of Galilee, why do you stand here looking up toward heaven? This Jesus, who has been taken up from you into heaven, shall return in just the same way that you have seen him going up to heaven."

12 Then they returned to Jerusalem from the mountain, which is called Olivet, which is next to Jerusalem, within a Sabbath day's journey.

13 And when they had entered into the cenacle, they ascended to the place where Peter and John, James and Andrew, Philip and Thomas, Bartholomew and Matthew, James of Alphaeus and Simon the Zealot, and Jude of James, were staying.

14 All these were persevering with one accord in prayer with the women, and with Mary, the mother of Jesus, and with his brothers.

15 In those days, Peter, rising up in the midst of the brothers, said (now the crowd of men altogether was about one hundred and twenty):

16 "Noble brothers, the Scripture must be fulfilled, which the Holy Spirit predicted by the mouth of David about Judas, who was the leader of those who apprehended Jesus.

17 He had been numbered among us, and he was chosen by lot for this ministry.

18 And this man certainly possessed an estate from the wages of iniquity, and so, having been hanged, he burst open in the middle and all his internal organs poured out.

19 And this became known to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that this field was called in their language, Akeldama, that is, 'Field of Blood.'

20 For it has been written in the book of Psalms: 'Let their dwelling place be desolate and may there be no one who dwells within it,' and 'Let another take his episcopate.'

21 Therefore, it is necessary that, out of these men who have been assembling with us throughout the entire time that the Lord Jesus went in and out among us,

22 beginning from the baptism of John, until the day when he was taken up from us, one of these be made a witness with us of his Resurrection."

23 And they appointed two: Joseph, who was called Barsabbas, who was surnamed Justus, and Matthias.

24 And praying, they said: "May you, O Lord, who knows the heart of everyone, reveal which one of these two you have chosen,

25 to take a place in this ministry and apostleship, from which Judas prevaricated, so that he might go to his own place."

26 And they cast lots concerning them, and the lot fell upon Matthias. And he was numbered with the eleven Apostles.

Acts 2

1 And when the days of Pentecost were completed, they were all together in the same place.

2 And suddenly, there came a sound from heaven, like that of a wind approaching violently, and it filled the entire house where they were sitting.

3 And there appeared to them separate tongues, as if of fire, which settled upon each one of them.

4 And they were all filled with the Holy Spirit. And they began to speak in various languages, just as the Holy Spirit bestowed eloquence to them.

5 Now there were Jews staying in Jerusalem, pious men from every nation that is under heaven.

6 And when this sound occurred, the multitude came together and was confused in mind, because each one was listening to them speaking in his own language.

7 Then all were astonished, and they wondered, saying: "Behold, are not all of these who are speaking Galileans?

8 And how is it that we have each heard them in our own language, into which we were born?

9 Parthians and Medes and Elamites, and those who inhabit Mesopotamia, Judea and Cappadocia, Pontus and Asia,

10 Phrygia and Pamphylia, Egypt and the parts of Libya which are around Cyrene, and new arrivals of the Romans,

11 likewise Jews and new converts, Cretans and Arabs: we have heard them speaking in our own languages the mighty deeds of God."

12 And they were all astonished, and they wondered, saying to one another: "But what does this mean?"

13 But others mockingly said, "These men are full of new wine."

14 But Peter, standing up with the eleven, lifted up his voice, and he spoke to them: "Men of Judea, and all those who are staying in Jerusalem, let this be known to you, and incline your ears to my words.

15 For these men are not inebriated, as you suppose, for it is the third hour of the day.

16 But this is what was spoken of by the prophet Joel:

17 'And this shall be: in the last days, says the Lord, I will pour out, from my Spirit, upon all flesh. And your sons and your daughters shall prophesy. And your youths shall see visions, and your elders shall dream dreams.

18 And certainly, upon my men and women servants in those days, I will pour out from my Spirit, and they shall prophesy.

19 And I will bestow wonders in heaven above, and signs on earth below: blood and fire and the vapor of smoke.

20 The sun shall be turned into darkness and the moon into blood, before the great and manifest day of the Lord arrives.

21 And this shall be: whoever shall invoke the name of the Lord will be saved.'

22 Men of Israel, hear these words: Jesus the Nazarene is a man confirmed by God among you through the miracles and wonders and signs that God accomplished through him in your midst, just as you also know.

23 This man, under the definitive plan and foreknowledge of God, was delivered by the hands of the unjust, afflicted, and put to death.

24 And he whom God has raised up has broken the sorrows of Hell, for certainly it was impossible for him to be held by it.

25 For David said about him: 'I foresaw the Lord always in my sight, for he is at my right hand, so that I may not be moved.

26 Because of this, my heart has rejoiced, and my tongue has exulted. Moreover, my flesh shall also rest in hope.

27 For you will not abandon my soul to Hell, nor will you allow your Holy One to see corruption.

28 You have made known to me the ways of life. You will completely fill me with happiness by your presence.'

29 Noble brothers, permit me to speak freely to you about the Patriarch David: for he passed away and was buried, and his sepulcher is with us, even to this very day.

30 Therefore, he was a prophet, for he knew that God had sworn an oath to him about the fruit of his loins, about the One who would sit upon his throne.

31 Foreseeing this, he was speaking about the Resurrection of the Christ. For he was neither left behind in Hell, nor did his flesh see corruption.

32 This Jesus, God raised up again, and of this we are all witnesses.

33 Therefore, being exalted to the right hand of God, and having received from the Father the Promise of the Holy Spirit, he poured this out, just as you now see and hear.

34 For David did not ascend into heaven. But he himself said: 'The Lord said to my Lord: Sit at my right hand,

35 until I make your enemies your footstool.'

36 Therefore, may the entire house of Israel know most certainly that God has made this same Jesus, whom you crucified, both Lord and Christ."

37 Now when they had heard these things, they were contrite in heart, and they said to Peter and to the other Apostles: "What should we do, noble brothers?"

38 Yet truly, Peter said to them: "Do penance; and be baptized, each one of you, in the name of Jesus Christ, for the remission of your sins. And you shall receive the gift of the Holy Spirit.

39 For the Promise is for you and for your sons, and for all who are far away: for whomever the Lord our God will have called."

40 And then, with very many other words, he testified and he exhorted them, saying, "Save yourselves from this depraved generation."

41 Therefore, those who accepted his discourse were baptized. And about three thousand souls were added on that day.

42 Now they were persevering in the doctrine of the Apostles, and in the communion of the breaking of the bread, and in the prayers.

43 And fear developed in every soul. Also, many miracles and signs were accomplished by the Apostles in Jerusalem. And there was a great awe in everyone.

44 And then all who believed were together, and they held all things in common.

45 They were selling their possessions and belongings, and dividing them to all, just as any of them had need.

46 Also, they continued, daily, to be of one accord in the temple and to break bread among the houses; and they took their meals with exultation and simplicity of heart,

47 praising God greatly, and holding favor with all the people. And every day, the Lord increased those who were being saved among them.

Acts 3

1 Now Peter and John went up to the temple at the ninth hour of prayer.

2 And a certain man, who was lame from his mother's womb, was being carried in. They would lay him every day at the gate of the temple, which is called the Beautiful, so that he might request alms from those entering into the temple.

3 And this man, when he had seen Peter and John beginning to enter the temple, was begging, so that he might receive alms.

4 Then Peter and John, gazing at him, said, "Look at us."

5 And he looked intently at them, hoping that he might receive something from them.

6 But Peter said: "Silver and gold is not mine. But what I have, I give to you. In the name of Jesus Christ the Nazarene, rise up and walk."

7 And taking him by the right hand, he lifted him up. And immediately his legs and feet were strengthened.

8 And leaping up, he stood and walked around. And he entered with them into the temple, walking and leaping and praising God.

9 And all the people saw him walking and praising God.

10 And they recognized him, that he was the same one who was sitting for alms at the Beautiful Gate of the temple. And they were filled with awe and amazement at what had happened to him.

11 Then, as he held on to Peter and John, all the people ran to them at the portico, which is called Solomon's, in astonishment.

12 But Peter, seeing this, responded to the people: "Men of Israel, why do you wonder at this? Or why do you stare at us, as if it were by our own strength or power that we caused this man to walk?

13 The God of Abraham and the God of Isaac and the God of Jacob, the God of our fathers, has glorified his Son Jesus, whom you, indeed, handed over and denied before the face of Pilate, when he was giving judgment to release him.

14 Then you denied the Holy and Just One, and petitioned for a murderous man to be given to you.

15 Truly, it was the Author of Life whom you put to death, whom God raised from the dead, to whom we are witnesses.

16 And by faith in his name, this man, whom you have seen and known, has confirmed his name. And faith through him has given this man complete health in the sight of you all.

17 And now, brothers, I know that you did this through ignorance, just as your leaders also did.

18 But in this way God has fulfilled the things that he announced beforehand through the mouth of all the Prophets: that his Christ would suffer.

19 Therefore, repent and be converted, so that your sins may be wiped away.

20 And then, when the time of consolation will have arrived from the presence of the Lord, he will send the One who was foretold to you, Jesus Christ,

21 whom heaven certainly must take up, until the time of the restoration of all things, which God has spoken of by the mouth of his holy prophets, from ages past.

22 Indeed, Moses said: 'For the Lord your God shall raise up a Prophet for you from your brothers, one like me; the same shall you listen to according to everything whatsoever that he shall speak to you.

23 And this shall be: every soul who will not listen to that Prophet shall be exterminated from the people.'

24 And all the prophets who have spoken, from Samuel and thereafter, have announced these days.

25 You are sons of the prophets and of the testament which God has appointed for our fathers, saying to Abraham: 'And by your offspring all the families of the earth shall be blessed.'

26 God raised up his Son and sent him first to you, to bless you, so that each one may turn himself away from his wickedness."

Acts 4

1 But while they were speaking to the people, the priests and the magistrate of the temple and the Sadducees overwhelmed them,

2 being grieved that they were teaching the people and announcing in Jesus the resurrection from the dead.

3 And they laid hands on them, and they placed them under guard until the next day. For it was now evening.

4 But many of those who had heard the word believed. And the number of men became five thousand.

5 And it happened on the next day that their leaders and elders and scribes gathered together in Jerusalem,

6 including Annas, the high priest, and Caiaphas, and John and Alexander, and as many as were of the priestly family.

7 And stationing them in the middle, they questioned them: "By what power, or in whose name, have you done this?"

8 Then Peter, filled with the Holy Spirit, said to them: "Leaders of the people and elders, listen.

9 If we today are judged by a good deed done to an infirm man, by which he has been made whole,

10 let it be known to all of you and to all of the people of Israel, that in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ the Nazarene, whom you crucified, whom God has raised from the dead, by him, this man stands before you, healthy.

11 He is the stone, which was rejected by you, the builders, which has become the head of the corner.

12 And there is no salvation in any other. For there is no other name under heaven given to men, by which it is necessary for us to be saved."

13 Then, seeing the constancy of Peter and John, having verified that they were men without letters or learning, they wondered. And they recognized that they had been with Jesus.

14 Also, seeing the man who had been cured standing with them, they were unable to say anything to contradict them.

15 But they ordered them to withdraw outside, away from the council, and they conferred among themselves,

16 saying: "What shall we do to these men? For certainly a public sign has been done through them, before all the inhabitants of Jerusalem. It is manifest, and we cannot deny it.

17 But lest it spread further among the people, let us threaten them not to speak anymore in this name to any man."

18 And calling them in, they warned them not to speak or teach at all in the name of Jesus.

19 Yet truly, Peter and John said in response to them: "Judge whether it is just in the sight of God to listen to you, rather than to God.

20 For we are unable to refrain from speaking the things that we have seen and heard."

21 But they, threatening them, sent them away, having not found a way that they might punish them because of the people. For all were glorifying the things that had been done in these events.

22 For the man in whom this sign of a cure had been accomplished was more than forty years old.

23 Then, having been released, they went to their own, and they reported in full what the leaders of the priests and the elders had said to them.

24 And when they had heard it, with one accord, they lifted up their voice to God, and they said: "Lord, you are the One who made heaven and earth, the sea and all that is in them,

25 who, by the Holy Spirit, through the mouth of our father David, your servant, said: 'Why have the Gentiles been seething, and why have the people been pondering nonsense?

26 The kings of the earth have stood up, and the leaders have joined together as one, against the Lord and against his Christ.'

27 For truly Herod and Pontius Pilate, with the Gentiles and the people of Israel, joined together in this city against your holy servant Jesus, whom you anointed

28 to do what your hand and your counsel had decreed would be done.

29 And now, O Lord, look upon their threats, and grant to your servants that they may speak your word with all confidence,

30 by extending your hand in cures and signs and miracles, to be done through the name of your holy Son, Jesus."

31 And when they had prayed, the place in which they were gathered was moved. And they were all filled with the Holy Spirit. And they were speaking the Word of God with confidence.

32 Then the multitude of believers were of one heart and one soul. Neither did anyone say that any of the things that he possessed were his own, but all things were common to them.

33 And with great power, the Apostles were rendering testimony to the Resurrection of Jesus Christ our Lord. And great grace was in them all.

34 And neither was anyone among them in need. For as many as were owners of fields or houses, selling these, were bringing the proceeds of the things that they were selling,

35 and were placing it before the feet of the Apostles. Then it was divided to each one, just as he had need.

36 Now Joseph, who the Apostles surnamed Barnabas (which is translated as 'son of consolation'), who was a Levite of Cyprian descent,

37 since he had land, he sold it, and he brought the proceeds and placed these at the feet of the Apostles.

Acts 5

1 But a certain man named Ananias, with his wife Sapphira, sold a field,

2 and he was deceitful about the price of the field, with his wife's consent. And bringing only part of it, he placed it at the feet of the Apostles.

3 But Peter said: "Ananias, why has Satan tempted your heart, so that you would lie to the Holy Spirit and be deceitful about the price of the land?

4 Did it not belong to you while you retained it? And having sold it, was it not in your power? Why have you set this thing in your heart? You have not lied to men, but to God!"

5 Then Ananias, upon hearing these words, fell down and expired. And a great fear overwhelmed all who heard of it.

6 And the young men rose up and removed him; and carrying him out, they buried him.

7 Then about the space of three hours passed, and his wife entered, not knowing what had happened.

8 And Peter said to her, "Tell me, woman, if you sold the field for this amount?" And she said, "Yes, for that amount."

9 And Peter said to her: "Why have you agreed together to test the Spirit of the Lord? Behold, the feet of those who have buried your husband are at the door, and they shall carry you out!"

10 Immediately, she fell down before his feet and expired. Then the young men entered and found her dead. And they carried her out and buried her next to her husband.

11 And a great fear came over the entire Church and over all who heard these things.

12 And through the hands of the Apostles many signs and wonders were accomplished among the people. And they all met with one accord at Solomon's portico.

13 And among the others, no one dared to join himself to them. But the people magnified them.

14 Now the multitude of men and women who believed in the Lord was ever increasing,

15 so much so that they laid the infirm in the streets, placing them on beds and stretchers, so that, as Peter arrived, at least his shadow might fall upon any one of them, and they would be freed from their infirmities.

16 But a multitude also hurried to Jerusalem from the neighboring cities, carrying the sick and those troubled by unclean spirits, who were all healed.

17 Then the high priest and all those who were with him, that is, the heretical sect of the Sadducees, rose up and were filled with jealousy.

18 And they laid hands on the Apostles, and they placed them in the common prison.

19 But in the night, an Angel of the Lord opened the doors of the prison and led them out, saying,

20 "Go and stand in the temple, speaking to the people all these words of life."

21 And when they had heard this, they entered the temple at first light, and they were teaching. Then the high priest, and those who were with him, approached, and they called together the council and all the elders of the sons of Israel. And they sent to the prison to have them brought.

22 But when the attendants had arrived, and, upon opening the prison, had not found them, they returned and reported to them,

23 saying: "We found the prison certainly locked up with all diligence, and the guards standing before the door. But upon opening it, we found no one within."

24 Then, when the magistrate of the temple and the chief priests heard these words, they were uncertain about them, as to what should happen.

25 But someone arrived and reported to them, "Behold, the men whom you placed in prison are in the temple, standing and teaching the people."

26 Then the magistrate, with the attendants, went and brought them without force. For they were afraid of the people, lest they be stoned.

27 And when they had brought them, they stood them before the council. And the high priest questioned them,

28 and said: "We strongly order you not to teach in this name. For behold, you have filled Jerusalem with your doctrine, and you wish to bring the blood of this man upon us."

29 But Peter and the Apostles responded by saying: "It is necessary to obey God, more so than men.

30 The God of our fathers has raised up Jesus, whom you put to death by hanging him on a tree.

31 It is he whom God has exalted at his right hand as Ruler and Savior, so as to offer repentance and the remission of sins to Israel.

32 And we are witnesses of these things, with the Holy Spirit, whom God has given to all who are obedient to him."

33 When they had heard these things, they were deeply wounded, and they were planning to put them to death.

34 But someone in the council, a Pharisee named Gamaliel, a teacher of the law honored by all the people, rose up and ordered the men to be put outside briefly.

35 And he said to them: "Men of Israel, you should be careful in your intentions about these men.

36 For before these days, Theudas stepped forward, asserting himself to be someone, and a number of men, about four hundred, joined with him. But he was killed, and all who believed in him were scattered, and they were reduced to nothing.

37 After this one, Judas the Galilean stepped forward, in the days of the enrollment, and he turned the people toward himself. But he also perished, and all of them, as many as had joined with him, were dispersed.

38 And now therefore, I say to you, withdraw from these men and leave them alone. For if this counsel or work is of men, it will be broken.

39 Yet truly, if it is of God, you will not be able to break it, and perhaps you might be found to have fought against God." And they agreed with him.

40 And calling in the Apostles, having beaten them, they warned them not to speak at all in the name of Jesus. And they dismissed them.

41 And indeed, they went forth from the presence of the council, rejoicing that they were considered worthy to suffer insult on behalf of the name of Jesus.

42 And every day, in the temple and among the houses, they did not cease to teach and to evangelize Christ Jesus.

Acts 6

1 In those days, as the number of disciples was increasing, there occurred a murmuring of the Greeks against the Hebrews, because their widows were treated with disdain in the daily ministration.

2 And so the twelve, calling together the multitude of the disciples, said: "It is not fair for us to leave behind the Word of God to serve at tables also.

3 Therefore, brothers, search among yourselves for seven men of good testimony, filled with the Holy Spirit and with wisdom, whom we may appoint over this work.

4 Yet truly, we will be continually in prayer and in the ministry of the Word."

5 And the plan pleased the entire multitude. And they chose Stephen, a man filled with faith and with the Holy Spirit, and Philip and Prochorus and Nicanor and Timon and Parmenas and Nicolas, a new arrival from Antioch.

6 These they set before the sight of the Apostles, and while praying, they imposed hands on them.

7 And the Word of the Lord was increasing, and the number of disciples in Jerusalem was multiplied exceedingly. And even a large group of the priests were obedient to the faith.

8 Then Stephen, filled with grace and fortitude, wrought great signs and miracles among the people.

9 But certain ones, from the synagogue of the so-called Libertines, and of the Cyrenians, and of the Alexandrians, and of those who were from Cilicia and Asia rose up and were disputing with Stephen.

10 But they were not able to resist the wisdom and the Spirit with which he was speaking.

11 Then they suborned men who were to claim that they had heard him speaking words of blasphemy against Moses and against God.

12 And thus did they stir up the people and the elders and the scribes. And hurrying together, they seized him and brought him to the council.

13 And they set up false witnesses, who said: "This man does not cease to speak words against the holy place and the law.

14 For we have heard him saying that this Jesus the Nazarene will destroy this place and will change the traditions, which Moses handed down to us."

15 And all those who were sitting in the council, gazing at him, saw his face, as if it had become the face of an Angel.

Acts 7

1 Then the high priest said, "Are these things so?"

2 And Stephen said: "Noble brothers and fathers, listen. The God of glory appeared to our father Abraham, when he was in Mesopotamia, before he stayed in Haran.

3 And God said to him, 'Depart from your country and from your kindred, and go into the land that I will show to you.'

4 Then he went away from the land of the Chaldeans, and he lived at Haran. And later, after his father was dead, God brought him into this land, in which you now dwell.

5 And he gave him no inheritance in it, not even the space of one step. But he promised to give it to him as a possession, and to his offspring after him, though he did not have a son.

6 Then God told him that his offspring would be a settler in a foreign land, and that they would subjugate them, and treat them badly, for four hundred years.

7 'And the nation whom they will serve, I will judge,' said the Lord. 'And after these things, they shall depart and shall serve me in this place.'

8 And he gave him the covenant of circumcision. And so he conceived Isaac and circumcised him on the eighth day. And Isaac conceived Jacob, and Jacob, the twelve Patriarchs.

9 And the Patriarchs, being jealous, sold Joseph into Egypt. But God was with him.

10 And he rescued him from all his tribulations. And he gave him grace and wisdom in the sight of Pharaoh, the king of Egypt. And he appointed him as governor over Egypt and over all his house.

11 Then a famine occurred in all of Egypt and Canaan, and a great tribulation. And our fathers did not find food.

12 But when Jacob had heard that there was grain in Egypt, he sent our fathers first.

13 And on the second occasion, Joseph was recognized by his brothers, and his ancestry was made manifest to Pharaoh.

14 Then Joseph sent for and brought his father Jacob, with all his kindred, seventy-five souls.

15 And Jacob descended into Egypt, and he passed away, and so did our fathers.

16 And they crossed over into Shechem, and they were placed in the sepulcher which Abraham bought for a sum of money from the sons of Hamor, the son of Shechem.

17 And when the time of the Promise that God had revealed to Abraham drew near, the people increased and were multiplied in Egypt,

18 even until another king, who did not know Joseph, rose up in Egypt.

19 This one, encompassing our kindred, afflicted our fathers, so that they would expose their infants, lest they be kept alive.

20 In the same time, Moses was born. And he was in the grace of God, and he was nourished for three months in the house of his father.

21 Then, having been abandoned, the daughter of Pharaoh took him in, and she raised him as her own son.

22 And Moses was instructed in all the wisdom of the Egyptians. And he was mighty in his words and in his deeds.

23 But when forty years of age were completed in him, it rose up in his heart that he should visit his brothers, the sons of Israel.

24 And when he had seen a certain one suffering injury, he defended him. And striking the Egyptian, he wrought a retribution for him who was enduring the injury.

25 Now he supposed that his brothers would understand that God would grant them salvation through his hand. But they did not understand it.

26 So truly, on the following day, he appeared before those who were arguing, and he would have reconciled them in peace, saying, 'Men, you are brothers. So why would you harm one another?'

27 But he who was causing the injury to his neighbor rejected him, saying: 'Who has appointed you as leader and judge over us?

28 Could it be that you want to kill me, in the same way that you killed the Egyptian yesterday?'

29 Then, at this word, Moses fled. And he became a foreigner in the land of Midian, where he produced two sons.

30 And when forty years were completed, there appeared to him, in the desert of Mount Sinai, an Angel, in a flame of fire in a bush.

31 And upon seeing this, Moses was amazed at the sight. And as he drew near in order to gaze at it, the voice of the Lord came to him, saying:

32 'I am the God of your fathers: the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob.' And Moses, being made to tremble, did not dare to look.

33 But the Lord said to him: 'Loosen the shoes from your feet. For the place in which you stand is holy ground.

34 Certainly, I have seen the affliction of my people who are in Egypt, and I have heard their groaning. And so, I am coming down to free them. And now, go forth and I will send you into Egypt.'

35 This Moses, whom they rejected by saying, 'Who has appointed you as leader and judge?' is the one God sent to be leader and redeemer, by the hand of the Angel who appeared to him in the bush.

36 This man led them out, accomplishing signs and wonders in the land of Egypt, and at the Red Sea, and in the desert, for forty years.

37 This is Moses, who said to the sons of Israel: 'God will raise up for you a prophet like me from your own brothers. You shall listen to him.'

38 This is he who was in the Church in the wilderness, with the Angel who was speaking to him on Mount Sinai, and with our fathers. It is he who received the words of life to give to us.

39 It is he whom our fathers were not willing to obey. Instead, they rejected him, and in their hearts they turned away toward Egypt,

40 saying to Aaron: 'Make gods for us, which may go before us. For this Moses, who led us away from the land of Egypt, we do not know what has happened to him.'

41 And so they fashioned a calf in those days, and they offered sacrifices to an idol, and they rejoiced in the works of their own hands.

42 Then God turned, and he handed them over, to subservience to the armies of heaven, just as it was written in the Book of the Prophets: 'Did you not offer victims and sacrifices to me for forty years in the desert, O house of Israel?

43 And yet you took up for yourselves the tabernacle of Moloch and the star of your god Rephan, figures which you yourselves formed in order to adore them. And so I will carry you away, beyond Babylon.'

44 The tabernacle of the testimony was with our fathers in the desert, just as God ordained for them, speaking to Moses, so that he would make it according to the form that he had seen.

45 But our fathers, receiving it, also brought it, with Joshua, into the land of the Gentiles, whom God expelled before the face of our fathers, even until the days of David,

46 who found grace before God and who asked that he might obtain a tabernacle for the God of Jacob.

47 But it was Solomon who built a house for him.

48 Yet the Most High does not live in houses built by hands, just as he said through the prophet:

49 'Heaven is my throne, and the earth is my footstool. What kind of house would you build for me? says the Lord. And which is my resting place?

50 Has not my hand made all these things?'

51 Stiff-necked and uncircumcised in heart and ears, you ever resist the Holy Spirit. Just as your fathers did, so also do you do.

52 Which of the Prophets have your fathers not persecuted? And they killed those who foretold the advent of the Just One. And you have now become the betrayers and murderers of him.

53 You received the law by the actions of Angels, and yet you have not kept it."

54 Then, upon hearing these things, they were deeply wounded in their hearts, and they gnashed their teeth at him.

55 But he, being filled with the Holy Spirit, and gazing intently toward heaven, saw the glory of God and Jesus standing at the right hand of God. And he said, "Behold, I see the heavens opened, and the Son of man standing at the right hand of God."

56 Then they, crying out with a loud voice, blocked their ears and, with one accord, rushed violently toward him.

57 And driving him out, beyond the city, they stoned him. And witnesses placed their garments beside the feet of a youth, who was called Saul.

58 And as they were stoning Stephen, he called out and said, "Lord Jesus, receive my spirit."

59 Then, having been brought to his knees, he cried out with a loud voice, saying, "Lord, do not hold this sin against them." And when he had said this, he fell asleep in the Lord. And Saul was consenting to his murder.

Acts 8

1 Now in those days, there occurred a great persecution against the Church at Jerusalem. And they were all dispersed throughout the regions of Judea and Samaria, except the Apostles.

2 But God-fearing men arranged for Stephen's funeral, and they made a great mourning over him.

3 Then Saul was laying waste to the Church by entering throughout the houses, and dragging away men and women, and committing them to prison.

4 Therefore, those who had been dispersed were traveling around, evangelizing the Word of God.

5 Now Philip, descending to a city of Samaria, was preaching Christ to them.

6 And the crowd was listening intently and with one accord to those things which were being said by Philip, and they were watching the signs which he was accomplishing.

7 For many of them had unclean spirits, and, crying out with a loud voice, these departed from them.

8 And many of the paralytics and the lame were cured.

9 Therefore, there was great gladness in that city. Now there was a certain man named Simon, who formerly had been a magician in that city, seducing the people of Samaria, claiming himself to be someone great.

10 And to all those who would listen, from the least even to the greatest, he was saying: "Here is the power of God, which is called great."

11 And they were attentive to him because, for a long time, he had deluded them with his magic.

12 Yet truly, once they had believed Philip, who was evangelizing the kingdom of God, both men and women were baptized in the name of Jesus Christ.

13 Then Simon himself also believed and, when he had been baptized, he adhered to Philip. And now, seeing also the greatest signs and miracles being wrought, he was amazed and stupefied.

14 Now when the Apostles who were in Jerusalem had heard that Samaria had received the Word of God, they sent Peter and John to them.

15 And when they had arrived, they prayed for them, so that they might receive the Holy Spirit.

16 For he had not yet come to any among them, since they were only baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus.

17 Then they laid their hands on them, and they received the Holy Spirit.

18 But when Simon had seen that, by the imposition of the hands of the Apostles, the Holy Spirit was given, he offered them money,

19 saying, "Give this power to me also, so that on whomever I will lay my hands, he may receive the Holy Spirit." But Peter said to him:

20 "Let your money be with you in perdition, for you have supposed that a gift of God might be possessed by money.

21 There is no part or place for you in this matter. For your heart is not upright in the sight of God.

22 And so, repent from this, your wickedness, and beg God, so that perhaps this plan of your heart might be forgiven you.

23 For I perceive you to be in the gall of bitterness and in the bond of iniquity."

24 Then Simon responded by saying, "Pray for me to the Lord, so that nothing of what you have said may happen to me."

25 And indeed, after testifying and speaking the Word of the Lord, they returned to Jerusalem, and they evangelized the many regions of the Samaritans.

26 Now an Angel of the Lord spoke to Philip, saying, "Rise up and go toward the south, to the way which descends from Jerusalem into Gaza, where there is a desert."

27 And rising up, he went. And behold, an Ethiopian man, a eunuch, powerful under Candace, the queen of the Ethiopians, who was over all her treasures, had arrived in Jerusalem to worship.

28 And while returning, he was sitting upon his chariot and reading from the prophet Isaiah.

29 Then the Spirit said to Philip, "Draw near and join yourself to this chariot."

30 And Philip, hurrying, heard him reading from the prophet Isaiah, and he said, "Do you think that you understand what you are reading?"

31 And he said, "But how can I, unless someone will have revealed it to me?" And he asked Philip to climb up and sit with him.

32 Now the place in Scripture that he was reading was this: "Like a sheep he was led to the slaughter. And like a lamb silent before his shearer, so he opened not his mouth.

33 He endured his judgment with humility. Who of his generation shall describe how his life was taken away from the earth?"

34 Then the eunuch responded to Philip, saying: "I beg you, about whom is the prophet saying this? About himself, or about someone else?"

35 Then Philip, opening his mouth and beginning from this Scripture, evangelized Jesus to him.

36 And while they were going along the way, they arrived at a certain water source. And the eunuch said: "There is water. What would prevent me from being baptized?"

37 Then Philip said, "If you believe from your whole heart, it is permitted." And he responded by saying, "I believe the Son of God to be Jesus the Christ."

38 And he ordered the chariot to stand still. And both Philip and the eunuch descended into the water. And he baptized him.

39 And when they had ascended from the water, the Spirit of the Lord took Philip away, and the eunuch did not see him anymore. Then he went on his way, rejoicing.

40 Now Philip was found in Azotus. And continuing on, he evangelized all the cities, until he arrived in Caesarea.

Acts 9

1 Now Saul, still breathing threats and beatings against the disciples of the Lord, went to the high priest,

2 and he petitioned him for letters to the synagogues in Damascus, so that, if he found any men or women belonging to this Way, he could lead them as prisoners to Jerusalem.

3 And as he made the journey, it happened that he was approaching Damascus. And suddenly, a light from heaven shone around him.

4 And falling to the ground, he heard a voice saying to him, "Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me?"

5 And he said, "Who are you, Lord?" And he: "I am Jesus, whom you are persecuting. It is hard for you to kick against the goad."

6 And he, trembling and astonished, said, "Lord, what do you want me to do?"

7 And the Lord said to him, "Rise up and go into the city, and there you will be told what you ought to do." Now the men who were accompanying him were standing stupefied, hearing indeed a voice, but seeing no one.

8 Then Saul rose up from the ground. And upon opening his eyes, he saw nothing. So leading him by the hand, they brought him into Damascus.

9 And in that place, he was without sight for three days, and he neither ate nor drank.

10 Now there was a certain disciple at Damascus, named Ananias. And the Lord said to him in a vision, "Ananias!" And he said, "Here I am, Lord."

11 And the Lord said to him: "Rise up and go into the street that is called Straight, and seek, in the house of Judas, the one named Saul of Tarsus. For behold, he is praying."

12 (And Paul saw a man named Ananias entering and imposing hands upon him, so that he might receive his sight.)

13 But Ananias responded: "Lord, I have heard from many about this man, how much harm he has done to your saints in Jerusalem.

14 And he has authority here from the leaders of the priests to bind all who invoke your name."

15 Then the Lord said to him: "Go, for this one is an instrument chosen by me to convey my name before nations and kings and the sons of Israel.

16 For I will reveal to him how much he must suffer on behalf of my name."

17 And Ananias departed. And he entered the house. And laying his hands upon him, he said: "Brother Saul, the Lord Jesus, he who appeared to you on the way by which you arrived, sent me so that you would receive your sight and be filled with the Holy Spirit."

18 And immediately, it was as if scales had fallen from his eyes, and he received his sight. And rising up, he was baptized.

19 And when he had taken a meal, he was strengthened. Now he was with the disciples who were at Damascus for some days.

20 And he was continuously preaching Jesus in the synagogues: that he is the Son of God.

21 And all who heard him were astonished, and they said, "Is this not the one who, in Jerusalem, was fighting against those invoking this name, and who came here for this: so that he might lead them away to the leaders of the priests?"

22 But Saul was increasing to a greater extent in ability, and so he was confounding the Jews who lived at Damascus, by affirming that he is the Christ.

23 And when many days were completed, the Jews took counsel as one, so that they might put him to death.

24 But their treachery became known to Saul. Now they were also watching the gates, day and night, so that they might put him to death.

25 But the disciples, taking him away by night, sent him over the wall by letting him down in a basket.

26 And when he had arrived in Jerusalem, he attempted to join himself to the disciples. And they were all afraid of him, not believing that he was a disciple.

27 But Barnabas took him aside and led him to the Apostles. And he explained to them how he had seen the Lord, and that he had spoken to him, and how, in Damascus, he had acted faithfully in the name of Jesus.

28 And he was with them, entering and departing Jerusalem, and acting faithfully in the name of the Lord.

29 He also was speaking with the Gentiles and disputing with the Greeks. But they were seeking to kill him.

30 And when the brothers had realized this, they brought him to Caesarea and sent him away to Tarsus.

31 Certainly, the Church had peace throughout all of Judea and Galilee and Samaria, and it was being built up, while walking in the fear of the Lord, and it was being filled with the consolation of the Holy Spirit.

32 Then it happened that Peter, as he traveled around everywhere, came to the saints who were living at Lydda.

33 But he found there a certain man, named Aeneas, who was a paralytic, who had lain in bed for eight years.

34 And Peter said to him: "Aeneas, the Lord Jesus Christ heals you. Rise up and arrange your bed." And immediately he rose up.

35 And all who were living in Lydda and Sharon saw him, and they were converted to the Lord.

36 Now in Joppa there was a certain disciple named Tabitha, which in translation is called Dorcas. She was filled with the good works and almsgiving that she was accomplishing.

37 And it happened that, in those days, she became ill and died. And when they had washed her, they laid her in an upper room.

38 Now since Lydda was close to Joppa, the disciples, upon hearing that Peter was there, sent two men to him, asking him: "Do not be slow in coming to us."

39 Then Peter, rising up, went with them. And when he had arrived, they led him to an upper room. And all the widows were standing around him, weeping and showing him the tunics and garments that Dorcas had made for them.

40 And when they had all been sent outside, Peter, kneeling down, prayed. And turning to the body, he said: "Tabitha, arise." And she opened her eyes and, upon seeing Peter, sat up again.

41 And offering her his hand, he lifted her up. And when he had called in the saints and the widows, he presented her alive.

42 Now this became known throughout all of Joppa. And many believed in the Lord.

43 And it happened that he resided for many days in Joppa, with a certain Simon, a tanner.

Acts 10

1 Now there was a certain man in Caesarea, named Cornelius, a centurion of the cohort which is called Italian,

2 a devout man, fearing God with all his house, giving many alms to the people, and praying to God continually.

3 This man saw in a vision clearly, at about the ninth hour of the day, the Angel of God entering to him and saying to him: "Cornelius!"

4 And he, gazing at him, was seized by fear, and he said, "What is it, lord?" And he said to him: "Your prayers and your almsgiving have ascended as a memorial in the sight of God.

5 And now, send men to Joppa and summon a certain Simon, who is surnamed Peter.

6 This man is a guest with a certain Simon, a tanner, whose house is beside the sea. He will tell you what you must do."

7 And when the Angel who was speaking to him had departed, he called, out of those who were subject to him, two of his household servants and a soldier who feared the Lord.

8 And when he had explained everything to them, he sent them to Joppa.

9 Then, on the following day, while they were making the journey and approaching the city, Peter ascended to the upper rooms, so that he might pray, at about the sixth hour.

10 And since he was hungry, he wanted to enjoy some food. Then, as they were preparing it, an ecstasy of mind fell over him.

11 And he saw heaven opened, and a certain container descending, as if a great linen sheet were let down, by its four corners, from heaven to earth,

12 on which were all four-footed beasts, and the crawling things of the earth and the flying things of the air.

13 And a voice came to him: "Rise up, Peter! Kill and eat."

14 But Peter said: "Far be it from me, lord. For I have never eaten anything common or unclean."

15 And the voice, again a second time to him: "What God has purified, you shall not call common."

16 Now this was done three times. And immediately the container was taken up to heaven.

17 Now while Peter was still hesitant within himself as to what the vision, which he had seen, might mean, behold, the men who had been sent from Cornelius stood at the gate, inquiring about Simon's house.

18 And when they had called out, they asked if Simon, who is surnamed Peter, was a guest in that place.

19 Then, as Peter was thinking about the vision, the Spirit said to him, "Behold, three men seek you.

20 And so, rise up, descend, and go with them, doubting nothing. For I have sent them."

21 Then Peter, descending to the men, said: "Behold, I am the one whom you seek. What is the reason for which you have arrived?"

22 And they said: "Cornelius, a centurion, a just and God-fearing man, who has good testimony from the entire nation of the Jews, received a message from a holy Angel to summon you to his house and to listen to words from you."

23 Therefore, leading them in, he received them as guests. Then, on following the day, rising up, he set out with them. And some of the brothers from Joppa accompanied him.

24 And on the next day, he entered Caesarea. And truly, Cornelius was waiting for them, having called together his family and closest friends.

25 And it happened that, when Peter had entered, Cornelius went to meet him. And falling before his feet, he reverenced.

26 Yet truly, Peter, lifting him up, said: "Rise up, for I also am only a man."

27 And speaking with him, he entered, and he found many who had gathered together.

28 And he said to them: "You know how abominable it would be for a Jewish man to be joined with, or to be added to, a foreign people. But God has revealed to me to call no man common or unclean.

29 Because of this and without doubt, I came when summoned. Therefore, I ask you, for what reason have you summoned me?"

30 And Cornelius said: "It is now the fourth day, to this very hour, since I was praying in my house at the ninth hour, and behold, a man stood before me in a white vestment, and he said:

31 'Cornelius, your prayer has been heard and your almsgiving has been remembered in the sight of God.

32 Therefore, send to Joppa and summon Simon, who is surnamed Peter. This man is a guest in the house of Simon, a tanner, near the sea.'

33 And so, I promptly sent for you. And you have done well in coming here. Therefore, all of us are now present in your sight to hear all the things that were taught to you by the Lord."

34 Then, Peter, opening his mouth, said: "I have concluded in truth that God is not a respecter of persons.

35 But within every nation, whoever fears him and works justice is acceptable to him.

36 God sent the Word to the sons of Israel, announcing the peace through Jesus Christ, for he is the Lord of all.

37 You know that the Word has been made known throughout all Judea. For beginning from Galilee, after the baptism which John preached,

38 Jesus of Nazareth, whom God anointed with the Holy Spirit and with power, traveled around doing good and healing all those oppressed by the devil. For God was with him.

39 And we are witnesses of all that he did in the region of Judea and in Jerusalem, he whom they killed by hanging him on a tree.

40 God raised him up on the third day and permitted him to be made manifest,

41 not to all the people, but to the witnesses preordained by God, to those of us who ate and drank with him after he rose again from the dead.

42 And he instructed us to preach to the people, and to testify that he is the One who was appointed by God to be the judge of the living and of the dead.

43 To him all the Prophets offer testimony that through his name all who believe in him receive the remission of sins."

44 While Peter was still speaking these words, the Holy Spirit fell over all of those who were listening to the Word.

45 And the faithful of the circumcision, who had arrived with Peter, were astonished that the grace of the Holy Spirit was also poured out upon the Gentiles.

46 For they heard them speaking in tongues and magnifying God.

47 Then Peter responded, "How could anyone prohibit water, so that those who have received the Holy Spirit would not be baptized, just as we also have been?"

48 And he ordered them to be baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Then they begged him to remain with them for some days.

Acts 11

1 Now the Apostles and brothers who were in Judea heard that the Gentiles had also received the Word of God.

2 Then, when Peter had gone up to Jerusalem, those who were of the circumcision argued against him,

3 saying, "Why did you enter to uncircumcised men, and why did you eat with them?"

4 And Peter began to explain to them, in an orderly manner, saying:

5 "I was in the city of Joppa praying, and I saw, in an ecstasy of mind, a vision: a certain container descending, like a great linen sheet being let down from heaven by its four corners. And it drew near to me.

6 And looking into it, I considered and saw the four-footed beasts of the earth, and the wild beasts, and the reptiles, and the flying things of the air.

7 Then I also heard a voice saying to me: 'Rise up, Peter. Kill and eat.'

8 But I said: 'Never, lord! For what is common or unclean has never entered into my mouth.'

9 Then the voice responded a second time from heaven, 'What God has cleansed, you shall not call common.'

10 Now this was done three times. And then everything was taken up again into heaven.

11 And behold, immediately there were three men standing near the house where I was, having been sent to me from Caesarea.

12 Then the Spirit told me that I should go with them, doubting nothing. And these six brothers went with me also. And we entered into the house of the man.

13 And he described for us how he had seen an Angel in his house, standing and saying to him: 'Send to Joppa and summon Simon, who is surnamed Peter.

14 And he shall speak to you words, by which you shall be saved with your whole house.'

15 And when I had begun to speak, the Holy Spirit fell upon them, just as upon us also, in the beginning.

16 Then I remembered the words of the Lord, just as he himself said: 'John, indeed, baptized with water, but you shall be baptized with the Holy Spirit.'

17 Therefore, if God gave them the same grace, as also to us, who have believed in the Lord Jesus Christ, who was I, that I would be able to prohibit God?"

18 Having heard these things, they were silent. And they glorified God, saying: "So has God also given to the Gentiles repentance unto life."

19 And some of them, having been dispersed by the persecution that had occurred under Stephen, traveled around, even to Phoenicia and Cyprus and Antioch, speaking the Word to no one, except to Jews only.

20 But some of these men from Cyprus and Cyrene, when they had entered into Antioch, were speaking also to the Greeks, announcing the Lord Jesus.

21 And the hand of the Lord was with them. And a great number believed and were converted to the Lord.

22 Now the news came to the ears of the Church at Jerusalem about these things, and they sent Barnabas as far as Antioch.

23 And when he had arrived there and had seen the grace of God, he was gladdened. And he exhorted them all to continue in the Lord with a resolute heart.

24 For he was a good man, and he was filled with the Holy Spirit and with faith. And a great multitude was added to the Lord.

25 Then Barnabas set out for Tarsus, so that he might seek Saul. And when he had found him, he brought him to Antioch.

26 And they were conversing there in the Church for an entire year. And they taught such a great multitude, that it was at Antioch that the disciples were first known by the name of Christian.

27 Now in these days, prophets from Jerusalem went over to Antioch.

28 And one of them, named Agabus, rising up, signified through the Spirit that there was going to be a great famine over the entire world, which did happen under Claudius.

29 Then the disciples declared, according to what each one possessed, what they would offer to be sent to the brothers living in Judea.

30 And so they did, sending it to the elders by the hands of Barnabas and Saul.

Acts 12

1 Now at the same time, king Herod extended his hand, in order to afflict some from the Church.

2 Then he killed James, the brother of John, with the sword.

3 And seeing that it pleased the Jews, he set out next to apprehend Peter also. Now it was the days of Unleavened Bread.

4 So when he had apprehended him, he sent him into prison, handing him over into the custody of four groups of four soldiers, intending to produce him to the people after the Passover.

5 And so Peter was detained in prison. But prayers were being made without ceasing, by the Church, to God on his behalf.

6 And when Herod was ready to produce him, in that same night, Peter was sleeping between two soldiers, and was bound with two chains. And there were guards in front of the door, guarding the prison.

7 And behold, an Angel of the Lord stood near, and a light shined forth in the cell. And tapping Peter on the side, he awakened him, saying, "Rise up, quickly." And the chains fell from his hands.

8 Then the Angel said to him: "Dress yourself, and put on your boots." And he did so. And he said to him, "Wrap your garment around yourself and follow me."

9 And going out, he followed him. And he did not know this truth: that this was being done by an Angel. For he thought that he was seeing a vision.

10 And passing by the first and second guards, they came to the iron gate which leads into the city; and it opened for them by itself. And departing, they continued on along a certain side street. And suddenly the Angel withdrew from him.

11 And Peter, returning to himself, said: "Now I know, truly, that the Lord sent his Angel, and that he rescued me from the hand of Herod and from all that the people of the Jews were anticipating."

12 And as he was considering this, he arrived at the house of Mary, the mother of John, who was surnamed Mark, where many were gathered and were praying.

13 Then, as he knocked at the door of the gate, a girl went out to answer, whose name was Rhoda.

14 And when she recognized the voice of Peter, out of joy, she did not open the gate, but instead, running in, she reported that Peter stood before the gate.

15 But they said to her, "You are crazy." But she reaffirmed that this was so. Then they were saying, "It is his angel."

16 But Peter was persevering in knocking. And when they had opened, they saw him and were astonished.

17 But motioning to them with his hand to be silent, he explained how the Lord had led him away from prison. And he said, "Inform James and those brothers." And going out, he went away to another place.

18 Then, when daylight came, there was no small commotion among the soldiers, as to what had happened concerning Peter.

19 And when Herod had requested him and did not obtain him, having had the guards interrogated, he ordered them led away. And descending from Judea into Caesarea, he lodged there.

20 Now he was angry with those of Tyre and Sidon. But they came to him with one accord, and, having persuaded Blastus, who was over the bedchamber of the king, they petitioned for peace, because their regions were supplied with food by him.

21 Then, on the appointed day, Herod was clothed in kingly apparel, and he sat in the judgment seat, and he gave a speech to them.

22 Then the people were crying out, "The voice of a god, and not of a man!"

23 And immediately, an Angel of the Lord struck him down, because he had not given honor to God. And having been consumed by worms, he expired.

24 But the word of the Lord was increasing and multiplying.

25 Then Barnabas and Saul, having completed the ministry, returned from Jerusalem, bringing with them John, who was surnamed Mark.

Acts 13

1 Now there were, in the Church at Antioch, prophets and teachers, among whom were Barnabas, and Simon, who was called the Black, and Lucius of Cyrene, and Manahen, who was the foster brother of Herod the tetrarch, and Saul.

2 Now as they were ministering for the Lord and fasting, the Holy Spirit said to them: "Separate Saul and Barnabas for me, for the work for which I have selected them."

3 Then, fasting and praying and imposing their hands upon them, they sent them away.

4 And having been sent by the Holy Spirit, they went to Seleucia. And from there they sailed to Cyprus.

5 And when they had arrived at Salamis, they were preaching the Word of God in the synagogues of the Jews. And they also had John in the ministry.

6 And when they had traveled throughout the entire island, even to Paphos, they found a certain man, a magician, a false prophet, a Jew, whose name was Bar-Jesu.

7 And he was with the proconsul, Sergius Paulus, a prudent man. This man, summoning Barnabas and Saul, wanted to hear the Word of God.

8 But Elymas the magician (for so his name is translated) stood against them, seeking to turn the proconsul away from the Faith.

9 Then Saul, who is also called Paul, having been filled with the Holy Spirit, looked intently at him,

10 and he said: "So full of every deceit and of all falsehoods, son of the devil, enemy of all justice, you never cease to subvert the righteous ways of the Lord!

11 And now, behold, the hand of the Lord is upon you. And you will be blinded, not seeing the sun for a length of time." And immediately a fog and a darkness fell over him. And wandering around, he was seeking someone who might lead him by the hand.

12 Then the proconsul, when he had seen what was done, believed, being in wonder over the doctrine of the Lord.

13 And when Paul and those who were with him had sailed from Paphos, they arrived at Perga in Pamphylia. Then John departed from them and returned to Jerusalem.

14 Yet truly, they, traveling on from Perga, arrived at Antioch in Pisidia. And upon entering the synagogue on the Sabbath day, they sat down.

15 Then, after the reading from the Law and the Prophets, the leaders of the synagogue sent to them, saying: "Noble brothers, if there is in you any word of exhortation to the people, speak."

16 Then Paul, rising up and motioning for silence with his hand, said: "Men of Israel and you who fear God, listen closely.

17 The God of the people of Israel chose our fathers, and exalted the people, when they were settlers in the land of Egypt. And with an exalted arm, he led them away from there.

18 And throughout a time of forty years, he endured their behavior in the desert.

19 And by destroying seven nations in the land of Canaan, he divided their land among them by lot,

20 after about four hundred and fifty years. And after these things, he gave them judges, even until the prophet Samuel.

21 And later on, they petitioned for a king. And God gave them Saul, the son of Kish, a man from the tribe of Benjamin, for forty years.

22 And having removed him, he raised up for them king David. And offering testimony about him, he said, 'I have found David, the son of Jesse, to be a man according to my own heart, who will accomplish all that I will.'

23 From his offspring, according to the Promise, God has brought Jesus the Savior to Israel.

24 John was preaching, before the face of his advent, a baptism of repentance to all the people of Israel.

25 Then, when John completed his course, he was saying: 'I am not the one you consider me to be. For behold, one arrives after me, the shoes of whose feet I am not worthy to loosen.'

26 Noble brothers, sons of the stock of Abraham, and those among you who fear God, it is to you the Word of this salvation has been sent.

27 For those who were living in Jerusalem, and its rulers, heeding neither him, nor the voices of the Prophets that are read on every Sabbath, fulfilled these by judging him.

28 And although they found no case for death against him, they petitioned Pilate, so that they might put him to death.

29 And when they had fulfilled everything that had been written about him, taking him down from the tree, they placed him in a tomb.

30 Yet truly, God raised him up from the dead on the third day.

31 And he was seen for many days by those who went up with him from Galilee to Jerusalem, who even now are his witnesses to the people.

32 And we are announcing to you that the Promise, which was made to our fathers,

33 has been fulfilled by God for our children by raising up Jesus, just as it has been written in the second Psalm also: 'You are my Son. This day I have begotten you.'

34 Now, since he raised him from the dead, so as to no longer return to corruption, he has said this: 'I will give to you the holy things of David, the faithful one.'

35 And also then, in another place, he says: 'You will not allow your Holy One to see corruption.'

36 For David, when he had ministered to his generation in accordance with the will of God, fell asleep, and he was placed next to his fathers, and he saw corruption.

37 Yet truly, he whom God has raised from the dead has not seen corruption.

38 Therefore, let it be known to you, noble brothers, that through him is announced to you remission from sins and from everything by which you were not able to be justified in the law of Moses.

39 In him, all who believe are justified.

40 Therefore, be careful, lest what was said by the Prophets may overwhelm you:

41 'You despisers! Look, and wonder, and be scattered! For I am working a deed in your days, a deed which you would not believe, even if someone were to explain it to you.' "

42 Then, as they were departing, they asked them if, on the following Sabbath, they might speak these words to them.

43 And when the synagogue had been dismissed, many among the Jews and the new worshipers were following Paul and Barnabas. And they, speaking to them, persuaded them to continue in the grace of God.

44 Yet truly, on the following Sabbath, nearly the entire city came together to hear the Word of God.

45 Then the Jews, seeing the crowds, were filled with envy, and they, blaspheming, contradicted the things that were being said by Paul.

46 Then Paul and Barnabas said firmly: "It was necessary to speak the Word of God first to you. But because you reject it, and so judge yourselves unworthy of eternal life, behold, we turn to the Gentiles.

47 For so has the Lord instructed us: 'I have set you as a light to the Gentiles, so that you may bring salvation to the ends of the earth.' "

48 Then the Gentiles, upon hearing this, were gladdened, and they were glorifying the Word of the Lord. And as many as believed were preordained to eternal life.

49 Now the word of the Lord was disseminated throughout the entire region.

50 But the Jews incited some devout and honest women, and the leaders of the city. And they stirred up a persecution against Paul and Barnabas. And they drove them away from their parts.

51 But they, shaking the dust from their feet against them, went on to Iconium.

52 The disciples were likewise filled with gladness and with the Holy Spirit.

Acts 14

1 Now it happened in Iconium that they entered together into the synagogue of the Jews, and they spoke in such a way that a copious multitude of both Jews and Greeks believed.

2 Yet truly, the Jews who were unbelieving had incited and enflamed the souls of the Gentiles against the brothers.

3 And so, they remained for a long time, acting faithfully in the Lord, offering testimony to the Word of his grace, providing signs and wonders done by their hands.

4 Then the multitude of the city was divided. And certainly, some were with the Jews, yet truly others were with the Apostles.

5 Now when an assault had been planned by the Gentiles and the Jews with their leaders, so that they might treat them with contempt and stone them,

6 they, realizing this, fled together to Lystra and Derbe, cities of Lycaonia, and to the entire surrounding region. And they were evangelizing in that place.

7 And a certain man was sitting at Lystra, disabled in his feet, lame from his mother's womb, who had never walked.

8 This man heard Paul speaking. And Paul, gazing at him intently, and perceiving that he had faith, so that he might be healed,

9 said with a loud voice, "Stand upright upon your feet!" And he leaped up and walked around.

10 But when the crowds had seen what Paul had done, they lifted up their voice in the Lycaonian language, saying, "The gods, having taken the likenesses of men, have descended to us!"

11 And they called Barnabas, 'Jupiter,' yet truly they called Paul, 'Mercury,' because he was the lead speaker.

12 Also, the priest of Jupiter, who was outside the city, in front of the gate, bringing in oxen and garlands, was willing to offer sacrifice with the people.

13 And as soon as the Apostles, Barnabas and Paul, had heard this, tearing their tunics, they leapt into the crowd, crying out

14 and saying: "Men, why would you do this? We also are mortals, men like yourselves, preaching to you to be converted, from these vain things, to the living God, who made heaven and earth and the sea and all that is in them.

15 In previous generations, he permitted all nations to walk in their own ways.

16 But certainly, he did not leave himself without testimony, doing good from heaven, giving rains and fruitful seasons, filling their hearts with food and gladness."

17 And by saying these things, they were barely able to restrain the crowds from immolating to them.

18 Now certain Jews from Antioch and Iconium arrived there. And having persuaded the crowd, they stoned Paul and dragged him outside of the city, thinking him to be dead.

19 But as the disciples were standing around him, he got up and entered the city. And the next day, he set out with Barnabas for Derbe.

20 And when they had evangelized that city, and had taught many, they returned again to Lystra and to Iconium and to Antioch,

21 strengthening the souls of the disciples, and exhorting them that they should remain always in the faith, and that it is necessary for us to enter into the kingdom of God through many tribulations.

22 And when they had established priests for them in each church, and had prayed with fasting, they commended them to the Lord, in whom they believed.

23 And traveling by way of Pisidia, they arrived in Pamphylia.

24 And having spoken the word of the Lord in Perga, they went down into Attalia.

25 And from there, they sailed to Antioch, where they had been commended to the grace of God for the work which they had now accomplished.

26 And when they had arrived and had gathered together the church, they related what great things God had done with them, and how he had opened the door of faith to the Gentiles.

27 And they remained for no small amount of time with the disciples.

Acts 15

1 And certain ones, descending from Judea, were teaching the brothers, "Unless you are circumcised according to the custom of Moses, you cannot be saved."

2 Therefore, when Paul and Barnabas made no small uprising against them, they decided that Paul and Barnabas, and some from the opposing side, should go up to the Apostles and priests in Jerusalem concerning this question.

3 Therefore, being led by the church, they traveled through Phoenicia and Samaria, describing the conversion of the Gentiles. And they caused great joy among all the brothers.

4 And when they had arrived in Jerusalem, they were received by the church and the Apostles and the elders, reporting what great things God had done with them.

5 But some from the sect of the Pharisees, those who were believers, rose up saying, "It is necessary for them to be circumcised and to be instructed to keep the Law of Moses."

6 And the Apostles and elders came together to take care of this matter.

7 And after a great contention had taken place, Peter rose up and said to them: "Noble brothers, you know that, in recent days, God has chosen from among us, by my mouth, Gentiles to hear the word of the Gospel and to believe.

8 And God, who knows hearts, offered testimony, by giving the Holy Spirit to them, just as to us.

9 And he distinguished nothing between us and them, purifying their hearts by faith.

10 Now therefore, why do you tempt God to impose a yoke upon the necks of the disciples, which neither our fathers nor we have been able to bear?

11 But by the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, we believe in order to be saved, in the same manner also as them."

12 Then the entire multitude was silent. And they were listening to Barnabas and Paul, describing what great signs and wonders God had wrought among the Gentiles through them.

13 And after they had been silent, James responded by saying: "Noble brothers, listen to me.

14 Simon has explained in what manner God first visited, so as to take from the Gentiles a people to his name.

15 And the words of the Prophets are in agreement with this, just as it was written:

16 'After these things, I will return, and I will rebuild the tabernacle of David, which has fallen down. And I will rebuild its ruins, and I will raise it up,

17 so that the rest of men may seek the Lord, along with all the nations over whom my name has been invoked, says the Lord, who does these things.'

18 To the Lord, his own work has been known from eternity.

19 Because of this, I judge that those who were converted to God from among the Gentiles are not to be disturbed,

20 but instead that we write to them, that they should keep themselves from the defilement of idols, and from fornication, and from whatever has been suffocated, and from blood.

21 For Moses, from ancient times, has had in each city those who preach him in the synagogues, where he is read on every Sabbath."

22 Then it pleased the Apostles and elders, with the whole Church, to choose men from among them, and to send to Antioch, with Paul and Barnabas, and Judas, who was surnamed Barsabbas, and Silas, preeminent men among the brothers,

23 what was written by their own hands: "The Apostles and elders, brothers, to those who are at Antioch and Syria and Cilicia, brothers from the Gentiles, greetings.

24 Since we have heard that some, going out from among us, have troubled you with words, subverting your souls, to whom we gave no commandment,

25 it pleased us, being assembled as one, to choose men and to send them to you, with our most beloved Barnabas and Paul:

26 men who have handed over their lives on behalf of the name of our Lord Jesus Christ.

27 Therefore, we have sent Judas and Silas, who themselves also will, with the spoken word, reaffirm to you the same things.

28 For it has seemed good to the Holy Spirit and to us to impose no further burden upon you, other than these necessary things:

29 that you abstain from things immolated to idols, and from blood, and from what has been suffocated, and from fornication. You will do well to keep yourselves from these things. Farewell."

30 And so, having been dismissed, they went down to Antioch. And gathering the multitude together, they delivered the epistle.

31 And when they had read it, they were gladdened by this consolation.

32 But Judas and Silas, being also prophets themselves, consoled the brothers with many words, and they were strengthened.

33 Then, after spending some more time there, they were dismissed with peace, by the brothers, to those who had sent them.

34 But it seemed good to Silas to remain there. So Judas alone departed to Jerusalem.

35 And Paul and Barnabas remained at Antioch, with many others, teaching and evangelizing the Word of the Lord.

36 Then, after some days, Paul said to Barnabas, "Let us return to visit the brothers throughout all the cities in which we have preached the Word of the Lord, to see how they are."

37 And Barnabas wanted to take John, who was surnamed Mark, with them also.

38 But Paul was saying that he ought not to be received, since he withdrew from them at Pamphylia, and he had not gone with them in the work.

39 And there occurred a dissension, to such an extent that they departed from one another. And Barnabas, indeed taking Mark, sailed to Cyprus.

40 Yet truly, Paul, choosing Silas, set out, being delivered by the brothers to the grace of God.

41 And he traveled through Syria and Cilicia, confirming the Churches, instructing them to keep the precepts of the Apostles and the elders.

Acts 16

1 Then he arrived at Derbe and Lystra. And behold, a certain disciple named Timothy was there, the son of a faithful Jewish woman, his father a Gentile.

2 The brothers who were at Lystra and Iconium rendered good testimony to him.

3 Paul wanted this man to travel with him, and taking him, he circumcised him, because of the Jews who were in those places. For they all knew that his father was a Gentile.

4 And as they were traveling through the cities, they delivered to them the dogmas to be kept, which were decreed by the Apostles and elders who were at Jerusalem.

5 And certainly, the Churches were being strengthened in faith and were increasing in number every day.

6 Then, while crossing through Phrygia and the region of Galatia, they were prevented by the Holy Spirit from speaking the Word in Asia.

7 But when they had arrived in Mysia, they attempted to go into Bithynia, but the Spirit of Jesus would not permit them.

8 Then, when they had crossed through Mysia, they descended to Troas.

9 And a vision in the night was revealed to Paul of a certain man of Macedonia, standing and pleading with him, and saying: "Cross into Macedonia and help us!"

10 Then, after he saw the vision, immediately we sought to set out for Macedonia, having been assured that God had called us to evangelize to them.

11 And sailing from Troas, taking a direct path, we arrived at Samothrace, and on the following day, at Neapolis,

12 and from there to Philippi, which is the preeminent city in the area of Macedonia, a colony. Now we were in this city some days, conferring together.

13 Then, on the Sabbath day, we were walking outside the gate, beside a river, where there seemed to be a prayer gathering. And sitting down, we were speaking with the women who had assembled.

14 And a certain woman, named Lydia, a seller of purple in the city of Thyatira, a worshiper of God, listened. And the Lord opened her heart to be receptive to what Paul was saying.

15 And when she had been baptized, with her household, she pleaded with us, saying: "If you have judged me to be faithful to the Lord, enter into my house and lodge there." And she convinced us.

16 Then it happened that, as we were going out to prayer, a certain girl, having a spirit of divination, met with us. She was a source of great profit to her masters, through her divining.

17 This girl, following Paul and us, was crying out, saying: "These men are servants of the Most High God! They are announcing to you the way of salvation!"

18 Now she behaved in this way for many days. But Paul, being grieved, turned and said to the spirit, "I command you, in the name of Jesus Christ, to go out from her." And it went away in that same hour.

19 But her masters, seeing that the hope of their profit went away, apprehended Paul and Silas, and they brought them to the rulers at the courthouse.

20 And presenting them to the magistrates, they said: "These men are disturbing our city, since they are Jews.

21 And they are announcing a way which is not lawful for us to accept or to observe, since we are Romans."

22 And the people rushed together against them. And the magistrates, tearing their tunics, ordered them to be beaten with staffs.

23 And when they had inflicted many scourges on them, they cast them into prison, instructing the guard to watch them diligently.

24 And since he had received this kind of order, he cast them into the interior prison cell, and he restricted their feet with stocks.

25 Then, in the middle of the night, Paul and Silas were praying and praising God. And those who were also in custody were listening to them.

26 Yet truly, there was a sudden earthquake, so great that the foundations of the prison were moved. And immediately all the doors were opened, and the bindings of everyone were released.

27 Then the prison guard, having been jarred awake, and seeing the doors of the prison open, drew his sword and intended to kill himself, supposing that the prisoners had fled.

28 But Paul cried out with a loud voice, saying: "Do no harm to yourself, for we are all here!"

29 Then calling for a light, he entered. And trembling, he fell before the feet of Paul and Silas.

30 And bringing them outside, he said, "Sirs, what must I do, so that I may be saved?"

31 So they said, "Believe in the Lord Jesus, and then you will be saved, with your household."

32 And they spoke the Word of the Lord to him, along with all those who were in his house.

33 And he, taking them in the same hour of the night, washed their scourges. And he was baptized, and next his entire household.

34 And when he had brought them into his own house, he set a table for them. And he was joyous, with his entire household, believing in God.

35 And when daylight had arrived, the magistrates sent the attendants, saying, "Release those men."

36 But the prison guard reported these words to Paul: "The magistrates have sent to have you released. Now therefore, depart. Go in peace."

37 But Paul said to them: "They have beaten us publicly, though we were not condemned. They have cast men who are Romans into prison. And now they would drive us away secretly? Not so. Instead, let them come forward,

38 and let us drive them away." Then the attendants reported these words to the magistrates. And upon hearing that they were Romans, they were afraid.

39 And arriving, they pleaded with them, and leading them out, they begged them to depart from the city.

40 And they went away from the prison and entered into the house of Lydia. And having seen the brothers, they consoled them, and then they set out.

Acts 17

1 Now when they had walked through Amphipolis and Apollonia, they arrived at Thessalonica, where there was a synagogue of the Jews.

2 Then Paul, according to custom, entered to them. And for three Sabbaths he disputed with them about the Scriptures,

3 interpreting and concluding that it was necessary for the Christ to suffer and to rise again from the dead, and that "this is the Jesus Christ, whom I am announcing to you."

4 And some of them believed and were joined to Paul and Silas, and a great number of these were from the worshipers and the Gentiles, and not a few were noble women.

5 But the Jews, being jealous, and joining with certain evildoers among the common men, caused a disturbance, and they stirred up the city. And taking up a position near the house of Jason, they sought to lead them out to the people.

6 And when they had not found them, they dragged Jason and certain brothers to the rulers of the city, crying out: "For these are the ones who have stirred up the city. And they came here,

7 and Jason has received them. And all these men act contrary to the decrees of Caesar, saying that there is another king, Jesus."

8 And they incited the people. And the rulers of the city, upon hearing these things,

9 and having received an explanation from Jason and the others, released them.

10 Yet truly, the brothers promptly sent Paul and Silas away by night to Beroea. And when they had arrived, they entered the synagogue of the Jews.

11 But these were more noble than those who were at Thessalonica. They received the Word with all enthusiasm, daily examining the Scriptures to see if these things were so.

12 And indeed, many believed among them, as well as not a few among the honorable Gentile men and women.

13 Then, when the Jews of Thessalonica had realized that the Word of God was also preached by Paul at Beroea, they went there also, stirring up and disturbing the multitude.

14 And then the brothers quickly sent Paul away, so that he might travel by sea. But Silas and Timothy remained there.

15 Then those who were leading Paul brought him as far as Athens. And having received an order from him to Silas and Timothy, that they should come to him quickly, they set out.

16 Now while Paul waited for them at Athens, his spirit was stirred up within him, seeing the city given over to idolatry.

17 And so, he was disputing with the Jews in the synagogue, and with the worshipers, and in public places, throughout each day, with whomever was there.

18 Now certain Epicurean and Stoic philosophers were arguing with him. And some were saying, "What does this sower of the Word want to say?" Yet others were saying, "He seems to be an announcer for new demons." For he was announcing to them Jesus and the Resurrection.

19 And apprehending him, they brought him to the Areopagus, saying: "Are we able to know what this new doctrine is, about which you speak?

20 For you bring certain new ideas to our ears. And so we would like to know what these things mean."

21 (Now all the Athenians, and arriving visitors, were occupying themselves with nothing other than speaking or hearing various new ideas.)

22 But Paul, standing in the middle of the Areopagus, said: "Men of Athens, I perceive that in all things you are rather superstitious.

23 For as I was passing by and noticing your idols, I also found an altar, on which was written: TO THE UNKNOWN GOD. Therefore, what you worship in ignorance, this is what I am preaching to you:

24 the God who made the world and all that is in it, the One who is the Lord of heaven and earth, who does not live in temples made with hands.

25 Neither is he served by the hands of men, as if in need of anything, since it is he who gives to all things life and breath and all else.

26 And he has made, out of one, every family of man: to live upon the face of the entire earth, determining the appointed seasons and the limits of their habitation,

27 so as to seek God, if perhaps they may consider him or find him, though he is not far from each one of us.

28 'For in him we live, and move, and exist.' Just as some of your own poets have said. 'For we are also of his family.'

29 Therefore, since we are of the family of God, we must not consider gold or silver or precious stones, or the engravings of art and of the imagination of man, to be a representation of what is Divine.

30 And indeed, God, having looked down to see the ignorance of these times, has now announced to men that everyone everywhere should do penance.

31 For he has appointed a day on which he will judge the world in equity, through the man whom he has appointed, offering faith to all, by raising him from the dead."

32 And when they had heard about the Resurrection of the dead, indeed, some were derisive, while others said, "We will listen to you about this again."

33 So Paul departed from their midst.

34 Yet truly, certain men, adhering to him, did believe. Among these were also Dionysius the Areopagite, and a woman named Damaris, and others with them.

Acts 18

1 After these things, having departed from Athens, he arrived at Corinth.

2 And upon finding a certain Jew named Aquila, born in Pontus, who had recently arrived from Italy with Priscilla his wife, (because Claudius had ordered all Jews to depart from Rome,) he met with them.

3 And because he was of the same trade, he lodged with them and was working. (Now they were tentmakers by trade.)

4 And he was arguing in the synagogue on every Sabbath, introducing the name of the Lord Jesus. And he was persuading Jews and Greeks.

5 And when Silas and Timothy had arrived from Macedonia, Paul stood firm in the Word, testifying to the Jews that Jesus is the Christ.

6 But since they were contradicting him and blaspheming, he shook out his garments and said to them: "Your blood is on your own heads. I am clean. From now on, I will go to the Gentiles."

7 And moving from that place, he entered into the house of a certain man, named Titus the Just, a worshiper of God, whose house was adjoined to the synagogue.

8 Now Crispus, a leader of the synagogue, believed in the Lord, with his entire house. And many of the Corinthians, upon hearing, believed and were baptized.

9 Then the Lord said to Paul, through a vision in the night: "Do not be afraid. Instead, speak out and do not be silent.

10 For I am with you. And no one will take hold of you, so as to do you harm. For many of the people in this city are with me."

11 Then he settled there for a year and six months, teaching the Word of God among them.

12 But when Gallio was proconsul of Achaia, the Jews rose up with one accord against Paul. And they brought him to the tribunal,

13 saying, "He persuades men to worship God contrary to the law."

14 Then, when Paul was beginning to open his mouth, Gallio said to the Jews: "If this were some matter of injustice, or a wicked deed, O noble Jews, I would support you, as is proper.

15 Yet if truly these are questions about a word and names and your law, you should see to it yourselves. I will not be the judge of such things."

16 And he ordered them from the tribunal.

17 But they, apprehending Sosthenes, a leader of the synagogue, beat him in front of the tribunal. And Gallio showed no concern for these things.

18 Yet truly, Paul, after he had remained for many more days, having said goodbye to the brothers, sailed into Syria, and with him were Priscilla and Aquila. Now he had shaved his head in Cenchreae, for he had made a vow.

19 And he arrived at Ephesus, and he left them behind there. Yet truly, he himself, entering into the synagogue, was disputing with the Jews.

20 Then, although they were asking him to remain for a longer time, he would not agree.

21 Instead, saying goodbye and telling them, "I will return to you again, God willing," he set out from Ephesus.

22 And after going down to Caesarea, he went up to Jerusalem, and he greeted the Church there, and then he descended to Antioch.

23 And having spent some length of time there, he set out, and he walked in order through the region of Galatia and Phrygia, strengthening all the disciples.

24 Now a certain Jew named Apollo, born at Alexandria, an eloquent man who was powerful with the Scriptures, arrived at Ephesus.

25 He was learned in the Way of the Lord. And being fervent in spirit, he was speaking and teaching the things that are of Jesus, but knowing only the baptism of John.

26 And so, he began to act faithfully in the synagogue. And when Priscilla and Aquila had heard him, they took him aside and expounded the Way of the Lord to him more thoroughly.

27 Then, since he wanted to go to Achaia, the brothers wrote an exhortation to the disciples, so that they might accept him. And when he had arrived, he held many discussions with those who had believed.

28 For he was vehemently and publicly reproving the Jews, by revealing through the Scriptures that Jesus is the Christ.

Acts 19

1 Now it happened that, while Apollo was at Corinth, Paul, after he had journeyed through the upper regions, arrived at Ephesus. And he met with certain disciples.

2 And he said to them, "After believing, have you received the Holy Spirit?" But they said to him, "We have not even heard that there is a Holy Spirit."

3 Yet truly, he said, "Then with what have you been baptized?" And they said, "With the baptism of John."

4 Then Paul said: "John baptized the people with the baptism of repentance, saying that they should believe in the One who is to come after him, that is, in Jesus."

5 Upon hearing these things, they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus.

6 And when Paul had imposed his hands on them, the Holy Spirit came over them. And they were speaking in tongues and prophesying.

7 Now the men were about twelve in all.

8 Then, upon entering the synagogue, he was speaking faithfully for three months, disputing and persuading them about the kingdom of God.

9 But when certain ones became hardened and would not believe, cursing the Way of the Lord in the presence of the multitude, Paul, withdrawing from them, separated the disciples, disputing daily in a certain school of Tyrannus.

10 Now this was done throughout two years, so that all who were living in Asia listened to the Word of the Lord, both Jews and Gentiles.

11 And God was accomplishing powerful and uncommon miracles by the hand of Paul,

12 so much so that even when small cloths and wrappings were brought from his body to the sick, the illnesses withdrew from them and the wicked spirits departed.

13 Then, even some of the traveling Jewish exorcists had attempted to invoke the name of the Lord Jesus over those who had evil spirits, saying, "I bind you by oath through Jesus, whom Paul preaches."

14 And there were certain Jews, the seven sons of Sceva, leaders among the priests, who were acting in this way.

15 But a wicked spirit responded by saying to them: "Jesus I know, and Paul I know. But who are you?"

16 And the man, in whom there was a wicked spirit, leaping at them and getting the better of them both, prevailed against them, so that they fled from that house, naked and wounded.

17 And so, this became known to all the Jews and Gentiles who were living at Ephesus. And a fear fell over them all. And the name of the Lord Jesus was magnified.

18 And many believers were arriving, confessing, and announcing their deeds.

19 Then many of those who had followed odd sects brought together their books, and they burned them in the sight of all. And after determining the value of these, they found the price to be fifty thousand denarii.

20 In this way, the Word of God was increasing strongly and was being confirmed.

21 Then, when these things were completed, Paul decided in the Spirit, after crossing through Macedonia and Achaia, to go to Jerusalem, saying, "Then, after I have been there, it is necessary for me to see Rome also."

22 But sending two of those who were ministering to him, Timothy and Erastus, into Macedonia, he himself remained for a time in Asia.

23 Now at that time, there occurred no small disturbance concerning the Way of the Lord.

24 For a certain man named Demetrius, a silversmith making silver shrines for Diana, was providing no small profit to craftsmen.

25 And calling them together, with those who were employed in the same way, he said: "Men, you know that our income is from this craft.

26 And you are seeing and hearing that this man Paul, by persuasion, has turned away a great multitude, not only from Ephesus, but from nearly all of Asia, saying, 'These things are not gods which have been made by hands.'

27 Thus, not only is this, our occupation, in danger of being brought into repudiation, but also the temple of the great Diana will be reputed as nothing! Then even her majesty, whom all of Asia and the world worships, will begin to be destroyed."

28 Upon hearing this, they were filled with anger, and they cried out, saying, "Great is Diana of the Ephesians!"

29 And the city was filled with confusion. And having seized Gaius and Aristarchus of Macedonia, companions of Paul, they rushed violently, with one accord, into the amphitheatre.

30 Then, when Paul wanted to enter to the people, the disciples would not permit him.

31 And some of the leaders from Asia, who were his friends, also sent to him, requesting that he not present himself in the amphitheatre.

32 But others were crying out various things. For the assembly was in confusion, and most did not know the reason they had been called together.

33 So they dragged Alexander from the crowd, while the Jews were propelling him forward. And Alexander, gesturing with his hand for silence, wanted to give the people an explanation.

34 But as soon as they realized him to be a Jew, all with one voice, for about two hours, were crying out, "Great is Diana of the Ephesians!"

35 And when the scribe had calmed the crowds, he said: "Men of Ephesus, now what man is there who does not know that the city of the Ephesians is in the service of the great Diana and of the offspring of Jupiter?

36 Therefore, since these things are not able to be contradicted, it is necessary for you to be calm and to do nothing rash.

37 For you have brought forward these men, who are neither sacrilegious nor blasphemers against your goddess.

38 But if Demetrius and the craftsmen who are with him have a case against anyone, they can convene in the courts, and there are proconsuls. Let them accuse one another.

39 But if you would inquire about other things, this can be decided in a lawful assembly.

40 For now we are in peril of being convicted of sedition over today's events, since there is no one guilty (against whom we are able to provide evidence) in this gathering." And when he had said this, he dismissed the assembly.

Acts 20

1 Then, after the tumult ceased, Paul, calling the disciples to himself and exhorting them, said farewell. And he set out, so that he might go into Macedonia.

2 And when he had walked through those areas and had exhorted them with many sermons, he went into Greece.

3 After he had spent three months there, treacheries were planned against him by the Jews, just as he was about to sail into Syria. And having been advised of this, he return through Macedonia.

4 Now those accompanying him were Sopater, the son of Pyrrhus from Beroea; and also the Thessalonians, Aristarchus and Secundus; and Gaius of Derbe, and Timothy; and also Tychicus and Trophimus from Asia.

5 These, after they had gone ahead, waited for us at Troas.

6 Yet truly, we sailed from Philippi, after the days of Unleavened Bread, and in five days we went to them at Troas, where we stayed for seven days.

7 Then, on the first Sabbath, when we had assembled together to break bread, Paul discoursed with them, intending to set out the next day. But he prolonged his sermon into the middle of the night.

8 Now there were plenty of lamps in the upper room, where we were gathered.

9 And a certain adolescent named Eutychus, sitting on the window sill, was being weighed down by a heavy drowsiness (for Paul was preaching at length). Then, as he went to sleep, he fell from the third floor room downward. And when he was lifted up, he was dead.

10 When Paul had gone down to him, he laid himself over him and, embracing him, said, "Do not worry, for his soul is still within him."

11 And so, going up, and breaking bread, and eating, and having spoken well on until daylight, he then set out.

12 Now they had brought the boy in alive, and they were more than a little consoled.

13 Then we climbed aboard the ship and sailed to Assos, where we were to take in Paul. For so he himself had decided, since he was making the journey by land.

14 And when he had joined us at Assos, we took him in, and we went to Mitylene.

15 And sailing from there, on the following day, we arrived opposite Chios. And next we landed at Samos. And on the following day we went to Miletus.

16 For Paul had decided to sail past Ephesus, so that he would not be delayed in Asia. For he was hurrying so that, if it were possible for him, he might observe the day of Pentecost at Jerusalem.

17 Then, sending from Miletus to Ephesus, he called those greater by birth in the church.

18 And when they had come to him and were together, he said to them: "You know that from the first day when I entered into Asia, I have been with you, for the entire time, in this manner:

19 serving the Lord, with all humility and despite the tears and trials which befell me from the treacheries of the Jews,

20 how I held back nothing that was of value, how well I have preached to you, and that I have taught you publicly and throughout the houses,

21 testifying both to Jews and to Gentiles about repentance in God and faith in our Lord Jesus Christ.

22 And now, behold, being obliged in spirit, I am going to Jerusalem, not knowing what will happen to me there,

23 except that the Holy Spirit, throughout every city, has cautioned me, saying that chains and tribulations await me at Jerusalem.

24 But I dread none of these things. Neither do I consider my life to be more precious because it is my own, provided that in some way I may complete my own course and that of the ministry of the Word, which I received from the Lord Jesus, to testify to the Gospel of the grace of God.

25 And now, behold, I know that you will no longer see my face, all of you among whom I have traveled, preaching the kingdom of God.

26 For this reason, I call you as witnesses on this very day: that I am clean from the blood of all.

27 For I have not turned aside in the least from announcing every counsel of God to you.

28 Take care of yourselves and of the entire flock, over which the Holy Spirit has stationed you as Bishops to rule the Church of God, which he has purchased by his own blood.

29 I know that after my departure ravenous wolves will enter among you, not sparing the flock.

30 And from among yourselves, men will rise up, speaking perverse things in order to entice disciples after them.

31 Because of this, be vigilant, retaining in memory that throughout three years I did not cease, night and day, with tears, to admonish each and every one of you.

32 And now, I commend you to God and to the Word of his grace. He has the power to build up, and to give an inheritance to all who are sanctified.

33 I have coveted neither silver and gold, nor apparel,

34 as you yourselves know. For that which was needed by me and by those who are with me, these hands have provided.

35 I have revealed all things to you, because by laboring in this way, it is necessary to support the weak and to remember the words of the Lord Jesus, how he said, 'It is more blessed to give than to receive.' "

36 And when he had said these things, kneeling down, he prayed with all of them.

37 Then a great weeping occurred among them all. And, falling upon the neck of Paul, they kissed him,

38 being grieved most of all over the word which he had said, that they would never see his face again. And they brought him to the ship.

Acts 21

1 And after these things had happened, having reluctantly parted from them, we sailed a direct course, arriving at Cos, and on following the day at Rhodes, and from there to Patara.

2 And when we had found a ship sailing across to Phoenicia, climbing aboard, we set sail.

3 Then, after we had caught sight of Cyprus, keeping it to the left, we sailed on to Syria, and we arrived at Tyre. For the ship was going to unload its cargo there.

4 Then, having found the disciples, we lodged there for seven days. And they were saying to Paul, through the Spirit, that he should not go up to Jerusalem.

5 And when the days were completed, setting out, we went on; and they all accompanied us with their wives and children, until we were outside of the city. And we kneeled down at the shore and prayed.

6 And when we had said farewell to one another, we climbed aboard the ship. And they returned to their own.

7 Yet truly, having completed our journey by boat from Tyre, we descended to Ptolemais. And greeting the brothers, we lodged with them for one day.

8 Then, after setting out the next day, we arrived at Caesarea. And upon entering into the house of Philip the evangelist, who was one of the seven, we stayed with him.

9 Now this man had four daughters, virgins, who were prophesying.

10 And while we were delayed for some days, a certain prophet from Judea, named Agabus, arrived.

11 And he, when he had come to us, took Paul's belt, and binding his own feet and hands, he said: "Thus says the Holy Spirit: The man whose belt this is, the Jews will bind in this way at Jerusalem. And they will deliver him into the hands of the Gentiles."

12 And when we had heard this, both we and those who were from that place begged him not to go up to Jerusalem.

13 Then Paul responded by saying: "What do you accomplish by weeping and afflicting my heart? For I am prepared, not only to be bound, but also to die in Jerusalem, for the name of the Lord Jesus."

14 And since we were not able to persuade him, we quieted, saying: "May the will of the Lord be done."

15 Then, after those days, having made preparations, we ascended to Jerusalem.

16 Now some of the disciples from Caesarea also went with us, bringing with them a certain Cypriot named Mnason, a very old disciple, whose guests we would be.

17 And when we had arrived at Jerusalem, the brothers received us willingly.

18 Then, on the following day, Paul entered with us to James. And all the elders were assembled.

19 And when he had greeted them, he explained each thing that God had accomplished among the Gentiles through his ministry.

20 And they, upon hearing it, magnified God and said to him: "You understand, brother, how many thousands there are among the Jews who have believed, and they are all zealous for the law.

21 Now they have heard about you, that you are teaching those Jews who are among the Gentiles to withdraw from Moses, telling them that they should not circumcise their sons, nor act according to custom.

22 What is next? The multitude ought to be convened. For they will hear that you have arrived.

23 Therefore, do this thing that we ask of you: We have four men, who are under a vow.

24 Take these and sanctify yourself with them, and require them to shave their heads. And then everyone will know that the things that they have heard about you are false, but that you yourself walk in keeping with the law.

25 But, about those Gentiles who have believed, we have written a judgment that they should keep themselves from what has been immolated to idols, and from blood, and from what has been suffocated, and from fornication."

26 Then Paul, taking the men on the next day, was purified with them, and he entered the temple, announcing the process of the days of purification, until an oblation would be offered on behalf of each one of them.

27 But when the seven days were reaching completion, those Jews who were from Asia, when they had seen him in the temple, incited all the people, and they laid hands on him, crying out:

28 "Men of Israel, help! This is the man who is teaching, everyone, everywhere, against the people and the law and this place. Furthermore, he has even brought Gentiles into the temple, and he has violated this holy place."

29 (For they had seen Trophimus, an Ephesian, in the city with him, and they supposed that Paul had brought him into the temple.)

30 And the entire city was stirred up. And it happened that the people ran together. And apprehending Paul, they dragged him outside of the temple. And immediately the doors were closed.

31 Then, as they were seeking to kill him, it was reported to the tribune of the cohort: "All Jerusalem is in confusion."

32 And so, immediately taking soldiers and centurions, he rushed down to them. And when they had seen the tribune and the soldiers, they ceased to strike Paul.

33 Then the tribune, drawing near, apprehended him and ordered that he be bound with two chains. And he was asking who he was and what he had done.

34 Then they were crying out various things within the crowd. And since he could not understand anything clearly because of the noise, he ordered him to be brought into the fortress.

35 And when he had arrived at the stairs, it happened that he was carried up by the soldiers, because of the threat of violence from the people.

36 For the multitude of the people were following and crying out, "Take him away!"

37 And as Paul was beginning to be brought into the fortress, he said to the tribune, "Is it permissible for me to say something to you?" And he said, "You know Greek?

38 So then, are you not that Egyptian who before these days incited a rebellion and led out into the desert four thousand murderous men?"

39 But Paul said to him: "I am a man, indeed a Jew, from Tarsus in Cilicia, a citizen of a well-known city. So I petition you, permit me to speak to the people."

40 And when he had given him permission, Paul, standing on the stairs, motioned with his hand to the people. And when a great silence occurred, he spoke to them in the Hebrew language, saying:

Acts 22

1 "Noble brothers and fathers, listen to the explanation that I now give to you."

2 And when they heard him speaking to them in the Hebrew language, they offered a greater silence.

3 And he said: "I am a Jewish man, born at Tarsus in Cilicia, but raised in this city beside the feet of Gamaliel, taught according to the truth of the law of the fathers, zealous for the law, just as all of you also are to this day.

4 I persecuted this Way, even unto death, binding and delivering into custody both men and women,

5 just as the high priest and all those greater by birth bear witness to me. Having received letters from them to the brothers, I journeyed to Damascus, so that I might lead them bound from there to Jerusalem, so that they might be punished.

6 But it happened that, as I was traveling and was approaching Damascus at midday, suddenly from heaven a great light shone around me.

7 And falling to the ground, I heard a voice saying to me, 'Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me?'

8 And I responded, 'Who are you, Lord?' And he said to me, 'I am Jesus the Nazarene, whom you are persecuting.'

9 And those who were with me, indeed, saw the light, but they did not hear the voice of him who was speaking with me.

10 And I said, 'What should I do, Lord?' Then the Lord said to me: 'Rise up, and go to Damascus. And there, you shall be told all that you must do.'

11 And since I could not see, because of the brightness of that light, I was led by the hand by my companions, and I went to Damascus.

12 Then a certain Ananias, a man in accord with the law, having the testimony of all the Jews who were living there,

13 drawing near to me and standing close by, said to me, 'Brother Saul, see!' And in that same hour, I looked upon him.

14 But he said: 'The God of our fathers has preordained you, so that you would come to know his will and would see the Just One, and would hear the voice from his mouth.

15 For you shall be his witness to all men about those things which you have seen and heard.

16 And now, why do you delay? Rise up, and be baptized, and wash away your sins, by invoking his name.'

17 Then it happened that, when I returned to Jerusalem and was praying in the temple, a mental stupor came over me,

18 and I saw him saying to me: 'Hurry! Depart quickly from Jerusalem! For they will not accept your testimony about me.'

19 And I said: 'Lord, they know that I am beating and enclosing in prison, throughout every synagogue, those who have believed in you.

20 And when the blood of your witness Stephen was poured out, I stood nearby and was consenting, and I watched over the garments of those who put him to death.'

21 And he said to me, 'Go forth. For I am sending you to far away nations.' "

22 Now they were listening to him, until this word, and then they lifted up their voice, saying: "Take this kind away from the earth! For it is not fitting for him to live!"

23 And while they were shouting, and tossing aside their garments, and casting dust into the air,

24 the tribune ordered him to be brought into the fortress, and to be scourged and tortured, in order to discover the reason that they were crying out in this way against him.

25 And when they had tied him with straps, Paul said to the centurion who was standing near him, "Is it lawful for you to scourge a man who is a Roman and has not been condemned?"

26 Upon hearing this, the centurion went to the tribune and reported it to him, saying: "What do you intend to do? For this man is a Roman citizen."

27 And the tribune, approaching, said to him: "Tell me. Are you a Roman?" So he said, "Yes."

28 And the tribune responded, "I obtained this citizenship at great cost." And Paul said, "But I was born to it."

29 Therefore, those who were going to torture him, immediately withdrew from him. The tribune was similarly afraid, after he realized that he was a Roman citizen, for he had bound him.

30 But on the next day, wanting to discover more diligently what the reason was that he was accused by the Jews, he released him, and he ordered the priests to convene, with the entire council. And, producing Paul, he stationed him among them.

Acts 23

1 Then Paul, gazing intently at the council, said, "Noble brothers, I have spoken with all good conscience before God, even to this present day."

2 And the high priest, Ananias, instructed those who were standing nearby to strike him on the mouth.

3 Then Paul said to him: "God shall strike you, you whitewashed wall! For would you sit and judge me according to the law, when, contrary to the law, you order me to be struck?"

4 And those who were standing nearby said, "Are you speaking evil about the high priest of God?"

5 And Paul said: "I did not know, brothers, that he is the high priest. For it is written: 'You shall not speak evil of the leader of your people.' "

6 Now Paul, knowing that one group were Sadducees and the other were Pharisees, exclaimed in the council: "Noble brothers, I am a Pharisee, the son of Pharisees! It is over the hope and resurrection of the dead that I am being judged."

7 And when he had said this, a dissension occurred between the Pharisees and the Sadducees. And the multitude was divided.

8 For the Sadducees claim that there is no resurrection, and neither angels, nor spirits. But the Pharisees confess both of these.

9 Then there occurred a great clamor. And some of the Pharisees, rising up, were fighting, saying: "We find nothing evil in this man. What if a spirit has spoken to him, or an angel?"

10 And since a great dissension had been made, the tribune, fearing that Paul might be torn apart by them, ordered the soldiers to descend and to seize him from their midst, and to bring him into the fortress.

11 Then, on the following night, the Lord stood near him and said: "Be constant. For just as you have testified about me in Jerusalem, so also it is necessary for you to testify at Rome."

12 And when daylight arrived, some of the Jews gathered together and bound themselves with an oath, saying that they would neither eat nor drink until they had killed Paul.

13 Now there were more than forty men who had taken this oath together.

14 And they approached the leaders of the priests, and the elders, and they said: "We have sworn ourselves by an oath, so that we will taste nothing, until we have killed Paul.

15 Therefore, with the council, you should now give notice to the tribune, so that he may bring him to you, as if you intended to determine something else about him. But before he approaches, we have made preparations to put him to death."

16 But when Paul's sister's son had heard of this, about their treachery, he went and entered into the fortress, and he reported it to Paul.

17 And Paul, calling to him one of the centurions, said: "Lead this young man to the tribune. For he has something to tell him."

18 And indeed, he took him and led him to the tribune, and he said, "Paul, the prisoner, asked me to lead this young man to you, since he has something to say to you."

19 Then the tribune, taking him by the hand, withdrew with him by themselves, and he asked him: "What is it that you have to tell me?"

20 Then he said: "The Jews have met to ask you to bring Paul tomorrow to the council, as if they intended to question him about something else.

21 But truly, you should not believe them, for they would ambush him with more than forty men from among them, who have bound themselves by an oath neither to eat, nor to drink, until they have put him to death. And they are now prepared, hoping for an affirmation from you."

22 And then the tribune dismissed the young man, instructing him not to tell anyone that he had made known these things to him.

23 Then, having called two centurions, he said to them: "Prepare two hundred soldiers, so that they may go as far as Caesarea, and seventy horsemen, and two hundred spearmen, for the third hour of the night.

24 And prepare beasts of burden to carry Paul, so that they may lead him safely to Felix, the governor."

25 For he was afraid, lest perhaps the Jews might seize him and kill him, and that afterwards he would be falsely accused, as if he had accepted a bribe. And so he wrote a letter containing the following:

26 "Claudius Lysias, to the most excellent governor, Felix: greetings.

27 This man, having been apprehended by the Jews and being about to be put to death by them, I rescued, overwhelming them with soldiers, since I realized that he is a Roman.

28 And wanting to know the reason that they objected to him, I brought him into their council.

29 And I discovered him to be accused about questions of their law. Yet truly, nothing deserving of death or imprisonment was within the accusation.

30 And when I had been given news of ambushes, which they had prepared against him, I sent him to you, notifying his accusers also, so that they may plead their accusations before you. Farewell."

31 Therefore the soldiers, taking Paul according to their orders, brought him by night to Antipatris.

32 And the next day, sending the horsemen to go with him, they returned to the fortress.

33 And when they had arrived at Caesarea and had delivered the letter to the governor, they also presented Paul before him.

34 And when he had read it and had asked which province he was from, realizing that he was from Cilicia, he said:

35 "I will hear you, when your accusers have arrived." And he ordered him to be kept in the praetorium of Herod.

Acts 24

1 Then, after five days, the high priest Ananias came down with some of the elders and a certain Tertullus, a speaker. And they went to the governor against Paul.

2 And having summoned Paul, Tertullus began to accuse him, saying: "Most excellent Felix, since we have much peace through you, and many things may be corrected by your providence,

3 we acknowledge this, always and everywhere, with acts of thanksgiving for everything.

4 But lest I speak at too great a length, I beg you, by your clemency, to listen to us briefly.

5 We have found this man to be pestilent, to be inciting seditions among all the Jews in the entire world, and to be the author of the sedition of the sect of the Nazarenes.

6 And he has even been attempting to violate the temple. And having apprehended him, we wanted him to be judged according to our law.

7 But Lysias, the tribune, overwhelming us with great violence, snatched him away from our hands,

8 ordering his accusers to come to you. From them, you yourself will be able, by judging about all these things, to understand the reason that we accuse him."

9 And then the Jews interjected, saying that these things were so.

10 Then, since the governor had motioned for him to speak, Paul responded: "Knowing that you have been the judge over this nation for many years, I will give an explanation of myself with an honest soul.

11 For, as you may realize, it has only been twelve days since I went up to worship in Jerusalem.

12 And they did not find me in the temple arguing with anyone, nor causing a rally of the people: neither in the synagogues, nor in the city.

13 And they are not able to prove to you the things about which they now accuse me.

14 But I confess this to you, that according to that sect, which they call a heresy, so do I serve my God and Father, believing all that is written in the Law and the Prophets,

15 having a hope in God, which these others themselves also expect, that there will be a future resurrection of the just and the unjust.

16 And in this, I myself always strive to have a conscience that is lacking in any offence toward God and toward men.

17 Then, after many years, I went to my nation, bringing alms and offerings and vows,

18 through which I obtained purification in the temple: neither with a crowd, nor with a commotion.

19 But certain Jews out of Asia are the ones who should have appeared before you to accuse me, if they have anything against me.

20 Or let these ones here say if they have found in me any iniquity, while standing before the council.

21 For while standing among them, I spoke out solely about this one matter: about the resurrection of the dead. It is about this that I am being judged today by you."

22 Then Felix, after having ascertained much knowledge about this Way, kept them waiting, by saying, "When Lysias the tribune has arrived, I will give you a hearing."

23 And he ordered a centurion to guard him, and to take rest, and not to prohibit any of his own from ministering to him.

24 Then, after some days, Felix, arriving with his wife Drusilla who was a Jew, called for Paul and listened to him about the faith that is in Christ Jesus.

25 And after he discoursed about justice and chastity, and about the future judgment, Felix was trembling, and he responded: "For now, go, but remain under guard. Then, at an opportune time, I will summon you."

26 He was also hoping that money might be given to him by Paul, and because of this, he frequently summoned him and spoke with him.

27 Then, when two years had passed, Felix was succeeded by Portius Festus. And since Felix wanted to show particular favor to the Jews, he left Paul behind as a prisoner.

Acts 25

1 And so, when Festus had arrived in the province, after three days, he ascended to Jerusalem from Caesarea.

2 And the leaders of the priests, and those first among the Jews, went to him against Paul. And they were petitioning him,

3 asking for favor against him, so that he would order him to be led to Jerusalem, where they were maintaining an ambush in order to kill him along the way.

4 But Festus responded that Paul was to be kept in Caesarea, and that he himself would soon go there.

5 "Therefore," he said, "let those among you who are able, descend at the same time, and if there is any guilt in the man, they may accuse him."

6 Then, having stayed among them no more than eight or ten days, he descended to Caesarea. And on the next day, he sat in the judgment seat, and he ordered Paul to be led in.

7 And when he had been brought, the Jews who had come down from Jerusalem stood around him, throwing out many serious accusations, none of which they were able to prove.

8 Paul offered this defense: "Neither against the law of the Jews, nor against the temple, nor against Caesar, have I offended in any matter."

9 But Festus, wanting to show greater favor to the Jews, responded to Paul by saying: "Are you willing to ascend to Jerusalem and to be judged there about these things before me?"

10 But Paul said: "I stand in Caesar's tribunal, which is where I ought to be judged. I have done no harm to the Jews, as you well know.

11 For if I have harmed them, or if I have done anything deserving of death, I do not object to dying. But if there is nothing to these things about which they accuse me, no one is able to deliver me to them. I appeal to Caesar."

12 Then Festus, having spoken with the council, responded: "You have appealed to Caesar, to Caesar you shall go."

13 And when some days had passed, king Agrippa and Bernice descended to Caesarea, to greet Festus.

14 And since they remained there for many days, Festus spoke to the king about Paul, saying: "A certain man was left behind as a prisoner by Felix.

15 When I was at Jerusalem, the leaders of the priests and the elders of the Jews came to me about him, asking for condemnation against him.

16 I answered them that it is not the custom of the Romans to condemn any man, before he who is being accused has been confronted by his accusers and has received the opportunity to defend himself, so as to clear himself of the charges.

17 Therefore, when they had arrived here, without any delay, on the following day, sitting in the judgment seat, I ordered the man to be brought.

18 But when the accusers had stood up, they did not present any accusation about him from which I would suspect evil.

19 Instead, they brought against him certain disputes about their own superstition and about a certain Jesus, who had died, but whom Paul asserted to be alive.

20 Therefore, being in doubt about this kind of question, I asked him if he was willing go to Jerusalem and to be judged there about these things.

21 But since Paul was appealing to be kept for a decision before Augustus, I ordered him to be kept, until I might send him to Caesar."

22 Then Agrippa said to Festus: "I myself also want to hear the man." "Tomorrow," he said, "you shall hear him."

23 And on the next day, when Agrippa and Bernice had arrived with great ostentation and had entered into the auditorium with the tribunes and the principal men of the city, Paul was brought in, at the order of Festus.

24 And Festus said: "King Agrippa, and all who are present together with us, you see this man, about whom all the multitude of the Jews disturbed me at Jerusalem, petitioning and clamoring that he should not be allowed to live any longer.

25 Truly, I have discovered nothing brought forth against him that is worthy of death. But since he himself has appealed to Augustus, it was my judgment to send him.

26 But I have not determined what to write to the emperor about him. Because of this, I have brought him before you all, and especially before you, O king Agrippa, so that, once an inquiry has occurred, I may have something to write.

27 For it seems to me unreasonable to send a prisoner and not to indicate the accusations set against him."

Acts 26

1 Yet truly, Agrippa said to Paul, "It is permitted for you to speak for yourself." Then Paul, extending his hand, began to offer his defense.

2 "I consider myself blessed, O king Agrippa, that I am to give my defense today before you, about everything of which I am accused by the Jews,

3 especially since you know everything that pertains to the Jews, both customs and questions. Because of this, I beg you to listen to me patiently.

4 And certainly, all the Jews know about my life from my youth, which had its beginning among my own people in Jerusalem.

5 They knew me well from the beginning, (if they would be willing to offer testimony) for I lived according to the most determined sect of our religion: as a Pharisee.

6 And now, it is in the hope of the Promise which was made by God to our fathers that I stand subject to judgment.

7 It is the Promise that our twelve tribes, worshiping night and day, hope to see. About this hope, O king, I am accused by the Jews.

8 Why should it be judged so unbelievable with you all that God might raise the dead?

9 And certainly, I myself formerly considered that I ought to act in many ways which are contrary to the name of Jesus the Nazarene.

10 This is also how I acted at Jerusalem. And so, I enclosed many holy persons in prison, having received authority from the leaders of the priests. And when they were to be killed, I brought the sentence.

11 And in every synagogue, frequently while punishing them, I compelled them to blaspheme. And being all the more maddened against them, I persecuted them, even to foreign cities.

12 Thereafter, as I was going to Damascus, with authority and permission from the high priest,

13 at midday, O king, I and those who were also with me, saw along the way a light from heaven shining around me with a splendor greater than that of the sun.

14 And when we had all fallen down to the ground, I heard a voice speaking to me in the Hebrew language: 'Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me? It is hard for you to kick against the goad.'

15 Then I said, 'Who are you, Lord?' And the Lord said, 'I am Jesus, whom you are persecuting.

16 But rise up and stand on your feet. For I appeared to you for this reason: so that I may establish you as a minister and a witness concerning the things that you have seen, and concerning the things that I will show to you:

17 rescuing you from the people and the nations to which I am now sending you,

18 in order to open their eyes, so that they may be converted from darkness to light, and from the power of Satan to God, so that they may receive the remission of sins and a place among the saints, through the faith that is in me.'

19 From then on, O king Agrippa, I was not unbelieving to the heavenly vision.

20 But I preached, first to those who are at Damascus and at Jerusalem, and then to the entire region of Judea, and to the Gentiles, so that they would repent and convert to God, doing the works that are worthy of repentance.

21 It was for this reason that the Jews, having apprehended me when I was in the temple, attempted to kill me.

22 But having been aided by the help of God, even to this day, I stand witnessing to the small and the great, saying nothing beyond what the Prophets and Moses have said would be in the future:

23 that the Christ would suffer, and that he would be the first from the resurrection of the dead, and that he would bring light to the people and to the nations."

24 While he was speaking these things and presenting his defense, Festus said with a loud voice: "Paul, you are insane! Too much studying has turned you to insanity."

25 And Paul said: "I am not insane, most excellent Festus, but rather I am speaking words of truth and sobriety.

26 For the king knows about these things. To him also, I am speaking with constancy. For I think that none of these things are unknown to him. And neither were these things done in a corner.

27 Do you believe the Prophets, O king Agrippa? I know that you believe."

28 Then Agrippa said to Paul, "To some extent, you persuade me to become a Christian."

29 And Paul said, "I hope to God that, both to a small extent and to a great extent, not only you, but also all those who hear me this day will become just as I also am, except for these chains."

30 And the king rose up, and the governor, and Bernice, and those who were sitting with them.

31 And when they had withdrawn, they were speaking among themselves, saying, "This man has done nothing worthy of death, nor of imprisonment."

32 Then Agrippa said to Festus, "This man could have been released, if he had not appealed to Caesar."

Acts 27

1 Then it was decided to send him by ship to Italy, and that Paul, with the others in custody, should be delivered to a centurion named Julius, of the cohort of Augusta.

2 After climbing aboard a ship from Adramyttium, we set sail and began to navigate along the ports of Asia, with Aristarchus, the Macedonian from Thessalonica, joining us.

3 And on the following day, we arrived at Sidon. And Julius, treating Paul humanely, permitted him to go to his friends and to look after himself.

4 And when we had set sail from there, we navigated below Cyprus, because the winds were contrary.

5 And navigating though the sea of Cilicia and Pamphylia, we arrived at Lystra, which is in Lycia.

6 And there the centurion found a ship from Alexandria sailing to Italy, and he transferred us to it.

7 And when we had sailed slowly for many days and had barely arrived opposite Cnidus, for the wind was hindering us, we sailed to Crete, near Salmone.

8 And barely being able to sail past it, we arrived at a certain place, which is called Good Shelter, next to which was the city of Lasea.

9 Then, after much time had passed, and since sailing would no longer be prudent because the Fast Day had now passed, Paul consoled them,

10 and he said to them: "Men, I perceive that the voyage is now in danger of injury and much damage, not only to the cargo and the ship, but also to our own lives."

11 But the centurion put more trust in the captain and the navigator of the ship, than in the things being said by Paul.

12 And since it was not a fitting port in which to winter, the majority opinion was to sail from there, so that somehow they might be able to arrive at Phoenicia, in order to winter there, at a port of Crete, which looks out toward the southwest and northwest.

13 And since the south wind was blowing gently, they thought that they might reach their goal. And after they had set out from Asson, they weighed anchor at Crete.

14 But not long afterward, a violent wind came against them, which is called the Northeast Wind.

15 And once the ship had been caught in it and was not able to strive against the wind, giving over the ship to the winds, we were driven along.

16 Then, being forced along a certain island, which is called the Tail, we were barely able to hold on to the ship's lifeboat.

17 When this was taken up, they used it to assist in securing the ship. For they were afraid that they might run aground. And having lowered the sails, they were being driven along in this way.

18 Then, since we were being tossed about strongly by the tempest, on the following day, they threw the heavy items overboard.

19 And on the third day, with their own hands, they threw the equipment of the ship overboard.

20 Then, when neither sun nor stars appeared for many days, and no end to the storm was imminent, all hope for our safety was now taken away.

21 And after they had fasted for a long time, Paul, standing in their midst, said: "Certainly, men, you should have listened to me and not set out from Crete, so as to cause this injury and loss.

22 And now, let me persuade you to be courageous in soul. For there shall be no loss of life among you, but only of the ship.

23 For an Angel of God, who is assigned to me and whom I serve, stood beside me this night,

24 saying: 'Do not be afraid, Paul! It is necessary for you to stand before Caesar. And behold, God has given to you all those who are sailing with you.'

25 Because of this, men, be courageous in soul. For I trust God that this will happen in the same way that it has been told to me.

26 But it is necessary for us to arrive at a certain island."

27 Then, after the fourteenth night arrived, as we were navigating in the sea of Adria, about the middle of the night, the sailors believed that they saw some portion of the land.

28 And upon dropping a weight, they found a depth of twenty paces. And some distance from there, they found a depth of fifteen paces.

29 Then, fearing that we might happen upon rough places, they cast four anchors out of the stern, and they were hoping for daylight to arrive soon.

30 Yet truly, the sailors were seeking a way to flee from the ship, for they had lowered a lifeboat into the sea, on the pretext that they were attempting to cast anchors from the bow of the ship.

31 So Paul said to the centurion and to the soldiers, "Unless these men remain in the ship, you will not be able to be saved."

32 Then the soldiers cut the ropes to the lifeboat, and they allowed it to fall.

33 And when it began to be light, Paul requested that they all take food, saying: "This is the fourteenth day that you have been waiting and continuing to fast, taking nothing.

34 For this reason, I beg you to accept food for the sake of your health. For not a hair from the head of any of you shall perish."

35 And when he had said these things, taking bread, he gave thanks to God in the sight of them all. And when he had broken it, he began to eat.

36 Then they all became more peaceful in soul. And they also took food.

37 Truly, we were two hundred and seventy-six souls on the ship.

38 And having been nourished with food, they lightened the ship, casting the wheat into the sea.

39 And when day had arrived, they did not recognize the landscape. Yet truly, they caught sight of a certain narrow inlet having a shore, into which they thought it might be possible to force the ship.

40 And when they had taken up the anchors, they committed themselves to the sea, at the same time loosing the restraints of the rudders. And so, raising the mainsail to the gusting wind, they pressed on toward the shore.

41 And when we happened upon a place open to two seas, they ran the ship aground. And indeed, the bow, being immobilized, remained fixed, but truly the stern was broken by the violence of the sea.

42 Then the soldiers were in agreement that they should kill the prisoners, lest anyone, after escaping by swimming, might flee.

43 But the centurion, wanting to save Paul, prohibited it from being done. And he ordered those who were able to swim to jump in first, and to escape, and to get to the land.

44 And as for the others, some they carried on boards, and others on those things that belonged to the ship. And so it happened that every soul escaped to the land.

Acts 28

1 And after we had escaped, we then realized that the island was called Malta. Yet truly, the natives offered us no small amount of humane treatment.

2 For they refreshed us all by kindling a fire, because rain was imminent and because of the cold.

3 But when Paul had gathered together a bundle of twigs, and had placed them on the fire, a viper, which had been drawn to the heat, fastened itself to his hand.

4 And truly, when the natives saw the beast hanging from his hand, they were saying to one another: "Certainly, this man must be a murderer, for though he escaped from the sea, vengeance will not permit him to live."

5 But shaking off the creature into the fire, he indeed suffered no ill effects.

6 But they were supposing that he would soon swell up, and then would suddenly fall down and die. But having waited a long time, and seeing no ill effects in him, they changed their minds and were saying that he was a god.

7 Now among these places were estates owned by the ruler of the island, named Publius. And he, taking us in, showed us kind hospitality for three days.

8 Then it happened that the father of Publius lay ill with a fever and with dysentery. Paul entered to him, and when he had prayed and had laid his hands on him, he saved him.

9 When this had been done, all who had diseases on the island approached and were cured.

10 And then they also presented us with many honors. And when we were ready to set sail, they gave us whatever we needed.

11 And so, after three months, we sailed in a ship from Alexandria, whose name was 'the Castors,' and which had wintered at the island.

12 And when we had arrived at Syracuse, we were delayed there for three days.

13 From there, sailing close to the shore, we arrived at Rhegium. And after one day, with the south wind blowing, we arrived on the second day at Puteoli.

14 There, after locating the brothers, we were asked to remain with them for seven days. And then we went on to Rome.

15 And there, when the brothers had heard of us, they went to meet us as far as the Forum of Appius and the Three Taverns. And when Paul had seen them, giving thanks to God, he took courage.

16 And when we had arrived at Rome, Paul was given permission to stay by himself, with a soldier to guard him.

17 And after the third day, he called together the leaders of the Jews. And when they had convened, he said to them: "Noble brothers, I have done nothing against the people, nor against the customs of the fathers, yet I was delivered as a prisoner from Jerusalem into the hands of the Romans.

18 And after they held a hearing about me, they would have released me, because there was no case for death against me.

19 But with the Jews speaking against me, I was constrained to appeal to Caesar, though it was not as if I had any kind of accusation against my own nation.

20 And so, because of this, I requested to see you and to speak to you. For it is because of the hope of Israel that I am encircled with this chain."

21 But they said to him: "We have not received letters about you from Judea, nor have any of the other new arrivals among the brothers reported or spoken anything evil against you.

22 But we are asking to hear your opinions from you, for concerning this sect, we know that it is being spoken against everywhere."

23 And when they had appointed a day for him, very many persons went to him at his guest quarters. And he discoursed, testifying to the kingdom of God, and persuading them about Jesus, using the law of Moses and the Prophets, from morning until evening.

24 And some believed the things that he was saying, yet others did not believe.

25 And when they could not agree among themselves, they departed, while Paul was speaking this one word: "How well did the Holy Spirit speak to our fathers through the prophet Isaiah,

26 saying: 'Go to this people and say to them: Hearing, you shall hear and not understand, and seeing, you shall see and not perceive.

27 For the heart of this people has grown dull, and they have listened with reluctant ears, and they have closed their eyes tightly, lest perhaps they might see with the eyes, and hear with the ears, and understand with the heart, and so be converted, and I would heal them.'

28 Therefore, let it be known to you, that this salvation of God has been sent to the Gentiles, and they shall listen to it."

29 And when he had said these things, the Jews went away from him, though they still had many questions among themselves.

30 Then he remained for two whole years in his own rented lodgings. And he received all who went in to him,

31 preaching the kingdom of God and teaching the things which are from the Lord Jesus Christ, with all faithfulness, without prohibition.

Romans 1

1 Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ, called as an Apostle, separated for the Gospel of God,

2 which he had promised beforehand, through his Prophets, in the Holy Scriptures,

3 about his Son, who was made for him from the offspring of David according to the flesh,

4 the Son of God, who was predestined in virtue according to the Spirit of sanctification from the resurrection of the dead, our Lord Jesus Christ,

5 through whom we have received grace and Apostleship, for the sake of his name, for the obedience of faith among all the Gentiles,

6 from whom you also have been called by Jesus Christ:

7 To all who are at Rome, the beloved of God, called as saints. Grace to you, and peace, from God our Father and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

8 Certainly, I give thanks to my God, through Jesus Christ, first for all of you, because your faith is being announced throughout the entire world.

9 For God is my witness, whom I serve in my spirit by the Gospel of his Son, that without ceasing I have kept a remembrance of you

10 always in my prayers, pleading that in some way, at some time, I may have a prosperous journey, within the will of God, to come to you.

11 For I long to see you, so that I may impart to you a certain spiritual grace to strengthen you,

12 specifically, to be consoled together with you through that which is mutual: your faith and mine.

13 But I want you to know, brothers, that I have often intended to come to you, (though I have been hindered even to the present time) so that I might obtain some fruit among you also, just as also among the other Gentiles.

14 To the Greeks and to the uncivilized, to the wise and to the foolish, I am in debt.

15 So within me there is a prompting to evangelize to you also who are at Rome.

16 For I am not ashamed of the Gospel. For it is the power of God unto salvation for all believers, the Jew first, and the Greek.

17 For the justice of God is revealed within it, by faith unto faith, just as it was written: "For the just one lives by faith."

18 For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven over every impiety and injustice among those men who fend off the truth of God with injustice.

19 For what is known about God is manifest in them. For God has manifested it to them.

20 For unseen things about him have been made conspicuous, since the creation of the world, being understood by the things that were made; likewise his everlasting virtue and divinity, so much so that they have no excuse.

21 For although they had known God, they did not glorify God, nor give thanks. Instead, they became weakened in their thoughts, and their foolish heart was obscured.

22 For, while proclaiming themselves to be wise, they became foolish.

23 And they exchanged the glory of the incorruptible God for the likeness of an image of corruptible man, and of flying things, and of four-legged beasts, and of serpents.

24 For this reason, God handed them over to the desires of their own heart for impurity, so that they afflicted their own bodies with indignities among themselves.

25 And they exchanged the truth of God for a lie. And they worshipped and served the creature, rather than the Creator, who is blessed for all eternity. Amen.

26 Because of this, God handed them over to shameful passions. For example, their females have exchanged the natural use of the body for a use which is against nature.

27 And similarly, the males also, abandoning the natural use of females, have burned in their desires for one another: males doing with males what is disgraceful, and receiving within themselves the recompense that necessarily results from their error.

28 And since they did not prove to have God by knowledge, God handed them over to a morally depraved way of thinking, so that they might do those things which are not fitting:

29 having been completely filled with all iniquity, malice, fornication, avarice, wickedness; full of envy, murder, contention, deceit, spite, gossiping;

30 slanderous, hateful toward God, abusive, arrogant, self-exalting, devisers of evil, disobedient to parents,

31 foolish, disorderly; without affection, without fidelity, without mercy.

32 And these, though they had known the justice of God, did not understand that those who act in such a manner are deserving of death, and not only those who do these things, but also those who consent to what is done.

Romans 2

1 For this reason, O man, each one of you who judges is inexcusable. For by that which you judge another, you condemn yourself. For you do the same things that you judge.

2 For we know that the judgment of God is in accord with truth against those who do such things.

3 But, O man, when you judge those who do such things as you yourself also do, do you think that you will escape the judgment of God?

4 Or do you despise the riches of his goodness and patience and forbearance? Do you not know that the kindness of God is calling you to repentance?

5 But in accord with your hard and impenitent heart, you store up wrath for yourself, unto the day of wrath and of revelation by the just judgment of God.

6 For he will render to each one according to his works:

7 To those who, in accord with patient good works, seek glory and honor and incorruption, certainly, he will render eternal life.

8 But to those who are contentious and who do not acquiesce to the truth, but instead trust in iniquity, he will render wrath and indignation.

9 Tribulation and anguish are upon every soul of man that works evil: the Jew first, and also the Greek.

10 But glory and honor and peace are for all who do what is good: the Jew first, and also the Greek.

11 For there is no favoritism with God.

12 For whoever had sinned without the law, will perish without the law. And whoever had sinned in the law, will be judged by the law.

13 For it is not the hearers of the law who are just before God, but rather it is the doers of the law who shall be justified.

14 For when the Gentiles, who do not have the law, do by nature those things which are of the law, such persons, not having the law, are a law unto themselves.

15 For they reveal the work of the law written in their hearts, while their conscience renders testimony about them, and their thoughts within themselves also accuse or even defend them,

16 unto the day when God shall judge the hidden things of men, through Jesus Christ, according to my Gospel.

17 But if you are called by name a Jew, and you rest upon the law, and you find glory in God,

18 and you have known his will, and you demonstrate the more useful things, having been instructed by the law:

19 you become confident within yourself that you are a guide to the blind, a light to those who are in darkness,

20 an instructor to the foolish, a teacher to children, because you have a type of knowledge and truth in the law.

21 As a result, you teach others, but you do not teach yourself. You preach that men should not steal, but you yourself steal.

22 You speak against adultery, but you commit adultery. You abominate idols, but you commit sacrilege.

23 You would glory in the law, but through a betrayal of the law you dishonor God.

24 (For because of you the name of God is being blasphemed among the Gentiles, just as it was written.)

25 Certainly, circumcision is beneficial, if you observe the law. But if you are a betrayer of the law, your circumcision becomes uncircumcision.

26 And so, if the uncircumcised keep the justices of the law, shall not this lack of circumcision be counted as circumcision?

27 And that which is by nature uncircumcised, if it fulfills the law, should it not judge you, who by the letter and by circumcision are a betrayer of the law?

28 For a Jew is not he who seems so outwardly. Neither is circumcision that which seems so outwardly, in the flesh.

29 But a Jew is he who is so inwardly. And circumcision of the heart is in the spirit, not in the letter. For its praise is not of men, but of God.

Romans 3

1 So then, what more is the Jew, or what is the usefulness of circumcision?

2 Much in every way: First of all, certainly, because the eloquence of God was entrusted to them.

3 But what if some of them have not believed? Shall their unbelief nullify the faith of God? Let it not be so!

4 For God is truthful, but every man is deceitful; just as it was written: "Therefore, you are justified in your words, and you will prevail when you give judgment."

5 But if even our injustice points to the justice of God, what shall we say? Could God be unfair for inflicting wrath?

6 (I am speaking in human terms.) Let it not be so! Otherwise, how would God judge this world?

7 For if the truth of God has abounded, through my falseness, unto his glory, why should I still be judged as such a sinner?

8 And should we not do evil, so that good may result? For so we have been slandered, and so some have claimed we said; their condemnation is just.

9 What is next? Should we try to excel ahead of them? By no means! For we have accused all Jews and Greeks to be under sin,

10 just as it was written: "There is no one who is just.

11 There is no one who understands. There is no one who seeks God.

12 All have gone astray; together they have become useless. There is no one who does good; there is not even one.

13 Their throat is an open sepulcher. With their tongues, they have been acting deceitfully. The venom of asps is under their lips.

14 Their mouth is full of curses and bitterness.

15 Their feet are swift to shed blood.

16 Grief and unhappiness are in their ways.

17 And the way of peace they have not known.

18 There is no fear of God before their eyes."

19 But we know that whatever the law speaks, it speaks to those who are in the law, so that every mouth may be silenced and the entire world may be subject to God.

20 For in his presence no flesh shall be justified by the works of the law. For knowledge of sin is through the law.

21 But now, without the law, the justice of God, to which the law and the prophets have testified, has been made manifest.

22 And the justice of God, though the faith of Jesus Christ, is in all those and over all those who believe in him. For there is no distinction.

23 For all have sinned and all are in need of the glory of God.

24 We have been justified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus,

25 whom God has offered as a propitiation, through faith in his blood, to reveal his justice for the remission of the former offenses,

26 and by the forbearance of God, to reveal his justice in this time, so that he himself might be both the Just One and the Justifier of anyone who is of the faith of Jesus Christ.

27 So then, where is your self-exaltation? It is excluded. Through what law? That of works? No, but rather through the law of faith.

28 For we judge a man to be justified by faith, without the works of the law.

29 Is God of the Jews only and not also of the Gentiles? On the contrary, of the Gentiles also.

30 For One is the God who justifies circumcision by faith and uncircumcision through faith.

31 Are we then destroying the law through faith? Let it not be so! Instead, we are making the law stand.

Romans 4

1 So then, what shall we say that Abraham had achieved, who is our father according to the flesh?

2 For if Abraham was justified by works, he would have glory, but not with God.

3 For what does Scripture say? "Abram believed God, and it was reputed to him unto justice."

4 But for he who works, wages are not accounted according to grace, but according to debt.

5 Yet truly, for he who does not work, but who believes in him who justifies the impious, his faith is reputed unto justice, according to the purpose of the grace of God.

6 Similarly, David also declares the blessedness of a man, to whom God brings justice without works:

7 "Blessed are they whose iniquities have been forgiven and whose sins have been covered.

8 Blessed is the man to whom the Lord has not imputed sin."

9 Does this blessedness, then, remain only in the circumcised, or is it even in the uncircumcised? For we say that faith was reputed to Abraham unto justice.

10 But then how was it reputed? In circumcision or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision.

11 For he received the sign of circumcision as a symbol of the justice of that faith which exists apart from circumcision, so that he might be the father of all those who believe while uncircumcised, so that it might also be reputed to them unto justice,

12 and he might be the father of circumcision, not only for those who are of circumcision, but even for those who follow the footsteps of that faith which is in the uncircumcision of our father Abraham.

13 For the Promise to Abraham, and to his posterity, that he would inherit the world, was not through the law, but through the justice of faith.

14 For if those who are of the law are the heirs, then faith becomes empty and the Promise is abolished.

15 For the law works unto wrath. And where there is no law, there is no law-breaking.

16 Because of this, it is from faith according to grace that the Promise is ensured for all posterity, not only for those who are of the law, but also for those who are of the faith of Abraham, who is the father of us all before God,

17 in whom he believed, who revives the dead and who calls those things that do not exist into existence. For it is written: "I have established you as the father of many nations."

18 And he believed, with a hope beyond hope, so that he might become the father of many nations, according to what was said to him: "Thus shall your posterity shall be."

19 And he was not weakened in faith, nor did he consider his own body to be dead (though he was then almost one hundred years old), nor the womb of Sarah to be dead.

20 And then, in the Promise of God, he did not hesitate out of distrust, but instead he was strengthened in faith, giving glory to God,

21 knowing most fully that whatever God has promised, he is also able to accomplish.

22 And for this reason, it was reputed to him unto justice.

23 Now this has been written, that it was reputed to him unto justice, not only for his sake,

24 but also for our sake. For the same shall be reputed to us, if we believe in him who raised up our Lord Jesus Christ from the dead,

25 who was handed over because of our offenses, and who rose again for our justification.

Romans 5

1 Therefore, having been justified by faith, let us be at peace with God, through our Lord Jesus Christ.

2 For through him we also have access by faith to this grace, in which we stand firm, and to glory, in the hope of the glory of the sons of God.

3 And not only that, but we also find glory in tribulation, knowing that tribulation exercises patience,

4 and patience leads to proving, yet truly proving leads to hope,

5 but hope is not unfounded, because the love of God is poured forth in our hearts through the Holy Spirit, who has been given to us.

6 Yet why did Christ, while we were still infirm, at the proper time, suffer death for the impious?

7 Now someone might barely be willing to die for the sake of justice, for example, perhaps someone might dare to die for the sake of a good man.

8 But God demonstrates his love for us in that, while we were yet sinners, at the proper time,

9 Christ died for us. Therefore, having been justified now by his blood, all the more so shall we be saved from wrath through him.

10 For if we were reconciled to God through the death of his Son, while we were still enemies, all the more so, having been reconciled, shall we be saved by his life.

11 And not only that, but we also glory in God through our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom we have now received reconciliation.

12 Therefore, just as through one man sin entered into this world, and through sin, death; so also death was transferred to all men, to all who have sinned.

13 For even before the law, sin was in the world, but sin was not imputed while the law did not exist.

14 Yet death reigned from Adam until Moses, even in those who have not sinned, in the likeness of the transgression of Adam, who is a figure of him who was to come.

15 But the gift is not entirely like the offense. For though by the offense of one, many died, yet much more so, by the grace of one man, Jesus Christ, has the grace and gift of God abounded to many.

16 And the sin through one is not entirely like the gift. For certainly, the judgment of one was unto condemnation, but the grace toward many offenses is unto justification.

17 For though, by the one offense, death reigned through one, yet so much more so shall those who receive an abundance of grace, both of the gift and of justice, reign in life through the one Jesus Christ.

18 Therefore, just as through the offense of one, all men fell under condemnation, so also through the justice of one, all men fall under justification unto life.

19 For, just as through the disobedience of one man, many were established as sinners, so also through the obedience of one man, many shall be established as just.

20 Now the law entered in such a way that offenses would abound. But where offenses were abundant, grace was superabundant.

21 So then, just as sin has reigned unto death, so also may grace reign through justice unto eternal life, through Jesus Christ our Lord.

Romans 6

1 So what shall we say? Should we remain in sin, so that grace may abound?

2 Let it not be so! For how can we who have died to sin still live in sin?

3 Do you not know that those of us who have been baptized in Christ Jesus have been baptized into his death?

4 For through baptism we have been buried with him into death, so that, in the manner that Christ rose from the dead, by the glory of the Father, so may we also walk in the newness of life.

5 For if we have been planted together, in the likeness of his death, so shall we also be, in the likeness of his resurrection.

6 For we know this: that our former selves have been crucified together with him, so that the body which is of sin may be destroyed, and moreover, so that we may no longer serve sin.

7 For he who has died has been justified from sin.

8 Now if we have died with Christ, we believe that we shall also live together with Christ.

9 For we know that Christ, in rising up from the dead, can no longer die: death no longer has dominion over him.

10 For in as much as he died for sin, he died once. But in as much as he lives, he lives for God.

11 And so, you should consider yourselves to be certainly dead to sin, and to be living for God in Christ Jesus our Lord.

12 Therefore, let not sin reign in your mortal body, such that you would obey its desires.

13 Nor should you offer the parts of your body as instruments of iniquity for sin. Instead, offer yourselves to God, as if you were living after death, and offer the parts of your body as instruments of justice for God.

14 For sin should not have dominion over you. For you are not under the law, but under grace.

15 What is next? Should we sin because we are not under the law, but under grace? Let it not be so!

16 Do you not know to whom you are offering yourselves as servants under obedience? You are the servants of whomever you obey: whether of sin, unto death, or of obedience, unto justice.

17 But thanks be to God that, though you used to be the servants of sin, now you have been obedient from the heart to the very form of the doctrine into which you have been received.

18 And having been freed from sin, we have become servants of justice.

19 I am speaking in human terms because of the infirmity of your flesh. For just as you offered the parts of your body to serve impurity and iniquity, for the sake of iniquity, so also have you now yielded the parts of your body to serve justice, for the sake of sanctification.

20 For though you were once the servants of sin, you have become the children of justice.

21 But what fruit did you hold at that time, in those things about which you are now ashamed? For the end of those things is death.

22 Yet truly, having been freed now from sin, and having been made servants of God, you hold your fruit in sanctification, and truly its end is eternal life.

23 For the wages of sin is death. But the free gift of God is eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord.

Romans 7

1 Or do you not know, brothers, (now I am speaking to those who know the law) that the law has dominion over a man only so long as he lives?

2 For example, a woman who is subject to a husband is obligated by the law while her husband lives. But when her husband has died, she is released from the law of her husband.

3 Therefore, while her husband lives, if she has been with another man, she should be called an adulteress. But when her husband has died, she is freed from the law of her husband, such that, if she has been with another man, she is not an adulteress.

4 And so, my brothers, you also have become dead to the law, through the body of Christ, so that you may be another one who has risen from the dead, in order that we may bear fruit for God.

5 For when we were in the flesh, the passions of sins, which were under the law, operated within our bodies, so as to bear fruit unto death.

6 But now we have been released from the law of death, by which we were being held, so that now we may serve with a renewed spirit, and not in the old way, by the letter.

7 What should we say next? Is the law sin? Let it not be so! But I do not know sin, except through the law. For example, I would not have known about coveting, unless the law said: "You shall not covet."

8 But sin, receiving an opportunity through the commandment, wrought in me all manner of coveting. For apart from the law, sin was dead.

9 Now I lived for some time apart from the law. But when the commandment had arrived, sin was revived,

10 and I died. And the commandment, which was unto life, was itself found to be unto death for me.

11 For sin, receiving an opportunity through the commandment, seduced me, and, through the law, sin killed me.

12 And so, the law itself is indeed holy, and the commandment is holy and just and good.

13 Then was what is good made into death for me? Let it not be so! But rather sin, in order that it might be known as sin by what is good, wrought death in me; so that sin, through the commandment, might become sinful beyond measure.

14 For we know that the law is spiritual. But I am carnal, having been sold under sin.

15 For I do things that I do not understand. For I do not do the good that I want to do. But the evil that I hate is what I do.

16 So, when I do what I do not want to do, I am in agreement with the law, that the law is good.

17 But I am then acting not according to the law, but according to the sin which lives within me.

18 For I know that what is good does not live within me, that is, within my flesh. For the willingness to do good lies close to me, but the carrying out of that good, I cannot reach.

19 For I do not do the good that I want to do. But instead, I do the evil that I do not want to do.

20 Now if I do what I am not willing to do, it is no longer I who am doing it, but the sin which lives within me.

21 And so, I discover the law, by wanting to do good within myself, though evil lies close beside me.

22 For I am delighted with the law of God, according to the inner man.

23 But I perceive another law within my body, fighting against the law of my mind, and captivating me with the law of sin which is in my body.

24 Unhappy man that I am, who will free me from this body of death?

25 The grace of God, by Jesus Christ our Lord! Therefore, I serve the law of God with my own mind; but with the flesh, the law of sin.

Romans 8

1 Therefore, there is now no condemnation for those who are in Christ Jesus, who are not walking according to the flesh.

2 For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus has freed me from the law of sin and death.

3 For though this was impossible under the law, because it was weakened by the flesh, God sent his own Son in the likeness of sinful flesh and because of sin, in order to condemn sin in the flesh,

4 so that the justification of the law might be fulfilled in us. For we are not walking according to the flesh, but according to the spirit.

5 For those who are in agreement with the flesh are mindful of the things of the flesh. But those who are in agreement with the spirit are mindful of the things of the spirit.

6 For the prudence of the flesh is death. But the prudence of the spirit is life and peace.

7 And the wisdom of the flesh is inimical to God. For it is not subject to the law of God, nor can it be.

8 So those who are in the flesh are not able to please God.

9 And you are not in the flesh, but in the spirit, if it is true that the Spirit of God lives within you. But if anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to him.

10 But if Christ is within you, then the body is indeed dead, concerning sin, but the spirit truly lives, because of justification.

11 But if the Spirit of him who raised up Jesus from the dead lives within you, then he who raised up Jesus Christ from the dead shall also enliven your mortal bodies, by means of his Spirit living within you.

12 Therefore, brothers, we are not debtors to the flesh, so as to live according to the flesh.

13 For if you live according to the flesh, you will die. But if, by the Spirit, you mortify the deeds of the flesh, you shall live.

14 For all those who are led by the Spirit of God are the sons of God.

15 And you have not received, again, a spirit of servitude in fear, but you have received the Spirit of the adoption of sons, in whom we cry out: "Abba, Father!"

16 For the Spirit himself renders testimony to our spirit that we are the sons of God.

17 But if we are sons, then we are also heirs: certainly heirs of God, but also co-heirs with Christ, yet in such a way that, if we suffer with him, we shall also be glorified with him.

18 For I consider that the sufferings of this time are not worthy to be compared with that future glory which shall be revealed in us.

19 For the anticipation of the creature anticipates the revelation of the sons of God.

20 For the creature was made subject to emptiness, not willingly, but for the sake of the One who made it subject, unto hope.

21 For the creature itself shall also be delivered from the servitude of corruption, into the liberty of the glory of the sons of God.

22 For we know that every creature groans inwardly, as if giving birth, even until now;

23 and not only these, but also ourselves, since we hold the first-fruits of the Spirit. For we also groan within ourselves, anticipating our adoption as the sons of God, and the redemption of our body.

24 For we have been saved by hope. But a hope which is seen is not hope. For when a man sees something, why would he hope?

25 But since we hope for what we do not see, we wait with patience.

26 And similarly, the Spirit also helps our weakness. For we do not know how to pray as we ought, but the Spirit himself asks on our behalf with ineffable sighing.

27 And he who examines hearts knows what the Spirit seeks, because he asks on behalf of the saints in accordance with God.

28 And we know that, for those who love God, all things work together unto good, for those who, in accordance with his purpose, are called to be saints.

29 For those whom he foreknew, he also predestinated, in conformity with the image of his Son, so that he might be the Firstborn among many brothers.

30 And those whom he predestinated, he also called. And those whom he called, he also justified. And those whom he justified, he also glorified.

31 So, what should we say about these things? If God is for us, who is against us?

32 He who did not spare even his own Son, but handed him over for the sake of us all, how could he not also, with him, have given us all things?

33 Who will make an accusation against the elect of God? God is the One who justifies;

34 who is the one who condemns? Christ Jesus who has died, and who has indeed also risen again, is at the right hand of God, and even now he intercedes for us.

35 Then who will separate us from the love of Christ? Tribulation? Or anguish? Or famine? Or nakedness? Or peril? Or persecution? Or the sword?

36 For it is as it has been written: "For your sake, we are being put to death all day long. We are being treated like sheep for the slaughter."

37 But in all these things we overcome, because of him who has loved us.

38 For I am certain that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor the present things, nor the future things, nor strength,

39 nor the heights, nor the depths, nor any other created thing, will be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

Romans 9

1 I am speaking the truth in Christ; I am not lying. My conscience offers testimony to me in the Holy Spirit,

2 because the sadness within me is great, and there is a continuous sorrow in my heart.

3 For I was desiring that I myself might be anathemized from Christ, for the sake of my brothers, who are my kinsmen according to the flesh.

4 These are the Israelites, to whom belongs adoption as sons, and the glory and the testament, and the giving and following of the law, and the promises.

5 Theirs are the fathers, and from them, according to the flesh, is the Christ, who is over all things, blessed God, for all eternity. Amen.

6 But it is not that the Word of God has perished. For not all those who are Israelites are of Israel.

7 And not all sons are the offspring of Abraham: "For your offspring will be invoked in Isaac."

8 In other words, those who are the sons of God are not those who are sons of the flesh, but those who are sons of the Promise; these are considered to be the offspring.

9 For the word of promise is this: "I will return at the proper time. And there shall be a son for Sarah."

10 And she was not alone. For Rebecca also, having conceived by Isaac our father, from one act,

11 when the children had not yet been born, and had not yet done anything good or bad (such that the purpose of God might be based on their choice),

12 and not because of deeds, but because of a calling, it was said to her: "The elder shall serve the younger."

13 So also it was written: "I have loved Jacob, but I have hated Esau."

14 What should we say next? Is there unfairness with God? Let it not be so!

15 For to Moses he says: "I will pity whomever I pity. And I will offer mercy to whomever I will pity."

16 Therefore, it is not based on those who choose, nor on those who excel, but on God who takes pity.

17 For Scripture says to the Pharaoh: "I have raised you up for this purpose, so that I may reveal my power by you, and so that my name may be announced to all the earth."

18 Therefore, he takes pity on whomever he wills, and he hardens whomever he wills.

19 And so, you would say to me: "Then why does he still find fault? For who can resist his will?"

20 O man, who are you to question God? How can the thing that has been formed say to the One who formed him: "Why have you made me this way?"

21 And does not the potter have the authority over the clay to make, from the same material, indeed, one vessel unto honor, yet truly another unto disgrace?

22 What if God, wanting to reveal his wrath and to make his power known, endured, with much patience, vessels deserving wrath, fit to be destroyed,

23 so that he might reveal the wealth of his glory, within these vessels of mercy, which he has prepared unto glory?

24 And so it is with those of us whom he has also called, not only from among the Jews, but even from among the Gentiles,

25 just as he says in Hosea: "I will call those who were not my people, 'my people,' and she who was not beloved, 'beloved,' and she who had not obtained mercy, 'one who has obtained mercy.'

26 And this shall be: in the place where it was said to them, 'You are not my people,' there they shall be called the sons of the living God."

27 And Isaiah cried out on behalf of Israel: "When the number of the sons of Israel is like the sand of the sea, a remnant shall be saved.

28 For he shall complete his word, while abbreviating it out of equity. For the Lord shall accomplish a brief word upon the earth."

29 And it is just as Isaiah predicted: "Unless the Lord of hosts had bequeathed offspring, we would have become like Sodom, and we would have been made similar to Gomorrah."

30 What should we say next? That the Gentiles who did not follow justice have attained justice, even the justice that is of faith.

31 Yet truly, Israel, though following the law of justice, has not arrived at the law of justice.

32 Why is this? Because they did not seek it from faith, but as if it were from works. For they stumbled over a stumbling block,

33 just as it was written: "Behold, I am placing a stumbling block in Zion, and a rock of scandal. But whoever believes in him shall not be confounded."

Romans 10

1 Brothers, certainly the will of my heart, and my prayer to God, is for them unto salvation.

2 For I offer testimony to them, that they have a zeal for God, but not according to knowledge.

3 For, being ignorant of the justice of God, and seeking to establish their own justice, they have not subjected themselves to the justice of God.

4 For the end of the law, Christ, is unto justice for all who believe.

5 And Moses wrote, about the justice that is of the law, that the man who will have done justice shall live by justice.

6 But the justice that is of faith speaks in this way: Do not say in your heart: "Who shall ascend into heaven?" (that is, to bring Christ down);

7 "Or who shall descend into the abyss?" (that is, to call back Christ from the dead).

8 But what does Scripture say? "The word is near, in your mouth and in your heart." This is the word of faith, which we are preaching.

9 For if you confess with your mouth the Lord Jesus, and if you believe in your heart that God has raised him up from the dead, you shall be saved.

10 For with the heart, we believe unto justice; but with the mouth, confession is unto salvation.

11 For Scripture says: "All those who believe in him shall not be confounded."

12 For there is no distinction between Jew and Greek. For the same Lord is over all, richly in all who call upon him.

13 For all those who have called upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.

14 Then in what way will those who have not believed in him call upon him? Or in what way will those who have not heard of him believe in him? And in what way will they hear of him without preaching?

15 And truly, in what way will they preach, unless they have been sent, just as it has been written: "How beautiful are the feet of those who evangelize peace, of those who evangelize what is good!"

16 But not all are obedient to the Gospel. For Isaiah says: "Lord, who has believed our report?"

17 Therefore, faith is from hearing, and hearing is through the Word of Christ.

18 But I say: Have they not heard? For certainly: "Their sound has gone forth throughout all the earth, and their words unto the limits of the whole world."

19 But I say: Has Israel not known? First, Moses says: "I will lead you into a rivalry with those who are not a nation; in the midst of a foolish nation, I will send you into wrath."

20 And Isaiah dares to say: "I was discovered by those who were not seeking me. I appeared openly to those who were not asking about me."

21 Then to Israel he says: "All day long I have stretched out my hands to a people who do not believe and who contradict me."

Romans 11

1 Therefore, I say: Has God driven away his people? Let it not be so! For I, too, am an Israelite of the offspring of Abraham, from the tribe of Benjamin.

2 God has not driven away his people, whom he foreknew. And do you not know what Scripture says in Elijah, how he calls upon God against Israel?

3 "Lord, they have slain your Prophets. They have overturned your altars. And I alone remain, and they are seeking my life."

4 But what is the Divine response to him? "I have retained for myself seven thousand men, who have not bent their knees before Baal."

5 Therefore, in the same way, again in this time, there is a remnant that has been saved in accord with the choice of grace.

6 And if it is by grace, then it is not now by works; otherwise grace is no longer free.

7 What is next? What Israel was seeking, he has not obtained. But the elect have obtained it. And truly, these others have been blinded,

8 just as it was written: "God has given them a spirit of reluctance: eyes that do not perceive, and ears that do not hear, even until this very day."

9 And David says: "Let their table become like a snare, and a deception, and a scandal, and a retribution for them.

10 Let their eyes be obscured, so that they may not see, and so that they may bow down their backs always."

11 Therefore, I say: Have they stumbled in such a way that they should fall? Let it not be so! Instead, by their offense, salvation is with the Gentiles, so that they may be a rival to them.

12 Now if their offense is the riches of the world, and if their diminution is the riches of the Gentiles, how much more is their fullness?

13 For I say to you Gentiles: Certainly, as long as I am an Apostle to the Gentiles, I will honor my ministry,

14 in such a way that I might provoke to rivalry those who are my own flesh, and so that I may save some of them.

15 For if their loss is for the reconciliation of the world, what could their return be for, except life out of death?

16 For if the first-fruit has been sanctified, so also has the whole. And if the root is holy, so also are the branches.

17 And if some of the branches are broken, and if you, being a wild olive branch, are grafted on to them, and you become a partaker of the root and of the fatness of the olive tree,

18 do not glorify yourself above the branches. For though you glory, you do not support the root, but the root supports you.

19 Therefore, you would say: The branches were broken off, so that I might be grafted on.

20 Well enough. They were broken off because of unbelief. But you stand on faith. So do not choose to savor what is exalted, but instead be afraid.

21 For if God has not spared the natural branches, perhaps also he might not spare you.

22 So then, notice the goodness and the severity of God. Certainly, toward those who have fallen, there is severity; but toward you, there is the goodness of God, if you remain in goodness. Otherwise, you also will be cut off.

23 Moreover, if they do not remain in unbelief, they will be grafted on. For God is able to graft them on again.

24 So if you have been cut off from the wild olive tree, which is natural to you, and, contrary to nature, you are grafted on to the good olive tree, how much more shall those who are the natural branches be grafted on to their own olive tree?

25 For I do not want you to be ignorant, brothers, of this mystery (lest you seem wise only to yourselves) that a certain blindness has occurred in Israel, until the fullness of the Gentiles has arrived.

26 And in this way, all of Israel may be saved, just as it was written: "From Zion shall arrive he who delivers, and he shall turn impiety away from Jacob.

27 And this will be my covenant for them, when I will take away their sins."

28 Certainly, according to the Gospel, they are enemies for your sake. But according to the election, they are most beloved for the sake of the fathers.

29 For the gifts and the call of God are without regret.

30 And just as you also, in times past, did not believe in God, but now you have obtained mercy because of their unbelief,

31 so also have these now not believed, for your mercy, so that they might obtain mercy also.

32 For God has enclosed everyone in unbelief, so that he may have mercy on everyone.

33 Oh, the depths of the richness of the wisdom and knowledge of God! How incomprehensible are his judgments, and how unsearchable are his ways!

34 For who has known the mind of the Lord? Or who has been his counselor?

35 Or who first gave to him, so that repayment would be owed?

36 For from him, and through him, and in him are all things. To him is glory, for all eternity. Amen.

Romans 12

1 And so, I beg you, brothers, by the mercy of God, that you offer your bodies as a living sacrifice, holy and pleasing to God, with the subservience of your mind.

2 And do not choose to be conformed to this age, but instead choose to be reformed in the newness of your mind, so that you may demonstrate what is the will of God: what is good, and what is well-pleasing, and what is perfect.

3 For I say, through the grace that has been given to me, to all who are among you: Taste no more than it is necessary to taste, but taste unto sobriety and just as God has distributed a share of the faith to each one.

4 For just as, within one body, we have many parts, though all the parts do not have the same role,

5 so also we, being many, are one body in Christ, and each one is a part, the one of the other.

6 And we each have different gifts, according to the grace that has been given to us: whether prophecy, in agreement with the reasonableness of faith;

7 or ministry, in ministering; or he who teaches, in doctrine;

8 he who exhorts, in exhortation; he who gives, in simplicity; he who governs, in solicitude; he who shows mercy, in cheerfulness.

9 Let love be without falseness: hating evil, clinging to what is good,

10 loving one another with fraternal charity, surpassing one another in honor:

11 in solicitude, not lazy; in spirit, fervent; serving the Lord;

12 in hope, rejoicing; in tribulation, enduring; in prayer, ever-willing;

13 in the difficulties of the saints, sharing; in hospitality, attentive.

14 Bless those who are persecuting you: bless, and do not curse.

15 Rejoice with those who are rejoicing. Weep with those who are weeping.

16 Be of the same mind toward one another: not savoring what is exalted, but consenting in humility. Do not choose to seem wise to yourself.

17 Render to no one harm for harm. Provide good things, not only in the sight of God, but also in the sight of all men.

18 If it is possible, in so far as you are able, be at peace with all men.

19 Do not defend yourselves, dearest ones. Instead, step aside from wrath. For it is written: "Vengeance is mine. I shall give retribution, says the Lord."

20 So if an enemy is hungry, feed him; if he is thirsty, give him a drink. For in doing so, you will heap burning coals upon his head.

21 Do not allow evil to prevail, instead prevail over evil by means of goodness.

Romans 13

1 Let every soul be subject to higher authorities. For there is no authority except from God and those who have been ordained by God.

2 And so, whoever resists authority, resists what has been ordained by God. And those who resist are acquiring damnation for themselves.

3 For leaders are not a source of fear to those who work good, but to those who work evil. And would you prefer not to be afraid of authority? Then do what is good, and you shall have praise from them.

4 For he is a minister of God for you unto good. But if you do what is evil, be afraid. For it is not without reason that he carries a sword. For he is a minister of God; an avenger to execute wrath upon whomever does evil.

5 For this reason, it is necessary to be subject, not solely because of wrath, but also because of conscience.

6 Therefore, you must also offer tribute. For they are the ministers of God, serving him in this.

7 Therefore, render to all whatever is owed. Taxes, to whom taxes is due; revenue, to whom revenue is due; fear, to whom fear is due; honor, to whom honor is due.

8 You should owe nothing to anyone, except so as to love one another. For whoever loves his neighbor has fulfilled the law.

9 For example: You shall not commit adultery. You shall not kill. You shall not steal. You shall not speak false testimony. You shall not covet. And if there is any other commandment, it is summed up in this word: You shall love your neighbor as yourself.

10 The love of neighbor does no harm. Therefore, love is the plenitude of the law.

11 And we know the present time, that now is the hour for us to rise up from sleep. For already our salvation is closer than when we first believed.

12 The night has passed, and the day draws near. Therefore, let us cast aside the works of darkness, and be clothed with the armor of light.

13 Let us walk honestly, as in the daylight, not in carousing and drunkenness, not in promiscuity and sexual immorality, not in contention and envy.

14 Instead, be clothed with the Lord Jesus Christ, and make no provision for the flesh in its desires.

Romans 14

1 But accept those who are weak in faith, without disputing about ideas.

2 For one person believes that he may eat all things, but if another is weak, let him eat plants.

3 He who eats should not despise him who does not eat. And he who does not eat should not judge him who eats. For God has accepted him.

4 Who are you to judge the servant of another? He stands or falls by his own Lord. But he shall stand. For God is able to make him stand.

5 For one person discerns one age from the next. But another discerns unto every age. Let each one increase according to his own mind.

6 He who understands the age, understands for the Lord. And he who eats, eats for the Lord; for he gives thanks to God. And he who does not eat, does not eat for the Lord, and he gives thanks to God.

7 For none of us lives for himself, and none of us dies for himself.

8 For if we live, we live for the Lord, and if we die, we die for the Lord. Therefore, whether we live or die, we belong to the Lord.

9 For Christ died and rose again for this purpose: that he might be the ruler of both the dead and the living.

10 So then, why do you judge your brother? Or why do you despise your brother? For we shall all stand before the judgment seat of Christ.

11 For it is written: "As I live, says the Lord, every knee shall bend to me, and every tongue shall confess to God."

12 And so, each one of us shall offer an explanation of himself to God.

13 Therefore, we should no longer judge one another. Instead, judge this to a greater extent: that you should not place an obstacle before your brother, nor lead him astray.

14 I know, with confidence in the Lord Jesus, that nothing is unclean in and of itself. But to him who considers anything to be unclean, it is unclean to him.

15 For if your brother is grieved because of your food, you are not now walking according to love. Do not allow your food to destroy him for whom Christ died.

16 Therefore, what is good for us should not be a cause of blasphemy.

17 For the kingdom of God is not food and drink, but rather justice and peace and joy, in the Holy Spirit.

18 For he who serves Christ in this, pleases God and is proven before men.

19 And so, let us pursue the things that are of peace, and let us keep to the things that are for the edification of one another.

20 Do not be willing to destroy the work of God because of food. Certainly, all things are clean. But there is harm for a man who offends by eating.

21 It is good to refrain from eating meat and from drinking wine, and from anything by which your brother is offended, or led astray, or weakened.

22 Do you have faith? It belongs to you, so hold it before God. Blessed is he who does not judge himself in that by which he is tested.

23 But he who discerns, if he eats, is condemned, because it is not of faith. For all that is not of faith is sin.

Romans 15

1 But we who are stronger must bear with the feebleness of the weak, and not so as to please ourselves.

2 Each one of you should please his neighbor unto good, for edification.

3 For even Christ did not please himself, but as it was written: "The reproaches of those who reproached you fell upon me."

4 For whatever was written, was written to teach us, so that, through patience and the consolation of the Scriptures, we might have hope.

5 So may the God of patience and solace grant you to be of one mind toward one another, in accord with Jesus Christ,

6 so that, together with one mouth, you may glorify the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.

7 For this reason, accept one another, just as Christ also has accepted you, in the honor of God.

8 For I declare that Christ Jesus was the minister of circumcision because of the truth of God, so as to confirm the promises to the fathers,

9 and that the Gentiles are to honor God because of his mercy, just as it was written: "Because of this, I will confess you among the Gentiles, O Lord, and I will sing to your name."

10 And again, he says: "Rejoice, O Gentiles, along with his people."

11 And again: "All Gentiles, praise the Lord; and all peoples, magnify him."

12 And again, Isaiah says: "There shall be a root of Jesse, and he shall rise up to rule the Gentiles, and in him the Gentiles shall hope."

13 So may the God of hope fill you with every joy and with peace in believing, so that you may abound in hope and in the virtue of the Holy Spirit.

14 But I am also certain about you, my brothers, that you also have been filled with love, completed with all knowledge, so that you are able to admonish one another.

15 But I have written to you, brothers, more boldly than to the others, as if calling you to mind again, because of the grace which has been given to me from God,

16 so that I may be a minister of Christ Jesus among the Gentiles, sanctifying the Gospel of God, in order that the oblation of the Gentiles may be made acceptable and may be sanctified in the Holy Spirit.

17 Therefore, I have glory in Christ Jesus before God.

18 So I dare not speak of any of those things which Christ does not effect through me, unto the obedience of the Gentiles, in word and deed,

19 with the power of signs and wonders, by power of the Holy Spirit. For in this way, from Jerusalem, throughout its surroundings, as far as Illyricum, I have replenished the Gospel of Christ.

20 And so I have preached this Gospel, not where Christ was known by name, lest I build upon the foundation of another,

21 but just as it was written: "Those to whom he was not announced shall perceive, and those who have not heard shall understand."

22 Because of this also, I was greatly hindered in coming to you, and I have been prevented until the present time.

23 Yet truly now, having no other destination in these regions, and having already had a great desire to come to you over the past many years,

24 when I begin to set out on my journey to Spain, I hope that, as I pass by, I may see you, and I may be guided from there by you, after first having borne some fruit among you.

25 But next I will set out for Jerusalem, to minister to the saints.

26 For those of Macedonia and Achaia have decided to make a collection for those of the poor among the saints who are at Jerusalem.

27 And this has pleased them, because they are in their debt. For, since the Gentiles have become partakers of their spiritual things, they also ought to minister to them in worldly things.

28 Therefore, when I have completed this task, and have consigned to them this fruit, I shall set out, by way of you, to Spain.

29 And I know that when I come to you I shall arrive with an abundance of the blessings of the Gospel of Christ.

30 Therefore, I beg you, brothers, through our Lord Jesus Christ and though the love of the Holy Spirit, that you assist me with your prayers to God on my behalf,

31 so that I may be freed from the unfaithful who are in Judea, and so that the oblation of my service may be acceptable to the saints in Jerusalem.

32 So may I come to you with joy, through the will of God, and so may I be refreshed with you.

33 And may the God of peace be with you all. Amen.

Romans 16

1 Now I commend to you our sister Phoebe, who is in the ministry of the church, which is at Cenchreae,

2 so that you may receive her in the Lord with the worthiness of the saints, and so that you may be of assistance to her in whatever task she will have need of you. For she herself has also assisted many, and myself also.

3 Greet Prisca and Aquila, my helpers in Christ Jesus,

4 who have risked their own necks on behalf of my life, for whom I give thanks, not I alone, but also all the churches of the Gentiles;

5 and greet the church at their house. Greet Epaenetus, my beloved, who is among the first-fruits of Asia in Christ.

6 Greet Mary, who has labored much among you.

7 Greet Andronicus and Junias, my kinsmen and fellow captives, who are noble among the Apostles, and who were in Christ prior to me.

8 Greet Ampliatus, most beloved to me in the Lord.

9 Greet Urbanus, our helper in Christ Jesus, and Stachys, my beloved.

10 Greet Apelles, who has been tested in Christ.

11 Greet those who are from the household of Aristobulus. Greet Herodian, my kinsman. Greet those who are of the household of Narcissus, who are in the Lord.

12 Greet Tryphaena and Tryphosa, who labor in the Lord. Greet Persis, most beloved, who has labored much in the Lord.

13 Greet Rufus, elect in the Lord, and his mother and mine.

14 Greet Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermas, Patrobas, Hermes, and the brothers who are with them.

15 Greet Philologus and Julia, Nereus and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints who are with them.

16 Greet one another with a holy kiss. All the churches of Christ greet you.

17 But I beg you, brothers, to take note of those who cause dissensions and offenses contrary to the doctrine that you have learned, and to turn away from them.

18 For ones such as these do not serve Christ our Lord, but their inner selves, and, through pleasing words and skillful speaking, they seduce the hearts of the innocent.

19 But your obedience has been made known in every place. And so, I rejoice in you. But I want you to be wise in what is good, and simple in what is evil.

20 And may the God of peace quickly crush Satan under your feet. The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.

21 Timothy, my fellow laborer, greets you, and Lucius and Jason and Sosipater, my kinsmen.

22 I, Tertius, who wrote this epistle, greet you in the Lord.

23 Gaius, my host, and the entire church, greets you. Erastus, the treasurer of the city, greets you, and Quartus, a brother.

24 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.

25 But to him who is able to confirm you according to my Gospel and the preaching of Jesus Christ, in accord with the revelation of the mystery which has been hidden from time immemorial,

26 (which now has been made clear through the Scriptures of the Prophets, in accord with the precept of the eternal God, unto the obedience of faith) which has been made known among all the Gentiles:

27 to God, who alone is wise, through Jesus Christ, to him be honor and glory forever and ever. Amen.

1 Corinthians 1

1 Paul, called as an Apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God; and Sosthenes, a brother:

2 to the Church of God which is at Corinth, to those sanctified in Christ Jesus, called to be saints with all who are invoking the name of our Lord Jesus Christ in every place of theirs and of ours.

3 Grace and peace to you from God our Father and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

4 I give thanks to my God continuously for you because of the grace of God that has been given to you in Christ Jesus.

5 By that grace, in all things, you have become wealthy in him, in every word and in all knowledge.

6 And so, the testimony of Christ has been strengthened in you.

7 In this way, nothing is lacking to you in any grace, as you await the revelation of our Lord Jesus Christ.

8 And he, too, will strengthen you, even until the end, without guilt, until the day of the advent of our Lord Jesus Christ.

9 God is faithful. Through him, you have been called into the fellowship of his Son, Jesus Christ our Lord.

10 And so, I beg you, brothers, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that every one of you speak in the same way, and that there be no schisms among you. So may you become perfect, with the same mind and with the same judgment.

11 For it has been indicated to me, about you, my brothers, by those who are with Chloes, that there are contentions among you.

12 Now I say this because each of you is saying: "Certainly, I am of Paul;" "But I am of Apollo;" "Truly, I am of Cephas;" as well as: "I am of Christ."

13 Has Christ been divided? Was Paul crucified for you? Or were you baptized in the name of Paul?

14 I give thanks to God that I have baptized none of you, except Crispus and Gaius,

15 lest anyone say that you have been baptized in my name.

16 And I also baptized the household of Stephanus. Other than these, I do not recall if I baptized any others.

17 For Christ did not send me to baptize, but to evangelize: not through the wisdom of words, lest the cross of Christ become empty.

18 For the Word of the Cross is certainly foolishness to those who are perishing. But to those who have been saved, that is, to us, it is the power of God.

19 For it has been written: "I will perish the wisdom of the wise, and I will reject the discernment of the prudent."

20 Where are the wise? Where are the scribes? Where are the truth-seekers of this age? Has not God made the wisdom of this world into foolishness?

21 For the world did not know God through wisdom, and so, in the wisdom of God, it pleased God to accomplish the salvation of believers, through the foolishness of our preaching.

22 For the Jews ask for signs, and the Greeks seek wisdom.

23 But we are preaching Christ crucified. Certainly, to the Jews, this is a scandal, and to the Gentiles, this is foolishness.

24 But to those who have been called, Jews as well as Greeks, the Christ is the virtue of God and the wisdom of God.

25 For what is foolishness to God is considered wise by men, and that which is weakness to God is considered strong by men.

26 So take care of your vocation, brothers. For not many are wise according to the flesh, not many are powerful, not many are noble.

27 But God has chosen the foolish of the world, so that he may confound the wise. And God has chosen the weak of the world, so that he may confound the strong.

28 And God has chosen the ignoble and contemptible of the world, those who are nothing, so that he may reduce to nothing those who are something.

29 So then, nothing that is of the flesh should glory in his sight.

30 But you are of him in Christ Jesus, who was made by God to be our wisdom and justice and sanctification and redemption.

31 And so, in the same way, it was written: "Whoever glories, should glory in the Lord."